<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Books | ifdattic]]></title>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-17T15:09:14+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://ifdattic.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Marcinkevičius]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review of Node.js the Right Way Book]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/review-nodejs-right-way-book"/>
    <updated>2014-12-25T16:08:52+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/review-of-node-dot-js-the-right-way-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left <a" src="href="http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/51+VjuSvKJL._SL250_.jpg">http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/51+VjuSvKJL._SL250_.jpg</a>" title="&lsquo;Node.js the Right Way Book Cover&rsquo; &lsquo;Node.js the Right Way Book Cover&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m a big fan of learning something new. After enrolling into <a href="https://university.mongodb.com/courses/M101JS/about">MongoUniversity MongoDB course</a> where all the examples would be in Node.js, decided it would be great time to at least get acquainted with Node.js. Then as the luck would have it, someone tweeted about &ldquo;<a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00HSO6YD8/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B00HSO6YD8&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=if015-20&amp;linkId=2KSSTQD6Z2X2CDRS">Node.js The Right Way</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/hexlib">Jim. R. Wilson</a>&rdquo; from <a href="https://pragprog.com/book/jwnode/node-js-the-right-way">The Pragmatic Programmers</a>, which is always a great place to look for books. As the ebook version is available on Amazon (screw the discounts, I require my ebooks to be locked into the Amazon ecosystem), I bought it. Now I knew how I will be spending my mornings for a while.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The book is made from the following chapters:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Getting Started</strong> introduces the Node.js event loop, outlines the five aspects of Node.js development and provides instructions you would need for the following chapters.</li>
<li><strong>Wrangling the File System</strong> will help you write your first Node.js program &ndash; using Node&rsquo;s filesystem tools to create asynchronous, nonblocking file utilities.</li>
<li><strong>Networking with Sockets</strong> is were you will create a TCP servers and client programs for accessing them. This chapter will offer insight into Node application design and provide experience creating testable and fault-tolerant systems.</li>
<li><strong>Robust Message-Passing</strong> will introduce you to using third-party libraries. Using ØMQ (ZeroMQ) you will create suites of programs that work together in concert, and you will learn the clustering tools for managing them.</li>
<li><strong>Accessing Databases</strong> introduces databases and how to interact with them asynchronously in Node. The database created in this chapter is the foundation for RESTful APIs you&rsquo;ll be developing in later chapters.</li>
<li><strong>Scalable Web Services</strong> chapter will use Express, a popular Node.js web framework for routing requests. It will introduce objects called promises for managing asynchronous code flows and how to couple them in interesting ways with generator functions.</li>
<li><strong>Web Apps</strong> is the final chapter were you will build a single-page web application for integrating with web services created in previous chapters. In this chapter you will be using Passport module for authenticating with Google account credentials and storing session data in Redis.</li>
</ol>


<p>Each chapter provides some aspects of Node.js development like: Architecture and Core, Patterns, JavaScriptisms, Supporting Code.</p>

<p>A few issues (suggestions) for the book is that code samples could be more concise. It does not take any value away from them, but would just be nicer.</p>

<p>The database chapter requires a dataset which extracts to at least 500 MB (didn&rsquo;t wait for it to finish). My suggestion would be to provide a cropped dataset or simply add a note to kill the extraction at some point (just extract enough to make the examples work).</p>

<p>In my opinion it would be great if book provided a Vagrant or Docker file for having an environment which contains all the required software and working code examples.</p>

<p>The book has a very nice flow. Providing a lot of code examples and giving explanations for each line (block) of code. Still, you should have at least some JavaScript knowledge.</p>

<p>At the end of each chapter, questions and exercises are provided for improving your knowledge of what you learned from the chapter.</p>

<p>If you want to learn Node.js in my opinion this is the great book for that. It would provide you with enough knowledge where you will be confident to start using it in your everyday life and continue learning it through practice.</p>

<p>You can buy it from <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00HSO6YD8/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B00HSO6YD8&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=if015-20&amp;linkId=2KSSTQD6Z2X2CDRS">Amazon</a> or <a href="https://pragprog.com/book/jwnode/node-js-the-right-way">The Pragmatic Programmers</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review of SQL Performance Explained book]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/review-of-sql-performance-explained-book"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T09:36:33+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/review-of-sql-performance-explained-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the review of <strong>SQL Performance Explained</strong> book by <strong><a href="http://use-the-index-luke.com/about">Markus Winand</a></strong>. The book explains everything developers need to know about the SQL performance. And the only thing that developers need to learn is how to index <a href="http://www.commitstrip.com/en/2014/06/03/the-problem-is-not-the-tool-itself/">(comic strip explaining it)</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Below is the list of the chapters in a book:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Anatomy of an Index</strong> doesn&rsquo;t cover SQL specifically, but it explains the fundamental structure of an index.</li>
<li><strong>The Where Clause</strong> explains all aspects of the <code>where</code> clause. This is the biggest chapter in the book and after learning the techniques provided, you will be able to write much faster SQL.</li>
<li><strong>Performance and Scalability</strong> is about performance measurements and database scalability. It will explain why adding hardware is not the best solution to slow queries.</li>
<li><strong>The Join Operation</strong> gives explanation about how to use indexes to perform a fast table join.</li>
<li><strong>Clustering Data</strong> explains how to get best performance when selecting only part of columns.</li>
<li><strong>Sorting and Grouping</strong> is about how to use indexes with <code>order by</code> and <code>group by</code>.</li>
<li><strong>Partial Results</strong> explains how to benefit from a &ldquo;pipelined&rdquo; execution if you don&rsquo;t need the full result set.</li>
<li><strong>Insert, Delete and Update</strong> deals with performance when executing write queries.</li>
</ol>


<p>The book is very well written so once you start reading it it&rsquo;s not so easy to put it down. The examples are for Oracle database, but it also covers all other databases (MySQL, MSSQL, PostgreSQL) so any differences or things to know won&rsquo;t be left out for database you&rsquo;re using.</p>

<p>I had this book for a while, but constantly prioritized something else. I was really glad I finally read it and wish I did it earlier. I don&rsquo;t think I&rsquo;m a novice when it comes to SQL (at least I knew about SQL injections, indexes, etc.), but reading this book really expanded my knowledge about improving my SQL. If you&rsquo;re working with relational databases I would suggest to read this book sooner than later. Other examples are provided in different languages (PHP, Java, etc.), so you won&rsquo;t be left in the dark thinking where to start.</p>

<p>You can buy this book from <a href="http://sql-performance-explained.com/">SQL Performance Explained website</a> or paperback from <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Performance-Explained-Everything-Developers-about/dp/3950307826">Amazon</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review of Vagrant: Up and Running book]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/review-of-vagrant-up-and-running-book"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T19:35:14+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/review-of-vagrant-up-and-running-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the review of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1449335837/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1449335837&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=if015-20">Vagrant: Up and Running by Mitchell Hashimoto</a>. The book gets you started with using <a href="http://www.vagrantup.com">Vagrant</a>. Vagrant allows you to create environments which can be similar or exactly like the environment your application will run on then it reaches the production stage.<!-- more --> Have you ever had a situation where application works perfectly on your Windows environment, but when you push it to Linux server you get errors, because you have a case typo in your code? Or how about when you need some third-party library and installation on Windows is as simple as building an Eiffel Tower, and even then, documentation says it might not work on Windows? Or maybe you&rsquo;re working on a few projects which require different PHP versions? Sounds familiar? Well, this is where Vagrant is going to help you, especially with &ldquo;<em>works on my machine</em>&rdquo; bugs.</p>

<p>All the bugs described above can really get on your nerves, especially if the deadline is already nibbling at your fingers, and the last thing you need is some bug running around, having a party at your expense. So I was thinking about starting to use manually created virtual machines which have their own cons, so I was putting this away <em>for &ldquo;tomorrow&rdquo;</em> for some time. And recently I learned about Vagrant, which sounded like a perfect way to get rid of a couple headaches and work more professionally. I just wish I found about it sooner, because it&rsquo;s very easy to start using it, doesn&rsquo;t take forever to configure, if you mess something up it&rsquo;s easy to start over, and my application will be running on the environment which is the same or similar to the production environment.</p>

<p>So, I was about to hit the Vagrant documentation when I found that this book was available to read an on-line version for free (some kind of promotion or something like that). And because I like reading (and books) which led to this review.</p>

<p>Vagrant: Up and Running is very well written, so it was a pleasure to read it. Most of the time it actually didn&rsquo;t feel like you&rsquo;re reading a technical book, it felt more like you asked a colleague or a friend to teach Vagrant to you (just hope it&rsquo;s not someone like me as I&rsquo;m not very good at explaining, probably should work on that a bit).</p>

<p>The book has clear topics with progressive tasks, code examples, code results and notes. This allows you to read again any topic for reference without the need to re-read a previous topic, but you still need to have a least some understanding of what was done before (it would be hard to provision a virtual machine if you don&rsquo;t know how to start it first). There are also a couple of images to help you along the way. Of course it&rsquo;s nice sometimes to see something else than just a bunch of &ldquo;letter monsters&rdquo;, but in my opinion the chosen images are not that useful (image of two words command, which gives three words output feels a bit like a waste of space/money/bytes/etc.).</p>

<p>If you want to follow the examples when you&rsquo;re reading the book, Internet connection is a must. You can download Vagrant, VirtualBox and a vagrant box beforehand, but as soon as you reach the provisioning of the virtual machine it will be impossible to follow the examples without Internet. Also unless you have a blazingly fast connection, you might want to jump around the book a little bit. If it feels like something that needs to be downloaded is coming up, I would suggest skipping a bit, start the download and go back to continue reading while it&rsquo;s downloading. This way you won&rsquo;t end waiting until it is possible to continue reading.</p>

<p>The book is made from the following chapters:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>An Introduction to Vagrant</strong> &ndash; provides information why you should be using Vagrant, the alternatives to Vagrant, and full installation with setup. The installation is provided for Windows, Linux, Mac OS X so no matter which OS you&rsquo;re using there will be no need for figuring out how it&rsquo;s installed.</li>
<li><strong>Your First Vagrant Machine</strong> &ndash; is where you end running a vagrant machine (two commands &amp; that&rsquo;s it, I&rsquo;m not lying). Of course the chapter won&rsquo;t leave you hanging. It will provide extensive explanations about <em>Vagrantfile</em> (configuration file), how to configure your machine, and what to do with your machine once the work is done and it&rsquo;s time to relax.</li>
<li><strong>Provisioning Your Vagrant VM</strong> &ndash; explains about virtual machine provisioning (how to do it manually or automatically). An empty running machine probably won&rsquo;t be very useful without needed software so the chapter explains how to provision your machine through <em>SSH</em>, <em>shell</em>, <em>Chef</em>, <em>Puppet</em>. It also has some other information you might need for provisioning.</li>
<li><strong>Networking in Vagrant</strong> &ndash; the chapter is about how to configure Vagrant virtual machine so it could communicate with a host and/or other devices.</li>
<li><strong>Modeling Multimachine Clusters</strong> &ndash; shows how to configure Vagrant to use multiple machines. This is especially useful if you work in the cloud where web/db/cache/etc. is on different machines. This will allow you to get close to your production environment (helping to get rid of &ldquo;works on my machine&rdquo; bugs), and you will be able to test in a controllable environment, what will happen if one of machines goes down.</li>
<li><strong>Boxes</strong> &ndash; is a chapter about Vagrant boxes. You will learn about boxes in general, how to manage them and how to create them from an existing environment or completely from scratch.</li>
<li><strong>Extending Vagrant with Plug-Ins</strong> &ndash; is quite a long chapter about managing and creating Vagrant plug-ins. But unless you know <em>Ruby</em> and think about creating plug-ins, you won&rsquo;t lose (just save a lot of time) anything skipping the whole chapter after the plug-in management section.</li>
<li><strong>Appendix A/B</strong> &ndash; is two appendix chapters giving some information about Vagrant variables for quick reference.</li>
</ul>


<p>The book takes about <em>11 hours</em> to finish. This of course will depend on your reading speed, how long you will play with the code and a couple more things.</p>

<p>Now, would I suggest reading it? I actually not sure.. It&rsquo;s a nice book which I really enjoyed reading, and it will get you up and ready for using Vagrant for your projects, but in my opinion you can easily get it just from reading the documentation. Vagrant documentation is really good, without circling about the same topic for ages, and in couple hours of reading and playing around you would be just as ready to use Vagrant as with the book. Also, something that really got on my nerves while reading the book was that the book wasn&rsquo;t released that long ago, but it uses version 1 of configuration while <code>vagrant init</code> gives you Vagrantfile in version 2. Of course Vagrant is made in a way which allows to use any configuration version together, but it&rsquo;s not fun jumping around (and plug-ins chapter goes with V2, because otherwise it won&rsquo;t work).</p>

<p>Even if a documentation is good enough, you might want to get this book for different reasons. For example if you have some free time while taking a train to work. It would be a great chance to put yourself on &ldquo;<em>the next level</em>&rdquo;. Also, I know a lot of people hate reading ebooks or documentations on-line, so getting a paper book would be a great investment. Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, I love paper books, but just not then the topic is technical, it&rsquo;s just no fun trying to juggle an open book and typing an example at the same time.</p>

<p>That I do know is that if you&rsquo;re a programmer, you definitely won&rsquo;t lose if you will learn Vagrant. Especially when there are services like <a href="https://puphpet.com">PuPHPet</a> which allows you to create virtual machines using a simple GUI.</p>

<p>You can buy this book from <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1449335837/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1449335837&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=if015-20">Amazon</a> or <a href="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920026358.do">O'Reilly</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review of Yii Application Development Cookbook SE book]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/review-of-yii-application-development-cookbook-se-book"/>
    <updated>2013-06-02T23:53:41+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/review-of-yii-application-development-cookbook-se-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the review of <strong>Yii Application Development Cookbook (Second Edition)</strong> book by <strong><a href="http://rmcreative.ru/author">Alexander Makarov</a></strong>. The cookbook covers practical Yii application development tips which will help you develop better applications, and it also has recipes for important Yii features which are very useful to know.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This isn&rsquo;t the first time I read Yii Application Development Cookbook. The first time I read it was then it was still in per-order (the first edition), and because it was such a good book I was already thinking about reading it for the second time after I finish reading <a href="http://yii.larryullman.com/index.php">The Yii Book by Larry Ullman</a> (which by the way you should pre-order, at the end of the review I will explain why). So when I found that a second edition is coming out and got my hands of a review copy I was quite happy.</p>

<p>The book is written by Alexander Makarov who is an experienced engineer from Russia and has been a Yii framework core team member since 2010. He also was the technical reviewer for three other books related to Yii, so you can be sure the cookbook is written by someone who knows inner workings of Yii framework.</p>

<p>The cookbook has a similar format to other PacktPub cookbooks and is easy to follow, but you should have at least a basic understanding on how Yii framework works before starting with recipes (<a href="http://www.yiiframework.com/doc/guide">The Definitive Guide to Yii</a> is a good place to start). The recipes are split into 13 chapters that will show you how to use Yii efficiently.</p>

<p>Every recipe is split into smaller sections (depending on the recipe some sections might be missing):</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Introduction</em> &ndash; explanation about the recipe, what it solves or any other information that might be needed.</li>
<li><em>Getting ready</em> &ndash; contains instructions how to make this recipe work (e.g., setting up new application or database tables needed for a recipe).</li>
<li><em>How to do it</em> &ndash; is a step by step instructions of recipe code.</li>
<li><em>How it works</em> &ndash; gives a fuller explanation of the recipe code and how it works.</li>
<li><em>There&rsquo;s more</em> &ndash; instructions about how the recipe can be improved or expanded. It also contains URLs for further information about the subject.</li>
<li><em>See also</em> &ndash; a list of similar recipes about the topic.</li>
</ul>


<p>The cookbook contains 90 recipes (if my finger counting is correct) and covers a wide range of topics. Recipes could be categorized in: simple recipes (you&rsquo;re probably already using them), advanced (or good to know) recipes, complex recipes (which will need more fiddling around to completely understand how they work) and recipes which will make you question yourself &ldquo;Why the hell I&rsquo;m not using this in my application?&rdquo;. Some recipes will feel like a duplicates because the topic was more or less covered in another recipe. I also think that a couple more recipes would have made the book a lot more &ldquo;stronger&rdquo; (like a dedicated recipe for caching just a part of your application).</p>

<p>Below is the list of the chapters in a cookbook:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Under the Hood</strong> provides information about the most interesting Yii features. Even if you already have some experience with Yii framework you might not know about them or might not be sure how exactly they work. A couple of features covered in this chapter: events, import, autoloading, exceptions, components, widget configuration.</li>
<li><strong>Router, Controller, and Views</strong> is about how to connect different parts of the framework to make a good application. Recipes will explain how to use pretty URLs, how to write reusable actions, views and other handy things.</li>
<li><strong>AJAX and jQuery</strong> focuses on adding jQuery and JavaScript functionality to your application. The chapter is about Yii specific tricks and will explain how to render the content on the client side, manage assets and a couple more useful things.</li>
<li><strong>Working with Forms</strong> shows how Yii works with forms which is a big part of any application. The chapter will explain how to write custom validators, handle file uploads and create custom input widgets.</li>
<li><strong>Testing Your Application</strong> covers unit testing, functional testing and code coverage reports. Recipes follow a test-driven development approach and will explain how to set your environment and start writing your own tests. This is a very important chapter because as soon as your application starts to grow the chance of breaking something is rising, and it can lead to a lot of problems.</li>
<li><strong>Database, Active Record, and Model Tricks</strong> is about working with databases efficiently. It will explain how to get data from the database using Active Record, query builder and SQL. It will explain which method is best used for which scenario. The chapter also has recipes for how to connect to more than one database, how to use scopes, create complex queries along with a few more tricks.</li>
<li><strong>Using Zii Components</strong> covers the default Yii framework widgets which help you work with your data.</li>
<li><strong>Extending Yii</strong> shows how to create widgets, actions, modules, filters, commands which would be useful for your applications and community (if you decide to share them).</li>
<li><strong>Error Handling, Debugging, and Logging</strong> explains how to configure your application to help you as much as possible when the time comes to catch and fix some nasty bug.</li>
<li><strong>Security</strong> provides information how to make your application follow security principle &ldquo;filter input, escape output&rdquo;. Recipes will explain how to use filters, how to use role-based access control, prevent XSS, CSRF, and SQL injections.</li>
<li><strong>Performance Tuning</strong> will show how to make your application run smoothly until you start getting very high loads.</li>
<li><strong>Using External Code</strong> will explain how to use third-party code in you applications. It&rsquo;s very easy to use third-party stand-alone libraries or libraries from other frameworks and the recipes in this chapter will show different ways how to do it.</li>
<li><strong>Deployment</strong> gives various tips that are useful for then you&rsquo;re ready to deploy your application.</li>
</ol>


<p>The book takes about 13 hours to finish. This of course will depend on your reading speed, how long you will play with the code and a couple more things.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re serious about learning Yii framework you should definitely buy this book. Even if you already have a good understanding of Yii framework I&rsquo;m sure you will find recipes which will make you even better. Of course if you&rsquo;re just thinking about learning Yii framework you shouldn&rsquo;t start with this book. Here&rsquo;s my suggestion I always give for anyone wanting to learn Yii framework. You should start with <a href="http://www.yiiframework.com/doc/guide">The Definitive Guide to Yii</a> (if you don&rsquo;t feel like investing into a book before you&rsquo;re sure Yii framework is for you) or <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00A9TUK8E/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00A9TUK8E&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=if015-20">Web Application Development with Yii and PHP by Jeffrey Winesett</a> or <a href="http://yii.larryullman.com/index.php">The Yii Book by Larry Ullman</a>. I would definitely suggest to get &ldquo;<em>The Yii Book</em>&rdquo; because it&rsquo;s a great book for newcomers to Yii framework. The book is still in pre-order but so far from that I read it&rsquo;s a great book. And a big plus is that your book will be upgraded after it will be updated for Yii 2 version, so you get two rabbits with one stone (because birds are too small for a nice meal). After that you should already have a good understanding about Yii framework and be able to develop applications with it, but to make them really great and get a better understanding of Yii you should read <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00BKZHDGS/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00BKZHDGS&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=if015-20">Yii Application Development Cookbook by Alexander Makarov</a>. Or if you still don&rsquo;t feel like investing into your future as a web developer then you can go start reading wiki articles, documentation and dissecting Yii source code. There is also a <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00ATYE3WI/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00ATYE3WI&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=if015-20">Yii Rapid Application Development Hotshot</a> book, which I personally haven&rsquo;t read, but my logic puts it as an optional book if you&rsquo;re still not confident enough about starting to develop great applications using Yii framework. Also, Yii framework has a great and friendly community so even if you get stuck somewhere, someone will help you out.</p>

<p>You can buy this book from <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00BKZHDGS/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B00BKZHDGS&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=if015-20">Amazon</a> or <a href="http://www.packtpub.com/yii-application-development-cookbook-2nd-edition/book">PacktPub</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review of jQuery Hotshot book]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/review-of-jquery-hotshot-book"/>
    <updated>2013-05-13T00:50:23+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/review-of-jquery-hotshot-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This was the first I read something from the <em>Packt Hotshot</em> series, so I wasn&rsquo;t sure what to expect. For those who haven&rsquo;t tried this series let me explain a bit about them. All of this is more or less logical assumption by checking the table of contents for other books in the series (it&rsquo;s just a way my mind works, I take small pieces of information and then try to connect them together, much more fun and keeps cogs in my head sharp).<!-- more --> In my opinion <em>Hotshot</em> books are somewhere between regular books (where you have a project an add more features with every chapter) and cookbooks (where you have a bunch of recipes to expand your project). Hotshot books give you a few projects (it varies but mostly 8 or 10) concentrating on some topic, but the end result is a project which with a few more additions can be made to a production application. The books have an interesting format by splitting the projects into sub-chapters like <em>Mission Briefing</em>, <em>Mission Accomplished</em>, <em>Classified Intel</em> and tasks to complete for each project. If you have a mind which manufacturer forgot to refurbish (yes I&rsquo;m pointing at you mother Nature) or an overflowing imagination, the learning can be very fun. Just image you&rsquo;re a secret agent disarming an atomic bomb by sliding a puzzle or a cowboy ready to show his skills by gunning down a few bounties on Stack Overflow, or whatever rocks your boat. At the end of each project there is a few ideas provided how it can be expanded, but it&rsquo;s left for the reader to add those changes (even after finishing school homework keeps following you around).</p>

<p>OK, lets get back to the book. The book starts with a common stuff like reviewers, introductions, conventions, errata and so on. So if you have read a Packt book before and itching for knowledge you might skip to the first project.</p>

<p>The book is very well written and easy to follow, so if you decide to type the code yourself, you will have no problems knowing how the files should be named or where to add new code. But you will probably want to download the source code as most of the projects use common stylesheet, images or some other assets (or you will have to get creative, it&rsquo;s always possible to find a way around then you need it). Code is easy to understand with detailed explanations after each task, but if you never tried <em>jQuery</em> before, you probably should read a book or a few tutorials about basics of jQuery.</p>

<p>jQuery Hotshot book has the following projects:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Sliding Puzzle</strong> &ndash; shows how to build a sliding puzzle game using jQuery &amp; jQuery UI (draggable). It also adds a sprinkle of <code>localStorage</code> API for keeping some data and explains a Fisher-Yates shuffle algorithm for randomizing puzzle pieces. We will probably see a big jump of sliding puzzle games in Facebook from now on.</li>
<li><strong>A Fixed Position Sidebar with Animated Scrolling</strong> &ndash; is a project which improves user interface by adding a fixed navigation. The project focus is on CSS, events (like <code>hashchange</code>, <code>scroll</code>, <code>resize</code>) and animations. The page scrolls to the last position after reload for improved usability.</li>
<li><strong>An Interactive Google Map</strong> &ndash; creates an interactive map using <strong>Google Maps API</strong>. Some of the tasks covered in a project: creating a map, adding markers, adding info window, getting an address and calculating a distance between two points. In my opinion in this day and age with geolocation and powerful smartphones, learning how to use Google Maps API is a must, as it can be used in your application to make it interactive for the end users.</li>
<li><strong>A jQuery Mobile Single-page App</strong> &ndash; introduces you to jQuery Mobile framework. If you think about making a mobile application you should definitely give jQuery Mobile a try. Project gives you an intro into how to structure your mobile application, how to get data from <strong>Stack Exchange API</strong> and then how to use <strong>JsRender</strong> template engine.</li>
<li><strong>jQuery File Uploader</strong> &ndash; creates a configurable jQuery plugin which will let you to upload files to your server using AJAX. Project uses jQuery for file uploads, jQuery UI for progressbar widget and HTML5 for working with files. The project concentrates on what can be done, so it will not work on all browsers and these tasks are left for the reader to implement. It&rsquo;s a great starting point if you want to create your own file uploader or just learn how they work.</li>
<li><strong>Extending Chrome with jQuery</strong> &ndash; explains how to create a Chrome browser extension. During the project you create an extension which collects microdata from pages and uses <code>localStorage</code> for saving to make something similar to the address book. I found this project quite interesting and probably will have to look for more information about this topic as it opens a lot of new ways for applying your web development knowledge.</li>
<li><strong>Build Your Own jQuery</strong> &ndash; takes you through steps of building a custom version of jQuery. At first it explains how to install (instructions are for Mac and Windows) required tools which includes <strong>Git</strong>, <strong>Node.js</strong>, <strong>Grunt.js</strong> and <strong>QUnit</strong>. After you have all the requisites the project shows how to build a custom jQuery version from source. You might be wondering what is the point then only a few clicks are needed to download it from a website, or even better, one copy-paste routine later your project already loads it from CDN. Well I haven&rsquo;t had a chance to use this for a project, but I started using dependency manager for PHP and it&rsquo;s bliss then after one command you have all the needed packages with the latest version.</li>
<li><strong>Infinite Scrolling with jQuery</strong> &ndash; explains how to add another user interface feature &ndash; <em>infinite scrolling</em>. Adding this feature to your projects is very easy and takes only a few lines of code. Most of the project in the book is spent explaining how to get data from <em>YouTube</em> using AJAX. After all the rendering is done so page will have enough content for infinite scrolling to make sense the code to create a scroller is added.</li>
<li><strong>A jQuery Heat Map</strong> &ndash; is split into two parts. The first one is for JavaScript which collects the clicks of visited pages. The second part focuses on explaining how to process collected information and display it for the administrator. To save time and space most of the project is from JavaScript side so you will have to make your own responsive design and server side code (or use the one included in the source code). This project can be really useful if you&rsquo;re thinking about collecting some analytical information about how your users interact with a website/application.</li>
<li><strong>A Sortable, Paged Table with Knockout.js</strong> &ndash; shows how to build a dynamic application which stays in sync with data. This project uses <strong>Knockout.js</strong> which is an MVVM (Model-View-View Model) framework. A great thing about using Knockout.js is what your data and UI always stays in sync, so if you change your data, UI will automatically update itself (it also works the other way around). If you&rsquo;re are thinking about creating a dynamic application it would be really useful to get a better understanding of it and you won&rsquo;t need to write scripts for DOM manipulations and getting server side rendered content through AJAX.</li>
</ol>


<p>So it&rsquo;s time for a verdict, as you&rsquo;re probably already feeling bad that a cup of tea which you made before starting to read this review is getting cold in the kitchen. So should you buy it? In my opinion it will depend on your JavaScript/jQuery skills. If you&rsquo;re already a JavaScript guru/ninja/or whatever the latest swear word is, you&rsquo;re probably not reading this review anyway. Because if your knowledge is big enough not to trip on the tricky JavaScript parts, you&rsquo;re probably already plucking the benefits of using plain JavaScript. If you&rsquo;re jQuery master you might not find this book challenging enough. Of course maybe you had thoughts about learning something this book covers (for example jQuery Mobile or Chrome extensions) so you might consider to get this book for those topics. If your knowledge of jQuery is on the advanced or beginner level it might be worth to get this book. jQuery Hotshot book covers a wide range of topics which are interesting an can greatly expand your skillset. The book is very easy to follow so you won&rsquo;t catch yourself checking your Facebook status because you got bored from endless pages of text going round and round about the same thing. And if you still haven&rsquo;t given jQuery a chance I would suggest first to start with a book (or tutorials) which explains the inner workings of jQuery and then return to this book.</p>

<p>You can buy this book from <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/1849519102/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=1849519102&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=if015-20">Amazon</a> or <a href="http://www.packtpub.com/jquery-hotshot/book">PacktPub</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
