<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Bucket List | ifdattic]]></title>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/categories/bucket-list/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-26T11:27:47+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://ifdattic.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Marcinkevičius]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fighting Your Fears: Triple Combo - Flower Girl]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/fighting-your-fears-triple-combo-flower-girl"/>
    <updated>2014-09-24T19:12:18+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/fighting-your-fears-triple-combo-flower-girl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today (2014-09-19), I hit a triple headshot on my &ldquo;did for the first time checklist.&rdquo; It was: gift someone flowers, ask for a name first, tell random girl she&rsquo;s amiable (I like the word translation in Lithuanian more so from now on in English &ldquo;cute&rdquo; will be used).</p>

<p>Today was planed as the day off cause after an eye doctor visit I was not supposed to see anything (blind as a rabbit who doesn&rsquo;t eat carrots). Spent hours just walking in the sun, listening to audio books (activity I enjoy as it allows me to disconnect), relaxing.</p>

<p>While walking through a shopping center in a flower section noticed a girl and kept walking (I look at walking like a shark looks at swimming &ndash; <em>you stop, you die</em>).</p>

<p>But one of the voices in my head went <em>&ldquo;she&rsquo;s cute&rdquo;</em> and another replied <em>&ldquo;yea, as she is working in a flower shop it might be fun to ask for her suggestion of what to gift to a cute girl and then give it to her.&rdquo;</em> The previous voice replied with <em>&ldquo;sure, sure, we definitely should do it&rdquo;</em>, but you know in that tone were someone agrees with you, but deep inside they are praying you won&rsquo;t take them on their offer.</p>

<p>Fortunately, during the past year, the voice which tries to throw me out of my comfort zone received much more control.</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Wait, is this idea making you uncomfortable?&rdquo;</em> Putting a hand on my chest, noticing the heart beating much faster. <em>&ldquo;It does! Oh, I will have so much fun making you do this!&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>As I had a few minutes, before circling back to a flower shop, the first voice started to try haggle his way out (<em>&ldquo;You know, I&rsquo;m not feeling so well right now, maybe next time?&rdquo;</em>) or bribing the heart into a heart attack, but all of it was met with a bored reaction <em>&ldquo;take the last deep breath if you want, but you&rsquo;re doing this.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>A deep breath, and I start looking at flowers.</p>

<p>The girl: <em>&ldquo;Hello, have you chosen something?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Me: <em>&ldquo;Hello. I don&rsquo;t know. What you would suggest to gift to a cute girl?&rdquo;.</em></p>

<p>Girl: <em>&ldquo;Uh, these are nice, and these, also this one.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Me: <em>&ldquo;This one looks nice, colorful. I will take it.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Girl: <em>&ldquo;Should I wrap them?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Me: <em>&ldquo;Sure. I will pay with a card.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>I think this is the part where <em>The Universe</em> came in with a bucket of popcorns and went <em>&ldquo;Oh, let&rsquo;s extend this awkward period where he is running all the terrible scenarios of how it could end.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Card payment problems..</p>

<p>Girl: <em>&ldquo;Can you pay in cash? We had some problems with card payments recently.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Me: <em>&ldquo;Sure. How much was it? Here you go.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Me standing like an idiot, waiting for her to finish with cash register and the second voice standing with a grin.</p>

<p>Translation is a bit rough from this point, but it&rsquo;s as close as I could get.</p>

<p>Me: <em>&ldquo;And let me gift these flowers to you.&rdquo;</em> (✓ gift someone flowers).</p>

<p>Girl: <em>&ldquo;What?! Why?!.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Me: <em>&ldquo;Cause you&rsquo;re cute and my mind thought &ndash; Let&rsquo;s gift some flowers to this cute girl.&rdquo;</em> (combo ✓ tell random girl she&rsquo;s cute).</p>

<p>I end up in goofy situations (don&rsquo;t ask for examples, because I will provide them), but I was starting to think of a much more comfortable things I could be doing right now, like running barefoot through broken glass.</p>

<p>Girl (while smiling, laughing and probably feeling much more uncomfortably than me): <em>&ldquo;**Random combination of: Really? Why? No. What? and a bunch of other words** Is this a prank or something like it?&rdquo;</em> [Oh come on! Stop extending this, just let me run to hide into some dark corner. Note: order hiding lessons from a cockroach].</p>

<p>Me: <em>&ldquo;No, a gift, for real.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>At this point I think the voices in my head were starting a movie night as a new one went (in English accent) <em>&ldquo;Come on, we already have a combo, let&rsquo;s check off something else, ask her for her name!&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Deep breath, a shift in position to make sure I&rsquo;m still standing.</p>

<p>Me: <em>&ldquo;What is your name?&rdquo;</em> (triple combo ✓ ask for a name first).</p>

<p>Girl: <em>&ldquo;**:insert name here:**&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Me: <em>&ldquo;Pleased, Andrius.&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Could have tried to continue the combo and do something else for the first time, but as you should be careful with a cornered animal (he has nothing to lose so his reaction is unpredictable), it felt like a good time to allow the opening.</p>

<p>Made my smile bigger (<a href="http://blog.bufferapp.com/the-science-of-smiling-a-guide-to-humans-most-powerful-gesture">research</a> says: you smile not because you&rsquo;re happy, but you are happy because you smile. So, I try to walk around with a smile. I might look like an idiot, but I think it works), said <em>&ldquo;Have a nice weekend&rdquo;</em> and backed off.</p>

<p>Checked my heartbeat (reflection stage) which was more or less back at normal.. At this point my imagination (another daemon roaming in my head) tells <em>&ldquo;I don&rsquo;t think your heart was beating during that challenge&rdquo;</em> and a flash of red lights blinking, alarm sounds blaring, blood cells running in panic and a heart shouting <em>&ldquo;How is it going!?! I&rsquo;m ready to give him a heart attack right away!&rdquo;</em> (OK, this video made me chuckle).</p>

<p>A pat on the head from a second voice followed by some wise words <em>&ldquo;Good boy. See, that wasn&rsquo;t so bad. After all, what is the worst that could happen?&rdquo;</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
