<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | ifdattic]]></title>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-06-24T07:35:17+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://ifdattic.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Marcinkevičius]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review of ZivaMind Meditation Course]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/review-zivamind-meditation-course"/>
    <updated>2015-06-18T14:29:48+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/review-of-zivamind-meditation-course</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If I notice something to be continuously mentioned, it might have some truth to it. When looking into that top performers (like <a href="http://fourhourworkweek.com/2015/02/02/arnold-schwarzenegger/">Tim Ferriss, Arnold Schwarzenegger</a>, etc.) do, most of the time the meditation is mentioned. <strong>As I would like to be top performer after I grow up meditation is something I want to have as a habit</strong>. Had a powerful experience once so know it can be a powerful tool.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/18736614889" title="Review of ZivaMind Meditation Course by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/308/18736614889_f916ca658e_z.jpg" width="640" height="320" alt="Review of ZivaMind Meditation Course"></a></p>

<p>The problem is what I&rsquo;m <strong>having problems finding one which would work for me</strong>. Most of them are spiritual. With some hairy guru, flowers and other elements which should bring peace &amp; bliss. For me the line between spiritual enough &amp; too spiritual is thin. I have nothing against it &amp; I&rsquo;m happy if it works for other people. For me, it makes me cringe. Just like the word God. (I like using it when cursing. Don&rsquo;t put any weight to it as it means nothing to me. Might throw away a great book just for using that word too much.) To give some anchor point to me even <a href="https://www.headspace.com/">Headspace application</a> is too spiritual. Just can&rsquo;t stomach that guru voice, it&rsquo;s me not you.</p>

<p>Another problem is what I always <strong>had problems keeping meditating for long</strong>. Would start strong, do it every day for a week or two. Then I will have a day or few where &ldquo;<em>I have no time</em>&rdquo; for it. Or the cheating will start making it more like a nap.</p>

<p>One day watched a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zC7a_gQB9YQ">Google talk with an Emily Fletcher about meditation</a>. Maybe her &ldquo;positivity&rdquo; was a bit too much. I don&rsquo;t like that in people. Think it&rsquo;s because if you took a scalpel deep enough into my brains you will find it&rsquo;s because I&rsquo;m not like that &amp; would love to be. A lot of points in the talk made sense to me.</p>

<p>After looking more into what Emily does decided to try her <a href="http://www.zivamind.com/">ZivaMind meditation course</a>. <strong>If you fail, try again</strong>.</p>

<p>The course isn&rsquo;t cheap (250$ at the time of purchase). But it&rsquo;s only if it wouldn&rsquo;t work, if it works that price would be a drop in the bucket.</p>

<p><strong>It&rsquo;s delivered in 8 days with some extras added</strong>. Some of the days you&rsquo;re asked to answer few questions to bring your awareness. Don&rsquo;t think that you only need 8 days to become a master and start flying around on your bliss. This is the time you will need to consume the lessons to be in position to continue the meditation practice by yourself. After 8 days you might still have a lot of questions. A lot of them are answered in a recorded call(s) (day 9 of course).</p>

<p>The great thing about the course I liked is that <strong>it almost has no spiritual stuff</strong>. It has the mantra which I will put in spiritual category. I don&rsquo;t mind it so much as it&rsquo;s used as a tool to anchor yourself when you start wondering too much. Found it helpful.</p>

<p><strong>I like delivery of course a lot</strong>. Like explaining that you don&rsquo;t need to do it for hours or become a monk to reap the benefits of meditation. It helps to calm yourself knowing that 15 minutes twice a day is something you can do. Of course if it won&rsquo;t work then meditation is out the window as becoming a monk won&rsquo;t help either. <strong>Showing how a meditation session might look is very helpful</strong>. After seeing it you stop beating yourself that you&rsquo;re doing it wrong or you will never be able to do it right or you think too much, etc.</p>

<p>The website application of the course could be better. For someone who works in web &amp; cares about security, receiving his password in email can lead to a heart attack. It doesn&rsquo;t remember that I have logged in so every day requires me to log back in.</p>

<p>A new day of meditation is enabled every 24 hours. Which I understand but don&rsquo;t think is a good choice. I think it would be better if a new one was made available after 16 hours. For first few days it wasn&rsquo;t an issue. After that I started waking up early and a new day wasn&rsquo;t available to me. Just make the change on the application, it&rsquo;s fine if mails are sent every 24 hours. And if someone is counting the end of 16 hours just to check the new video they have bigger problems.</p>

<p>One of the days contained a video about space. Have no efing idea what it was about or what it has to do with meditation. Some spiritual thought provoking time &ndash; yes, but I would rather it was not added.</p>

<p>In one video you&rsquo;re taught a breathing technique to help you meditate. Unfortunately, I can&rsquo;t do it. As someone who has only one nostril working most of the time, anything breathing related is uncomfortably painful. If you have never drowned, choked, suffocated &mdash; yes, I&rsquo;m that good at accidental suicides &mdash; it would be hard to explain the feeling.</p>

<p>The course provides audio files to help meditate for various reasons: sleep, travel, performance. They are helpful, but from that I noticed they have white noise during silent periods which makes it hard to concentrate. It could also have lite versions which contained less explanations (explanations are good for beginning). <strong>The video version of 15 minute meditation I found very helpful</strong>. Most of it is silence, but that I liked about them is that I don&rsquo;t have to keep eyes on the clock. Having a timer application running is not a problem. It&rsquo;s just a better quality meditation if I keep my eyes closed through it. It would be great if audio version of this was available (without white noise).</p>

<p><strong>The suggestion to use the last few minutes of meditation for gratitude is great</strong>. I have a habit of being grateful for 3 things each day, big or small. Makes you appreciate your life &amp; what you have a lot more. Those few minutes were I run through all the things that happened &amp; I&rsquo;m grateful for makes me even happier.</p>

<p>I just started the course &amp; need to keep it for longer to know if it works. So far my thoughts are positive and feeling good with sticking with it. Doubt that I will find anything better &amp; if it won&rsquo;t work then the problem is somewhere else. <strong>If like me you have problems with making meditation a habit I would suggest to try out the <a href="http://www.zivamind.com/">ZivaMind meditation course</a></strong>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - Phone STD &amp; Parks (part 2) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks"/>
    <updated>2015-06-03T08:55:35+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks-part-2-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After taking an inventory of what happened so far decided now was the time to:</p>

<ul>
<li>check where to find the places suggested by the host (shops, restaurants, etc.);</li>
<li>buy the local SIM card for internet;</li>
<li>get something to eat.</li>
</ul>


<p>I was in no hurry to start going through museums and similar places. I was here for two weeks and decided to spend the weekend just exploring the city. Also after I move to another place I will receive the museum card from my host, saving me some money &amp; time.</p>

<p>After a while I went inside one shop which looked like they were selling SIM cards. If you want to imagine the conversation better the merchant was Indian (like Russell Peters said &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t make stereotypes, I see them&rdquo;).</p>

<p>&ldquo;Hi, I would like a local SIM card with a data plan, do you have any?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Hi, yes, it will be 20 € please. What model is your phone?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;The Nexus 5 <em>*confused with a raised eyebrow*</em>, does it make any difference?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;I never had Nexus, I can do Apple, Samsung, Nokia. Here are the instructions how to install it. I don&rsquo;t know if it will work on your phone.&rdquo;</p>

<p>After some haggling we decided to try and if it will work, I will pay. If it will not work he will take the card back and I will not need to pay. Good deal, <em>I have nothing to lose after all, or so I thought</em>. After changing the card and rebooting the phone the language automatically changed to Dutch (without asking me about it), started installing some apps and if you enter the settings (to change the language or enable WiFi) the application would just close down. WTF?!? <em>I wasn&rsquo;t expecting my phone catching an STD</em>. I had doubts about myself, who knows were I might end sticking my USB stick in, but I didn&rsquo;t expect this happening to my phone. Thanked the shop keeper for trying and left without local SIM card.</p>

<p>Continued to keep going down the street as somewhere around here was a park (I love green &amp; blue colors on maps). At the same time trying to figure out how to at least change the language to English. What I found is what if you restart the phone you have about few seconds of browsing the settings app before it&rsquo;s closed. Not an easy task to change something in few seconds when you don&rsquo;t even know where it is. After a while I just gave up as this was unsustainable. Restarting the phone took about a minute and it provides only a few seconds which probably won&rsquo;t be enough. Another problem was what I was kind of lost, the GPS/maps application was in Dutch and without any cache. <em>The easy way would be just to go back, which is boring</em>. After calculating the direction I should move to I continued my travels.</p>

<p><a href="http://ifdattic.smugmug.com/2016-June-Amsterdam/i-QWZNbnT/A" title=""><img src="http://ifdattic.smugmug.com/2016-June-Amsterdam/i-QWZNbnT/0/M/IMG_20150622_162833-M.jpg" title="" alt=""></a></p>

<p>After reaching a place which was close to the boat house stopped for some traditional Dutch pancakes. At first trying to think how to fix the phone. Soon changed that with just drinking my mint tea with honey and enjoying the fresh air. Decided my best choice would be to go back home, try to figure out how to fix my phone or at least to cache the map.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17333602178" title="Traditional Dutch Pancakes by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8879/17333602178_1f965387dc_z.jpg" width="474" height="640" alt="Traditional Dutch Pancakes"></a></p>

<p>The Google wasn&rsquo;t helpful with answers about what I should do. Except for step-by-step instructions where to find the languages. Which wasn&rsquo;t helpful as settings application wasn&rsquo;t working. In the end I was able to fix my phone. Not really sure why or how, but I was glad for settings application to start working allowing me to go back to English language. The fix was kind of simple. Inserted my original SIM card which doesn&rsquo;t work outside my country, but I&rsquo;m guessing the &ldquo;virus&rdquo; figured it was not able to do his thing and just left. Or something along those lines. It&rsquo;s a mystery to me. I was just glad for it to start working the way it&rsquo;s supposed to work. Except for antivirus being in English which I was able to change only after about a month.</p>

<p>Back in full gear went to look for that park again. Small, but nice park. As long as you don&rsquo;t step into any dog shit that is. Decided it&rsquo;s time to visit the Vondelpark park. It was the weekend and streets can get noisy from all the tourists who come to be loud, be stupid, be drunk, be unhappy and be back in 9-to-5 job on Monday. Don&rsquo;t get offended if any of those describe you. <em>I don&rsquo;t have anything against having some fun (choose your own definition)</em> or anything like that, I just don&rsquo;t think that because it&rsquo;s the weekend and you went to another country it allows you to be an idiot. <strong>I know common sense is dead, but try to find it</strong>.</p>

<p>The Vondelpark is wonderful. It&rsquo;s a large area with green zones, water and all kinds of people in it. If the day is sunny &amp; warm it&rsquo;s perfect to just lie down and relax, maybe with a book, maybe without one. It takes a while to walk through whole park, especially if you get lost as roads can sometime get confusing (they are wiggly). It has public toilets, refreshments (you can always bring your own), benches. It should take care of most of your needs. You will also meet some &ldquo;strange people&rdquo;, I call them &ldquo;crackers.&rdquo; Don&rsquo;t know why but this is what comes to my head then I think about them (in the voice of Eddie Griffin). I met three different categories during my two weeks. The first one being friendly ones which talk with you about something and  after a bit asks if maybe you could share some coins. The second one was similar to friendlies except I call them idiots. I try to be positive, but when you tell me about how hard their life is and they have no money for food because he wasted couple hundred euros yesterday in casino. Sorry, this is were I draw the line and walk away. I&rsquo;m not good enough yet to deal with this kind of situations. The third one are the aggressive kind and best to avoid as it wouldn&rsquo;t be surprising if one of them stabbed you (I have good imagination).</p>

<p>Before leaving the park stopped to listen to one guy playing incredible jazz music. Liked it so much that stopped to listen to it while talking with his friends. They were from Chile and damn, their language is beautiful. A bit later two other people stopped to listen to music and join the conversation. After a while a new guy mentioned that if someone wants Marilyn Monroe LSD he has some to sell. I would guess it would be an easy way to spice up my birthday and after listening to Tim Ferriss podcast I sometimes wonder that it would be a positive experience to experiment a little with psychedelic drugs. The thing is that some risks I like to take in the controlled environment. <em>Taking who knows what, with who knows who, who knows were for me personally isn&rsquo;t that comforting or something I couldn&rsquo;t live without</em>.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - First Experiences (part 1) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-first-experiences"/>
    <updated>2015-05-12T10:35:44+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-first-experiences-part-1-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>&ldquo;Why are you going to Amsterdam if you don&rsquo;t smoke?&rdquo;</em> A question from my friend before leaving, makes me smile every time I remember it. If you came here looking for some crazy juicy stories from Amsterdam, keep looking. I&rsquo;m sure a lot of (young) people go to Amsterdam exactly for sex, drugs &amp; alcohol. I chose to explore the other side of it: beautiful city, great culture &amp; museums.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t know what the series are about you can read the <a href="/testing-world-series-intro">intro</a>.</p>

<p>A few months before my birthday I was starting to think what I should get myself for it. It&rsquo;s not like I care a lot (any) about my birthday. It&rsquo;s just what most of the time I can remember what is the date so it&rsquo;s easy to assign some crazy gift/event with it (like testing operation table for the first time or quitting my job). The runner was to get a tattoo. I don&rsquo;t like or understand tattoos, but it would be another thing I done in life. Wondering that kind of tattoo? A black dot (probably below my belly button) and if someone would ask what it means (tattoo must have a meaning) the reply would be &ldquo;I dot F&hellip;ing give a S..t&rdquo; (aggressive, but effective). Then I remembered my promise to return to Amsterdam for at least a week. The first time I visited I was acting like some stupid tourist (going through shops, etc.) and it was only for half a day. From the map it looked like a great city with a lot to see. We have a winner!</p>

<p>I spent a lot of time trying to decide what kind of a trip it should be. First was thinking about traveling around whole Netherlands (it happened in a way, but you will read about it at the end). After some calculations decided to just take two weeks off, working as little as possible and just stay all that time in Amsterdam. Tickets purchased, places booked, map marked with places to visit (didn&rsquo;t think about keeping it so can&rsquo;t share it). Only need to wait until the end of June.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17521426095" title="Packed &amp; ready to go by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7683/17521426095_e7069aa254_z.jpg" width="637" height="640" alt="Packed &amp; ready to go"></a></p>

<p>Few hours later after a strangely pleasant flight (don&rsquo;t like them) was back in Eindhoven. A few years ago I lived in this city for a few weeks through ERASMUS. You can take the bus or the train to the Amsterdam. It costs about the same and it takes about the same amount of time. The bus is near the airport exit, but it looked like you should have a printed ticket for that (maybe someone knows if you can buy the ticket from a driver?) so just decided to use the train. At the same time I would grab something to eat at city center. While reading a cafe menu almost got hit by a car. <em>A great way to start your holidays/trip is on the front hood of a car as an ornament</em>. Maybe I lost my appetite or maybe the menu didn&rsquo;t had anything tasty and decided to try to reach Amsterdam before some other car tried to take a bite out of me.</p>

<p>Before you arrive to Netherlands &ndash; get a lot of € coins, a lot, like at least 20€ worth of coins. Why? You need them to buy the bus/train tickets and no one has any coins. You could pay with a debit/credit card, but I was against that as you get a 2% charge for paying with a card. Also I try to avoid having my card while trying and keep it at the place I&rsquo;m staying. <em>If I loose my wallet with the money in it I just lost my money, I can always get more at the ATM. If I loose my wallet with the card in it I&rsquo;m just left with that I have in cash. Just a safer choice in my opinion</em>. You can buy a ticket from the office with an extra charge. Now that I think about it the price is probably the same in the end.. Still stupid.. Forgot to add that some places accept only cash, some places accept only cards and some places I&rsquo;m not even sure accepts anything. I work with technology, I know it fails. What do you do when you can&rsquo;t accept card payments? Tell everyone to F&hellip; off and close down the shop? Well in short just <strong>know what you will be charged for paying with a card and always check which payment methods are available</strong>.</p>

<p>The trains have a free WiFi allowing you to contact your host about your arrival, search for information or just read the articles. Which I did as the first half part of the trip is boring. The second half starts where the sea should start so it&rsquo;s more interesting to look at the canals and ships. I have planed my way from the train station, but the more I looked at the map the more doubts I had about reaching it. Must be my paranoia, I&rsquo;m sure it will turn around somewhere and I will go to the train station. At least I thought so until the voice over the speakers went &ldquo;This is the last stop, please get out&rdquo;, crap. So, I&rsquo;m in the Schiphol airport. WiFi is not working anymore. Everything is in Dutch and I have no idea which bus goes to the city center. I guess I could always walk to it, it&rsquo;s only one screen away, the same distance as if walking to America. All the thoughts were gone once I found the tour mini-bus which was giving information about how to get to the city and selling the tickets.</p>

<p>While studying the map provided with the ticket I was starting to get doubts again about reaching the train station (<em>it can be confusing until you get your bearings around any new city</em>). Decided to just risk it and get out at what looked the closest stop to the place of my stay. Made the right choice and got out on the street I needed. The sun was shining and atmosphere was refreshing. It&rsquo;s nice to be back in Amsterdam, this city does have something special.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16901067473" title="Under attack by ducks! by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5329/16901067473_b3f0ea1c0c_z.jpg" width="474" height="640" alt="Under attack by ducks!"></a></p>

<p>That I love about traveling and booking your places through airbnb is what you can try some interesting houses without having to make a long term commitment. My first house &ndash; a house boat. Even if it&rsquo;s only for one day (it had some maintenance issues) it&rsquo;s a new experience. Somehow I missed checking the rest of the photos of my host and was expecting some tall guy. The door opens and I see someone who looks like Mr. Chow from Hangover movie, even his voice was similar. &ldquo;You&rsquo;re Andrew? Hi, you look different than in your photo. Come in, sorry, I&rsquo;m still hangover from yesterday, come in come in.&rdquo; After all the formalities of explaining rules and suggestions, I looked around and took a big breath of air overflowed with excitement. It&rsquo;s strange when you look out the window and water is like only a hands length away and when a big fleet of ducks start swimming your way for their payment of food. Can&rsquo;t even remember it without smiling. Another strange thing is tourists swimming in boats past your window, especially when you&rsquo;re peeing.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing the World and Looking for Home - Intro to series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/testing-world-series-intro"/>
    <updated>2015-05-03T07:44:47+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-intro-to-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16728375584" title="Testing the World and Looking for Home - Intro to series by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7745/16728375584_736018f7be_c.jpg" width="800" height="400" alt="Testing the World and Looking for Home - Intro to series"></a></p>

<p>I have a &ldquo;strange&rdquo; approach / thinking about everything. I <strong>never understood putting imaginary walls like countries / borders / nationality / etc.</strong> To me it always looked strange. <em>Why someone would be willing to cram in himself into some imaginary box</em>. Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, I understand what culture, country you grew up, nationality defines you and could have a high impact on how you might react to things. But my answer to &ldquo;Where are you from?&rdquo; is &ldquo;From Earth, last time I checked?&rdquo; (I have some doubts, but lets leave it at that). I&rsquo;m also not someone who will just pack his backpack and would go on the round the world trip (at least not yet). Damn, about a year ago, listening to someone&rsquo;s latest trip would suck out the energy from me.</p>

<p><strong>Staying in another country in my opinion is something you have to do as soon as possible</strong>. No matter how much you read, it won&rsquo;t <em>expand your thinking</em> as mush as surrounding yourself with a different culture &amp; environment. Today, when you have so much opportunities to travel, <em>it&rsquo;s something you can&rsquo;t miss out on</em>.</p>

<p>As a digital nomad I have a great opportunity to travel as long as I have my laptop and internet connection. Even internet is not a requirement. My current approach is to visit the country for a few weeks or months, learn about the culture and life in that country and return to my &ldquo;base of operations&rdquo; country. A lot of people would suggest that you should stay 3 months in one place or at least a month, and I agree with you, but I also found that for me 2 weeks is great. It allows enough time to get a feel for a place, but it&rsquo;s not that long in case you won&rsquo;t like it. My &ldquo;base of operations&rdquo; country is the one I grew up and quite used up to. But it&rsquo;s not the country I would like to live for the rest of my life. Before, I used to hate it. As I traveled more and my thinking expanded the thinking about it changed and just like any country it has pros and cons. One of the pros is that it&rsquo;s relatively cheap to live in, allowing to save that money for the next trip.</p>

<p><strong>So what is my main reason for traveling? It&rsquo;s to find a place which I could call my home</strong>. <em>You know what feeling where thinking about some place makes you warm inside and you can&rsquo;t wait to return to it</em>. Some might say the home is the place which you make, and you would probably be right, but as long as I&rsquo;m able I will first try to find that place. At least failing to find that place would help me into understanding what I&rsquo;m really looking for.</p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t done a lot of traveling yet. But thought that some might find it useful to learn what I learned through my travels. <strong>The purpose of the series is to share what I liked, disliked and general tips about places visited</strong>. <em>It&rsquo;s always good to be wise and learn from other people mistakes, but never forget to make your own</em>.</p>

<p><strong>Below you will find the links to all the articles in the series, happy reading:</strong></p>

<h2>Amsterdam, Netherlands [2014]</h2>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>

<h2>Barcelona / Seville / Madrid, Spain [2014]</h2>

<p>* Intro
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Digital Nomad One Backpack Packing for 6 Weeks Trip (Video)]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/one-backpack-packing"/>
    <updated>2015-03-16T18:02:17+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/digital-nomad-one-backpack-packing-for-6-weeks-trip-video</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 2014 I took the 6 weeks trip to Spain. Forgot to record a video of packing my backpack at that moment. After talking with other digital nomads about packing thought that it might be really fun to try recording a video of it. This is the first time I did something like it, so feedback would be appreciated. Here&rsquo;s the video:</p>

<iframe width="732" height="412" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xH3QEfMXjh0?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>For the list of gear mentioned in the video check the <a href="https://bitly.com/bundles/ifdattic/1#">bitly collection</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
