<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | ifdattic]]></title>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-31T13:26:54+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://ifdattic.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Marcinkevičius]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - First Experiences (part 1) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-first-experiences"/>
    <updated>2015-05-12T11:35:44+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-first-experiences-part-1-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>&ldquo;Why are you going to Amsterdam if you don&rsquo;t smoke?&rdquo;</em> A question from my friend before leaving, makes me smile every time I remember it. If you came here looking for some crazy juicy stories from Amsterdam, keep looking. I&rsquo;m sure a lot of (young) people go to Amsterdam exactly for sex, drugs &amp; alcohol. I chose to explore the other side of it: beautiful city, great culture &amp; museums.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t know what the series are about you can read the <a href="/testing-world-series-intro">intro</a>.</p>

<p>A few months before my birthday I was starting to think what I should get myself for it. It&rsquo;s not like I care a lot (any) about my birthday. It&rsquo;s just what most of the time I can remember what is the date so it&rsquo;s easy to assign some crazy gift/event with it (like testing operation table for the first time or quitting my job). The runner was to get a tattoo. I don&rsquo;t like or understand tattoos, but it would be another thing I done in life. Wondering that kind of tattoo? A black dot (probably below my belly button) and if someone would ask what it means (tattoo must have a meaning) the reply would be &ldquo;I dot F&hellip;ing give a S..t&rdquo; (aggressive, but effective). Then I remembered my promise to return to Amsterdam for at least a week. The first time I visited I was acting like some stupid tourist (going through shops, etc.) and it was only for half a day. From the map it looked like a great city with a lot to see. We have a winner!</p>

<p>I spent a lot of time trying to decide what kind of a trip it should be. First was thinking about traveling around whole Netherlands (it happened in a way, but you will read about it at the end). After some calculations decided to just take two weeks off, working as little as possible and just stay all that time in Amsterdam. Tickets purchased, places booked, map marked with places to visit (didn&rsquo;t think about keeping it so can&rsquo;t share it). Only need to wait until the end of June.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17521426095" title="Packed &amp; ready to go by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7683/17521426095_e7069aa254_z.jpg" width="637" height="640" alt="Packed &amp; ready to go"></a></p>

<p>Few hours later after a strangely pleasant flight (don&rsquo;t like them) was back in Eindhoven. A few years ago I lived in this city for a few weeks through ERASMUS. You can take the bus or the train to the Amsterdam. It costs about the same and it takes about the same amount of time. The bus is near the airport exit, but it looked like you should have a printed ticket for that (maybe someone knows if you can buy the ticket from a driver?) so just decided to use the train. At the same time I would grab something to eat at city center. While reading a cafe menu almost got hit by a car. <em>A great way to start your holidays/trip is on the front hood of a car as an ornament</em>. Maybe I lost my appetite or maybe the menu didn&rsquo;t had anything tasty and decided to try to reach Amsterdam before some other car tried to take a bite out of me.</p>

<p>Before you arrive to Netherlands &ndash; get a lot of € coins, a lot, like at least 20€ worth of coins. Why? You need them to buy the bus/train tickets and no one has any coins. You could pay with a debit/credit card, but I was against that as you get a 2% charge for paying with a card. Also I try to avoid having my card while trying and keep it at the place I&rsquo;m staying. <em>If I loose my wallet with the money in it I just lost my money, I can always get more at the ATM. If I loose my wallet with the card in it I&rsquo;m just left with that I have in cash. Just a safer choice in my opinion</em>. You can buy a ticket from the office with an extra charge. Now that I think about it the price is probably the same in the end.. Still stupid.. Forgot to add that some places accept only cash, some places accept only cards and some places I&rsquo;m not even sure accepts anything. I work with technology, I know it fails. What do you do when you can&rsquo;t accept card payments? Tell everyone to F&hellip; off and close down the shop? Well in short just <strong>know what you will be charged for paying with a card and always check which payment methods are available</strong>.</p>

<p>The trains have a free WiFi allowing you to contact your host about your arrival, search for information or just read the articles. Which I did as the first half part of the trip is boring. The second half starts where the sea should start so it&rsquo;s more interesting to look at the canals and ships. I have planed my way from the train station, but the more I looked at the map the more doubts I had about reaching it. Must be my paranoia, I&rsquo;m sure it will turn around somewhere and I will go to the train station. At least I thought so until the voice over the speakers went &ldquo;This is the last stop, please get out&rdquo;, crap. So, I&rsquo;m in the Schiphol airport. WiFi is not working anymore. Everything is in Dutch and I have no idea which bus goes to the city center. I guess I could always walk to it, it&rsquo;s only one screen away, the same distance as if walking to America. All the thoughts were gone once I found the tour mini-bus which was giving information about how to get to the city and selling the tickets.</p>

<p>While studying the map provided with the ticket I was starting to get doubts again about reaching the train station (<em>it can be confusing until you get your bearings around any new city</em>). Decided to just risk it and get out at what looked the closest stop to the place of my stay. Made the right choice and got out on the street I needed. The sun was shining and atmosphere was refreshing. It&rsquo;s nice to be back in Amsterdam, this city does have something special.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16901067473" title="Under attack by ducks! by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5329/16901067473_b3f0ea1c0c_z.jpg" width="474" height="640" alt="Under attack by ducks!"></a></p>

<p>That I love about traveling and booking your places through airbnb is what you can try some interesting houses without having to make a long term commitment. My first house &ndash; a house boat. Even if it&rsquo;s only for one day (it had some maintenance issues) it&rsquo;s a new experience. Somehow I missed checking the rest of the photos of my host and was expecting some tall guy. The door opens and I see someone who looks like Mr. Chow from Hangover movie, even his voice was similar. &ldquo;You&rsquo;re Andrew? Hi, you look different than in your photo. Come in, sorry, I&rsquo;m still hangover from yesterday, come in come in.&rdquo; After all the formalities of explaining rules and suggestions, I looked around and took a big breath of air overflowed with excitement. It&rsquo;s strange when you look out the window and water is like only a hands length away and when a big fleet of ducks start swimming your way for their payment of food. Can&rsquo;t even remember it without smiling. Another strange thing is tourists swimming in boats past your window, especially when you&rsquo;re peeing.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing the World and Looking for Home - Intro to series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/testing-world-series-intro"/>
    <updated>2015-05-03T08:44:47+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-intro-to-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16728375584" title="Testing the World and Looking for Home - Intro to series by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7745/16728375584_736018f7be_c.jpg" width="800" height="400" alt="Testing the World and Looking for Home - Intro to series"></a></p>

<p>I have a &ldquo;strange&rdquo; approach / thinking about everything. I <strong>never understood putting imaginary walls like countries / borders / nationality / etc.</strong> To me it always looked strange. <em>Why someone would be willing to cram in himself into some imaginary box</em>. Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, I understand what culture, country you grew up, nationality defines you and could have a high impact on how you might react to things. But my answer to &ldquo;Where are you from?&rdquo; is &ldquo;From Earth, last time I checked?&rdquo; (I have some doubts, but lets leave it at that). I&rsquo;m also not someone who will just pack his backpack and would go on the round the world trip (at least not yet). Damn, about a year ago, listening to someone&rsquo;s latest trip would suck out the energy from me.</p>

<p><strong>Staying in another country in my opinion is something you have to do as soon as possible</strong>. No matter how much you read, it won&rsquo;t <em>expand your thinking</em> as mush as surrounding yourself with a different culture &amp; environment. Today, when you have so much opportunities to travel, <em>it&rsquo;s something you can&rsquo;t miss out on</em>.</p>

<p>As a digital nomad I have a great opportunity to travel as long as I have my laptop and internet connection. Even internet is not a requirement. My current approach is to visit the country for a few weeks or months, learn about the culture and life in that country and return to my &ldquo;base of operations&rdquo; country. A lot of people would suggest that you should stay 3 months in one place or at least a month, and I agree with you, but I also found that for me 2 weeks is great. It allows enough time to get a feel for a place, but it&rsquo;s not that long in case you won&rsquo;t like it. My &ldquo;base of operations&rdquo; country is the one I grew up and quite used up to. But it&rsquo;s not the country I would like to live for the rest of my life. Before, I used to hate it. As I traveled more and my thinking expanded the thinking about it changed and just like any country it has pros and cons. One of the pros is that it&rsquo;s relatively cheap to live in, allowing to save that money for the next trip.</p>

<p><strong>So what is my main reason for traveling? It&rsquo;s to find a place which I could call my home</strong>. <em>You know what feeling where thinking about some place makes you warm inside and you can&rsquo;t wait to return to it</em>. Some might say the home is the place which you make, and you would probably be right, but as long as I&rsquo;m able I will first try to find that place. At least failing to find that place would help me into understanding what I&rsquo;m really looking for.</p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t done a lot of traveling yet. But thought that some might find it useful to learn what I learned through my travels. <strong>The purpose of the series is to share what I liked, disliked and general tips about places visited</strong>. <em>It&rsquo;s always good to be wise and learn from other people mistakes, but never forget to make your own</em>.</p>

<p><strong>Below you will find the links to all the articles in the series, happy reading:</strong></p>

<h2>Amsterdam, Netherlands [2014]</h2>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>

<h2>Barcelona / Seville / Madrid, Spain [2014]</h2>

<p>* Intro
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Digital Nomad One Backpack Packing for 6 Weeks Trip (Video)]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/one-backpack-packing"/>
    <updated>2015-03-16T19:02:17+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/digital-nomad-one-backpack-packing-for-6-weeks-trip-video</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 2014 I took the 6 weeks trip to Spain. Forgot to record a video of packing my backpack at that moment. After talking with other digital nomads about packing thought that it might be really fun to try recording a video of it. This is the first time I did something like it, so feedback would be appreciated. Here&rsquo;s the video:</p>

<iframe width="732" height="412" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xH3QEfMXjh0?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>For the list of gear mentioned in the video check the <a href="https://bitly.com/bundles/ifdattic/1#">bitly collection</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Most important skill I learned from stopping smoking &amp; drinking]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/important-skill-learned-from-no-smoking-drinking"/>
    <updated>2015-03-08T12:03:17+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/most-important-skill-i-learned-from-stopping-smoking-and-drinking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p><strong>tl;dr; Headbutt the problem and solve it right now as it won&rsquo;t go away</strong></p></blockquote>

<p>I stopped (will allow to say &ldquo;quit&rdquo; in 10 years) smoking about one year and 7 months ago (2013/08/10). I stopped drinking about 7 months ago (2014/08/15).</p>

<p>Funny thing is on 2013 I was burning a bunch of personal crap (dreadlocks, paintings, clothes, etc). A year later, I&rsquo;m burning the rest of my personal crap (letters, talismans, diaries, photos, etc.). Remembered that a year before I was doing the same thing and stopped smoking. Thought that it would be great if I stopped drinking after this burning.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16565367989" title="Burning personal crap, last day of drinking by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr" target="_blank"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8743/16565367989_8462b9b24c_c.jpg" width="724" height="800" alt="Burning personal crap, last day of drinking"></a></p>

<p>It wasn&rsquo;t exactly easy and my though always was to not give any of them away. I liked both of guilty pleasures a lot. Actually, I thought it would be impossible to give them away. But once you challenge yourself you find that &ldquo;impossible&rdquo; is just a state of mind. Everything is possible when you don&rsquo;t know it&rsquo;s impossible. Or don&rsquo;t allow yourself to fail before trying.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not against smoking or drinking. I&rsquo;m not saying I won&rsquo;t start doing it ever again. I do know, I don&rsquo;t want to do them ever again, but I don&rsquo;t know if I&rsquo;m yet strong enough to keep it forever.</p>

<p>Even writing this article requires a lot of willpower to keep yourself from thinking how delicious is a thick smoke filling your lungs or a cold alcoholic beverage touching the tip of your tongue.</p>

<p>Only my thinking changed &ndash; they are the same as crutches are for a healthy person. Most of the time they are only hiding a deeper issue which won&rsquo;t go away. Feeling stressed? Go have a cigarette or a cold beer. Yes, it will get better. For now. The problem is that the issue is still there. Only hidden under a wall which will crumble like  a sand castle.</p>

<p>An believe me, the mind/body plays tricks on you trying to trip you. <em>&ldquo;Oh, this is such a perfect problem to have a cold beer over. Let me start you salivating from your mouth.&rdquo;</em> But if you win and reply with <em>&ldquo;No. It won&rsquo;t help with a problem. It won&rsquo;t solve a problem. It won&rsquo;t make me feel any better now or tomorrow and I will still have the same problem the next day. It&rsquo;s time to think how to solve this problem.&rdquo;</em> This moment is so empowering as you know that you took the hard way out, not the easy one out.</p>

<p>Stopping to drink and/or smoke might have improved my health &amp; finances. But the most important skill it taught me is to <strong>take the hard way out and solve a problem right away, not to hide away from it</strong>.</p>

<p>Have you tried to stop drinking or smoking? Have it taught you anything?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My experience with SensioLabs Symfony certification exam]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/my-experience-sensiolabs-symfony-certification-exam"/>
    <updated>2015-02-17T18:19:52+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/my-experience-with-sensiolabs-symfony-certification-exam</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One day I check my email and see one from Fabien <em>&ldquo;Symfony turned 9 and for being one of top 100 contributors you get a free voucher.&rdquo;</em> It definitely lifted my spirits.</p>

<p>Voucher was valid for a year so I just created a calendar reminder <em>&ldquo;Learn for Symfony certificate.&rdquo;</em> Made it due sometime in Summer and more or less forgot about it. More than enough time left for it.</p>

<p>After the SymfonyCon Madrid I evaluated my career possibilities. Decided it&rsquo;s time to stop riding a dead horse and move the majority of my time working with Symfony framework. At the same time remembered the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parkinson%27s_law">Parkinson&rsquo;s Law</a>. <strong>The task will take as long as it&rsquo;s given time</strong>. Time to add the deadline. No matter how much I will learn for it, on March 1st I need to book the exam.</p>

<p>Somehow I made January &amp; February months for learning a lot of new things. Because of that I didn&rsquo;t get as much practical experience as suspected. Still <strong>made a habit of 90 minutes reading Symfony documentation for breakfast</strong>, um, tasty. This habit was mandatory!</p>

<p>The only preparation what I did was to take all the topics written in certification page and put them in a Trello card. Add items for cookbook topics, doctrine, etc. Not all are required for certification, but a good documentation is like a good book for me, so I didn&rsquo;t mind adding them. Add the links for easy access to as much of items as possible and that&rsquo;s it.</p>

<p>At first the list of about 160 items makes you take a big breath. But one check-box at a time you can see the progress.</p>

<p>This was also the <em>great chance to improve the documentation</em> (fixing typos, etc.). Changing it to the way you imagine it (changing formatting, etc.) and picking the brains of Symfony contributors (discussions in PRs, etc.).</p>

<p><em>90 minutes each day was spent making a few notes once in a while, creating pull requests, experimenting a bit</em>. On February I did some calculations and estimated that around the middle of it I should be done. It was time to register for an exam. Really wanted to do it on February 13th the Friday (how cool does that sound). But the place I like staying at wasn&rsquo;t available for rent. Also it felt like trying to avoid the unavoidable (a bad habit to have). So just registered for Monday (the sooner the better).</p>

<p>In the remaining days finished with the remaining topics. Did a <em>quick second round on the book</em> and it was time to take the exam the next day. <em>This took me about 6 weeks (~63 hours)</em>. I never believed about learning till the last second. My choice always is to put a good nights sleep between learning &amp; applying it. So Sunday documentation breakfast was the last one I will be taking for at least a while (<em>failure is always an option</em>).</p>

<p>The next day I woke up feeling great. Slept well, had a nice meeting the day before, exercised, took a shower, ate and the day looked like it will be a great one. Or would it? Nah, it would be a good one. The worst that could happen is that I won&rsquo;t pass the exam and that&rsquo;s it. It&rsquo;s not the end of a world.</p>

<p>OK, I worried a bit about slipping on the icy bridge while walking to the exam center and breaking my neck or dropping into a cold water. But this is the problem with my imagination. Other than that, I was trying to keep a relaxed attitude by taking a long slow walk along the snowed river to the exam center. Went out early to keep my paranoia in check about arriving late, <em>I like to stay safe</em>.</p>

<p>It sounds silly, but after arriving <em>I noticed my legs getting a bit weaker and heart pounding a little harder. Stupid body</em>. Had about half an hour before the exam. I always try to prepare myself for the worst scenario (which never happens) just in case. And you get a pleasant surprise when the end result is better than that you were expecting. If you&rsquo;re prepared to lose both legs, losing only one of them is wonderful. But most of the time from my research (books, articles, etc.) the suggestion is to imagine the result you want and your mind will go towards it. I&rsquo;m still skeptic about it, but if it&rsquo;s repeated often there must be something to it. And <em>you can&rsquo;t learn without testing</em>, so why not, let&rsquo;s try it.</p>

<p>I sat down. Closed my eyes. Started taking monotonic breaths and focusing my mind on passing the exam. At least my heart stopped pounding. A fresher head couldn&rsquo;t hurt either.</p>

<p><em>I&rsquo;m personally a little skeptic about these exams as you could pass them with a good memory</em>. Especially after I met a person with a Java certificate when he shouldn&rsquo;t be a programmer in the first place. Unfortunately for me, <em>I  don&rsquo;t have a good memory, and it works in strange ways</em>. For example, trying to remember when I had my first operation (string of 10 characters) leads to the following flow: it was on my birthday, I finished school that year, it was my 19th birthday, I finished school one year after 18th birthday, on my school leaving certificate it&rsquo;s written 2006, so I had it on 2006-06-28. Not the best way to remember a date. <em>Fortunately for me, my logic module pick up the pace and helps were memory starts ramble. I just have to put enough resources to be able to link them together.</em></p>

<p>By reminding myself that it wouldn&rsquo;t matter if I fail my head wasn&rsquo;t occupied by negative thoughts about that will happen if I fail. This allowed to take the exam with <em>stone cold focus. Read the question, read the answers, pick the one which is correct or makes most sense, keep going</em>. Flagged two questions for review, but after the second time told myself to stop doing that and simply believe in myself. <em>I enjoyed the exam a lot. It had a good flow &amp; presentation of questions</em>. A few of them made my head go &ldquo;What??&rdquo; (unlike Zend Certificate which contained quite a few &ldquo;WTF?!?&rdquo; questions). Solution to them was simple &ndash; read the question &amp; answers again, you can do this.</p>

<p>75 questions later was confirming that I&rsquo;m finishing the exam and the moment of truth&hellip; Thinking I did good on exam. Still, took the big breath guessing if I should just wait for screen to change or close my eyes&hellip; The screen is still waiting&hellip; The screen finishes loading&hellip; And a log-in pop-up shoots to the front of the screen&hellip;</p>

<p>(╯°□°）╯︵ ┻━┻</p>

<p>After some fiddling I bring the screen back. My eyes start shooting around the screen scanning for required information. &hellip; &ldquo;<strong>Passed</strong>.&rdquo; Great, which level? &hellip; &ldquo;<strong>Expert</strong>.&rdquo; Yes *fist pump*</p>

<p>Unlike with PHP certificate my reaction at the end of exam was much more &ldquo;professional.&rdquo; It still felt awesome!!!</p>

<p>Note: For anyone who is interested I made a <a href="https://trello.com/c/aHnP3WUI/1-learn-for-symfony-certification">Trello card</a> public.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
