<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | ifdattic]]></title>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-08T09:25:38+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://ifdattic.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Marcinkevičius]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - Exploring the City (part 3) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-exploring-city"/>
    <updated>2015-07-08T09:07:57+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-exploring-the-city-part-3-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the morning it felt great to have my cup of tea in front of a fleet of ducks. I like water, it&rsquo;s relaxing. As the houseboat required maintenance we moved to hosts' house which was close to city center. It was a nice place. The only problem was that internet connection was down. For someone who requires it for working this wasn&rsquo;t good news. At least the host could hotspot his phone, but the speed of it was as exciting as counting dust falling. I could hardly check my email. After having a birthday breakfast prepared by the host I went out for a random walk around the city. My first destination was to check out NEMO science center. We saw it while taking a taxi ride and it looked interesting. It didn&rsquo;t look that interesting after I found out you have to take the stairs to the top. Was starting to think if I should even bother with it. Well, nothing is easy in life and you need to put some effort if you want something back. Climbing them wasn&rsquo;t as bad as I thought, just the first 10 steps looked terrible. You can see most of the Amsterdam from the roof and it&rsquo;s a nice place to relax (as long as you stay away from kids). I chose a quiet spot and sit down to read Psycho Cybernetics. You can&rsquo;t get the original on kindle and I chose to return without it after a trip.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17333628968" title="10438926_10202278717309911_6209002604154581610_n by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7690/17333628968_eb54ccf813_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="10438926_10202278717309911_6209002604154581610_n"></a></p>

<p>Can&rsquo;t remember exactly which places I visited, but I took a large circle around town. I roughly guessing that during my trips I walk about 10-20 kilometers per day. Of course Amsterdam is a great city to rent a bike and explore it this way, but I don&rsquo;t see a point for that personally. For me I get tired about the same. It&rsquo;s just the question of time (bike takes a bit less) which I had enough, so I chose the transport type I like most &ndash; my legs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16901198423" title="10269094_10202278718189933_2393730023996421613_o by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7797/16901198423_de904fbbc3_z.jpg" width="640" height="452" alt="10269094_10202278718189933_2393730023996421613_o"></a></p>

<p>After returning the host invited to join them to watch a game in a city. Unlike most people think I&rsquo;m not against the sports and if I had enough health or skills I would do them. That I don&rsquo;t understand is the point of watching a bunch of people with the ball. I can find more interesting things to do. Recently someone asked &ldquo;what things?&rdquo; and my answer was &ldquo;You&rsquo;re old enough, use your imagination.&rdquo; But sure, why not, let&rsquo;s try it, who knows maybe I will enjoy it. The game was a nice one, but I could still just watch 2 minute reel the next day and save at least an hour.</p>

<p>The tip time: <em>avoid drinking beer (or a lot of any beverage) in Netherlands</em>. Why? Because you have to pay for the toilet in bars. And no, they don&rsquo;t care that you&rsquo;re a customer. You want to piss &ndash; you pay. As they don&rsquo;t even have normal beer (meaning you can drink as much as you want and you won&rsquo;t get drunk) if you went a little overboard you could end up spending more on WC than on the drinks. Drink responsibly.</p>

<p>After a while we went to a house boat. Amsterdam is beautiful during the night. I don&rsquo;t know about you, but I personally find it funny when people try to hide the usage of drugs. Like if you close yourself in the toilet and I hear *cocaine snorting sounds* like I will be thinking that you&rsquo;re cleaning the toilet. Then four of us went to a club. One high on cocaine, one on ecstasy, one on weed and one (me) had a few beers. And from that I saw, I still had the most fun (and it wasn&rsquo;t a fun night). Before entering we first had to wait until some overdosed girl was taken out. Kids, use drugs responsibly.</p>

<p>You might kind of guess it, but I&rsquo;m not a big fan of clubs. I&rsquo;m not against them or anything, it&rsquo;s just not for me. If it&rsquo;s impossible to have a normal conversation (the one were your only reply is nod then lips stop moving) then the place is too loud. Give me one person who loves to talk (I&rsquo;m better listener than talker), a cup of tea, cozy atmosphere and I will be having the best night of my life. The place was crowded, full of smoke and DJs were so terrible that I wanted to go to them and slap them in the face and just tell them to leave the Spotify playing without messing with controls. One thing I noticed is that I stopped caring about tobacco smokes. Don&rsquo;t like it, it makes me nauseating, but don&rsquo;t care and don&rsquo;t ever want to do that again. Then came 3 AM and I think I know how Cinderella must have felt when midnight came. All the better looking (from outside) ass grinders (girls that grind their asses into anything that moves or doesn&rsquo;t move) in a blink of an eye changed into some alligator monsters. Group or no group, I don&rsquo;t care, I chose not to stay a second longer in there. They looked hungry and I&rsquo;m too old to be grinded into a wall.</p>

<p>The next day I chose to go to Westerpark because it looked like a big splash of green and was close from my position. My suggestion is just to avoid it and better go to Vondelpark. Only the start of it is a real park and the rest is I think some kind off housings (haven&rsquo;t found the entry). You end up walking a side street all the way around without being able to enjoy any greenery. As my new host will be able to check-in me only in the evening we made a deal that I will leave some things at her place so I wouldn&rsquo;t have to walk with them everywhere tomorrow (knowing with how much I travel it&rsquo;s not that big of a deal). Can&rsquo;t remember the exact description but it make me happy thinking about &ldquo;go meet a girl in a red dress.&rdquo; Sometimes silly things make you smile. Went by the Anne Frank house and right away I knew that I won&rsquo;t be visiting it (especially after the host added some more info about it). No way I&rsquo;m standing in that long of a line for something I don&rsquo;t find interesting. I was invited for a cup of tea, we talked and learned about each other. One of many enjoyable conversations we had with the host. Can&rsquo;t remember that I did for the rest of the day.</p>

<p>The next day after waking up and noticing that WiFi is still not available I packed my stuff and left. The host was not home, but I was not going to waste precious hours I could spend working and earning money to pay off this trip. The weather was gray and wet, not enjoyable. I chose to stop at some organic burger place with a big table in the corner (window included). You wouldn&rsquo;t believe how productive you can be after changing the scenery and with a cold beer nearby. Did all my planned work in about an hour surprising myself and my client. Too bad I was charging by an hour. Time for another tip. In Amsterdam you don&rsquo;t need to worry much if you might need WiFi for something. Some places require using some app (skip those), some have it available (you stand in the street doing what you do) and some have the password on their menu. You might need to shop around to find the WiFi you like, but you will find it somewhere if needed.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17519150272" title="10480565_10202281410217232_2518834619728254079_o by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5455/17519150272_a8f301ceda_z.jpg" width="474" height="640" alt="10480565_10202281410217232_2518834619728254079_o"></a></p>

<p>The new place I was staying at was a bit strange, but nice. Third floor, from one window you can see the street and canals. My room was in the attic which has a window to the inner yard. It was quiet except for birds singing (strangely I liked that). Most of the mornings I woke up with sun tickling my naked leg. The architecture I found a bit strange and hard to figure out. Every day I had to watch out not to be killed by circular stairs or low ceilings (I&rsquo;m tall). Also I find it strange that everything is small when Dutch people are tall. I think some great-great-grandfather just went &ldquo;How about we mess up with future generations and build everything small?&rdquo; The host was a very lively French girl. I enjoyed our conversations and dinners together a lot. We became friends during this trip. She found my approach to minimalism interesting. She accepted my suggestion to try it out and simplify her own life by removing material chains. I also gave her many heart attacks (which I found satisfying) as most people are not used to someone who moves around like a ghost.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Amsterdam - Exploring the City](/amsterdam-exploring-city)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review of Dutch PHP 2015 Conference]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/dutch-php-2015-conference-review"/>
    <updated>2015-06-29T20:51:19+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/review-of-dutch-php-2015-conference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On June of 2015 I attended the Dutch PHP conference and this is a short review of it.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/19264000576" title="Dutch PHP 2015 Conference by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/408/19264000576_4272fa2fa2_z.jpg" width="640" height="303" alt="Dutch PHP 2015 Conference"></a></p>

<p>The conference was at Amsterdam RAI venue which is outside city center. Organizers provided directions how to get to it from city center and it&rsquo;s not hard to find. Depending on where you&rsquo;re staying for conference it might have been easier or harder to reach it. I heard some people that they would like it closer to their hotel as they don&rsquo;t want to figure out how to use public transport or take it for 20 minutes to get to the venue. I didn&rsquo;t had a direct route from my airbnb place to the venue, but it was not a big problem for me. For someone who likes exploring places by choosing a direction and walking in it a 45 minute walk to venue is a good way to freshen up my head.</p>

<p>Venue is big and well supported by staff. Signs make it easy to find where you need to go. The staff is always available to provide you with refreshments (tea, coffee, juice, water) and clean up. Stand up tables make it easy to discuss with other people while having a refreshment and sitting desks are comfortable if you need to do some work.</p>

<p>This might be normal for Dutch people, but I don&rsquo;t think of a bunch of cold sandwiches as a normal lunch. For someone who tries to avoid carbs it&rsquo;s nerving to think how many days will be spent feeling like crap from all that bread. I guess this is my own problem for not preparing and bringing something to eat. Still, from all my experience I personally hate Dutch food, not my cuisine.</p>

<p>On first day I was attending <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14190">Introduction to Event Sourcing and CQRS</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/beausimensen">Beau D. Simensen</a> &amp; <a href="https://twitter.com/willemjanz">Willem-Jan Zijderveld</a>. Lately I&rsquo;m very into Domain Driven Design and similar ways of improving applications so this workshop gave a good introduction into CQRS. The first part of workshop was explaining all the principles. Found that trying to follow the host and do it on my own laptop wasn&rsquo;t very easy due to it going too fast and having some issues. After deciding to just follow the host found the experience much better. This allowed to focus better on that is going on rather than trying to multi-task. The second part of the workshop was doing the same things, but using Broadway library. Think the workshop was well done. It might be better if the git repository was tagged after each step, so for anyone trying to follow along if they are getting behind they could just checkout the step being currently done.</p>

<p>After the workshops anyone who wanted could attend code night. During it you could work on one of available open source projects helping to improve them. It had drinks, pizza and great people to talk &amp; work with. At the end of code night during the raffle it was possible to win some prizes. It was well organized and think the code night was a success. Watch the time lapse videos of it (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ShfMqa57PMM">part 1</a> &amp; <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=R4d04rImZAU">part 2</a>).</p>

<p>The conference had a lot of sponsors. You could play games, pick up swag, learn about new tools in sponsor booths. At the end of the conference it was possible to win prizes through the raffle.</p>

<p>Only the second talk was delayed by 15 minutes, but otherwise all conference run like well maintained clock. All talks were on time, none went over, good amount of breaks between tasks.</p>

<p>For each time slot 5 different talks were going at the same time. For anyone interested an un-official talks were available. The talks were very well done with all/most of the problems fixed (from the talks I attended). The talks weren&rsquo;t just about PHP so you could always choose topics which interest you most (devops, testing, JavaScript, CSS, etc.).</p>

<p>The opening keynote was <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14478">Hacking Foresight from Hindsight</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/joshholmes">Josh Holmes</a>. The important point of the talk was that we shouldn&rsquo;t try to do everything ourselves and should try to find mentors who will help us grow faster professionally &amp; personally.</p>

<p>For the first talk I went to <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14208">Get some hypermedia up in your API</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/victorwelling">Victor Welling</a>. During it he explained how to solve problems like documentation, versioning, visibility of your API by extending with with HAL.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m a tall guy and ergonomically it&rsquo;s more comfortable to stay farther away from the screen. At that moment decided to experiment with sitting in the front rows. You don&rsquo;t need to spend all the time looking at the screen and found that I enjoyed having a closer proximity/relationship with a speaker much more than being able to see the screen all the time.</p>

<p>The second talk I chose was <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14211">Automation made simple with Ansible</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/erikaheidi">Erika Heidi</a>. I played a little with Ansible before. Repetition helps with retaining information. The talk gradually explains what is possible with Ansible and after it you should be in a good position to play around with it in your projects. After talking with Erika between talks, I think now I know how my phone feels when I plug it to charge the batteries. She is a very positive girl and talking with her you can feel your own batteries charging.</p>

<p>Had a hard choice for third talk as Mathias Verraes &amp; Matthias Noback was talking at the same slot. Chose to go to <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14214">Towards Modelling Processes</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/mathiasverraes">Mathias Verraes</a>. Talk had a simulated event storming and the main point of talk was explaining how to think in temporal model, not just structural.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/18667538394" title="DPC15 - Towards Modelling Processes by Mathias Verraes by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/256/18667538394_8203dbba5e_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DPC15 - Towards Modelling Processes by Mathias Verraes"></a></p>

<p>Was a little late for <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14219">Command Bus to Awesome Town</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/rosstuck">Ross Tuck</a> talk. The speaker was lively with enough jokes between the slides. The talk explained what is command bus &amp; why/how you might want to use one in your project.</p>

<p>During the conference I went to enough talks about event sourcing and similar topics, but going to <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14226">Let&rsquo;s Write Some History!</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/willemjanz">Willem-Jan Zijderveld</a> helped me to understand a few more concepts I was missing/confused.</p>

<p>For last first day talk I chose <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14231">Journey into your Lizard Brain</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/rdohms">Rafael Dohms</a>. During it he shared a personal story, explained how developers think &amp; gave tips on how to become a better developer. One of the most important points in my opinion would be to focus on the current moment. I think conferences could have more of &ldquo;soft&rdquo; talks as I find them refreshing when mixed with technical talks.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/18667539664" title="DPC15 - Journey into your Lizard Brain by Rafael Dohms by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/469/18667539664_38611826a4_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DPC15 - Journey into your Lizard Brain by Rafael Dohms"></a></p>

<p>The Conference Social was at Akhnaton. Organizers provided directions how to get from venue to it. It was easy to find the bar and after arrival everyone received drink tokens. Received enough tokens to spend the rest of the evening with a bottle of water in my hand (might be a different experience depending on your drinking habits).</p>

<p>The day before I decided to skip the morning talk. Even thought woke up refreshed I&rsquo;m trying to learn to make a decision and keep with it (unless the situation changes).</p>

<p>For second talk I went to <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14238">Hexagonal architecture &ndash; message-oriented software design</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/matthiasnoback">Matthias Noback</a>. The talk was well paced, explaining how to improve your applications by focusing on messages.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/19293946821" title="DPC15 - Hexagonal architecture - message-oriented software design by Matthias Noback by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/445/19293946821_426765221f_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DPC15 - Hexagonal architecture - message-oriented software design by Matthias Noback"></a></p>

<p>I think the composer is a wonderful tool making my life much easier. I think I know enough of it to do what is needed and advise others of best practices (like using CLI and not editing JSON file). It never hurts to make sure so I went to <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14245">Composer The Right Way</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/rdohms">Rafael Dohms</a>. The talk explained some parts which you might not use so often &amp; how to use composer better. If you don&rsquo;t use composer (or know what it is) stop making your life harder!</p>

<p>For the fourth talk was thinking about going to <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14248">Implement Single Sign On easily with Symfony</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/Saro0h">Sarah Khalil</a>. When considered that can&rsquo;t think of anything were I would need to implement it in the near future and need to mix a less technical talk for better ratio. Went to <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14249">Software architecture in an agile age</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/harrieverveer">Harrie Verveer</a>. Maybe it&rsquo;s the trauma from college when had to do a lot of UML diagrams or maybe being sleepy after lunch, but expected a little more from the talk. It was still a good talk explaining how to work better on your projects. I agree with most important idea what no matter which format you use it&rsquo;s good to make at least few notes/diagrams before you start building things.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/19284034222" title="DPC15 - Software architecture in an agile age by Harrie Verveer by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/357/19284034222_5f5d050fb2_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="DPC15 - Software architecture in an agile age by Harrie Verveer"></a></p>

<p>For last talk chose to go to <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14253">Adding 1.21 Gigawatts to Application with RabbitMQ</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/asgrim">James Titcumb</a>. The talk is very technical with code examples and at some points it can feel a little dry. We talked with a speaker about how it can be improved. The talk explains very well how to use RabbitMQ in your projects, including pitfalls to avoid.</p>

<p>The closing keynote <a href="https://joind.in/talk/view/14639">Behind the Scenes of Maintaining an Open Source Project</a> was done by <a href="https://twitter.com/seldaek">Jordi Boggiano</a> about how open source project looks behind the scenes. He went through different stages of it (maintenance, anger, etc.) including anecdotes and personal stories. Staying behind the screen we often forget about the world behind our backs and that open source is only possible thanks to the community and people who spend their energy &amp; time.</p>

<p>I enjoyed the conference a lot and really happy about attending it. It&rsquo;s was nice to put Twitter/GitHub profiles with real people. Would like to thank the organizers, speakers, audience for three great days of new experiences &amp; sharing knowledge. In the end I would like to borrow (in other words steal) the quote from <a href="https://twitter.com/michellesanver">Michelle Sanver</a> which summarizes what is a conference very well &ndash; &ldquo;<em><a href="https://blog.liip.ch/archive/2015/02/10/conferences-that-are-parties-with-talks-phpbenelux-and-sunshinephp.html">A conference is a party with talks</a></em>&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review of ZivaMind Meditation Course]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/review-zivamind-meditation-course"/>
    <updated>2015-06-18T15:29:48+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/review-of-zivamind-meditation-course</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If I notice something to be continuously mentioned, it might have some truth to it. When looking into that top performers (like <a href="http://fourhourworkweek.com/2015/02/02/arnold-schwarzenegger/">Tim Ferriss, Arnold Schwarzenegger</a>, etc.) do, most of the time the meditation is mentioned. <strong>As I would like to be top performer after I grow up meditation is something I want to have as a habit</strong>. Had a powerful experience once so know it can be a powerful tool.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/18736614889" title="Review of ZivaMind Meditation Course by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/1/308/18736614889_f916ca658e_z.jpg" width="640" height="320" alt="Review of ZivaMind Meditation Course"></a></p>

<p>The problem is what I&rsquo;m <strong>having problems finding one which would work for me</strong>. Most of them are spiritual. With some hairy guru, flowers and other elements which should bring peace &amp; bliss. For me the line between spiritual enough &amp; too spiritual is thin. I have nothing against it &amp; I&rsquo;m happy if it works for other people. For me, it makes me cringe. Just like the word God. (I like using it when cursing. Don&rsquo;t put any weight to it as it means nothing to me. Might throw away a great book just for using that word too much.) To give some anchor point to me even <a href="https://www.headspace.com/">Headspace application</a> is too spiritual. Just can&rsquo;t stomach that guru voice, it&rsquo;s me not you.</p>

<p>Another problem is what I always <strong>had problems keeping meditating for long</strong>. Would start strong, do it every day for a week or two. Then I will have a day or few where &ldquo;<em>I have no time</em>&rdquo; for it. Or the cheating will start making it more like a nap.</p>

<p>One day watched a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zC7a_gQB9YQ">Google talk with an Emily Fletcher about meditation</a>. Maybe her &ldquo;positivity&rdquo; was a bit too much. I don&rsquo;t like that in people. Think it&rsquo;s because if you took a scalpel deep enough into my brains you will find it&rsquo;s because I&rsquo;m not like that &amp; would love to be. A lot of points in the talk made sense to me.</p>

<p>After looking more into what Emily does decided to try her <a href="http://www.zivamind.com/">ZivaMind meditation course</a>. <strong>If you fail, try again</strong>.</p>

<p>The course isn&rsquo;t cheap (250$ at the time of purchase). But it&rsquo;s only if it wouldn&rsquo;t work, if it works that price would be a drop in the bucket.</p>

<p><strong>It&rsquo;s delivered in 8 days with some extras added</strong>. Some of the days you&rsquo;re asked to answer few questions to bring your awareness. Don&rsquo;t think that you only need 8 days to become a master and start flying around on your bliss. This is the time you will need to consume the lessons to be in position to continue the meditation practice by yourself. After 8 days you might still have a lot of questions. A lot of them are answered in a recorded call(s) (day 9 of course).</p>

<p>The great thing about the course I liked is that <strong>it almost has no spiritual stuff</strong>. It has the mantra which I will put in spiritual category. I don&rsquo;t mind it so much as it&rsquo;s used as a tool to anchor yourself when you start wondering too much. Found it helpful.</p>

<p><strong>I like delivery of course a lot</strong>. Like explaining that you don&rsquo;t need to do it for hours or become a monk to reap the benefits of meditation. It helps to calm yourself knowing that 15 minutes twice a day is something you can do. Of course if it won&rsquo;t work then meditation is out the window as becoming a monk won&rsquo;t help either. <strong>Showing how a meditation session might look is very helpful</strong>. After seeing it you stop beating yourself that you&rsquo;re doing it wrong or you will never be able to do it right or you think too much, etc.</p>

<p>The website application of the course could be better. For someone who works in web &amp; cares about security, receiving his password in email can lead to a heart attack. It doesn&rsquo;t remember that I have logged in so every day requires me to log back in.</p>

<p>A new day of meditation is enabled every 24 hours. Which I understand but don&rsquo;t think is a good choice. I think it would be better if a new one was made available after 16 hours. For first few days it wasn&rsquo;t an issue. After that I started waking up early and a new day wasn&rsquo;t available to me. Just make the change on the application, it&rsquo;s fine if mails are sent every 24 hours. And if someone is counting the end of 16 hours just to check the new video they have bigger problems.</p>

<p>One of the days contained a video about space. Have no efing idea what it was about or what it has to do with meditation. Some spiritual thought provoking time &ndash; yes, but I would rather it was not added.</p>

<p>In one video you&rsquo;re taught a breathing technique to help you meditate. Unfortunately, I can&rsquo;t do it. As someone who has only one nostril working most of the time, anything breathing related is uncomfortably painful. If you have never drowned, choked, suffocated &mdash; yes, I&rsquo;m that good at accidental suicides &mdash; it would be hard to explain the feeling.</p>

<p>The course provides audio files to help meditate for various reasons: sleep, travel, performance. They are helpful, but from that I noticed they have white noise during silent periods which makes it hard to concentrate. It could also have lite versions which contained less explanations (explanations are good for beginning). <strong>The video version of 15 minute meditation I found very helpful</strong>. Most of it is silence, but that I liked about them is that I don&rsquo;t have to keep eyes on the clock. Having a timer application running is not a problem. It&rsquo;s just a better quality meditation if I keep my eyes closed through it. It would be great if audio version of this was available (without white noise).</p>

<p><strong>The suggestion to use the last few minutes of meditation for gratitude is great</strong>. I have a habit of being grateful for 3 things each day, big or small. Makes you appreciate your life &amp; what you have a lot more. Those few minutes were I run through all the things that happened &amp; I&rsquo;m grateful for makes me even happier.</p>

<p>I just started the course &amp; need to keep it for longer to know if it works. So far my thoughts are positive and feeling good with sticking with it. Doubt that I will find anything better &amp; if it won&rsquo;t work then the problem is somewhere else. <strong>If like me you have problems with making meditation a habit I would suggest to try out the <a href="http://www.zivamind.com/">ZivaMind meditation course</a></strong>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - Phone STD &amp; Parks (part 2) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks"/>
    <updated>2015-06-03T09:55:35+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks-part-2-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After taking an inventory of what happened so far decided now was the time to:</p>

<ul>
<li>check where to find the places suggested by the host (shops, restaurants, etc.);</li>
<li>buy the local SIM card for internet;</li>
<li>get something to eat.</li>
</ul>


<p>I was in no hurry to start going through museums and similar places. I was here for two weeks and decided to spend the weekend just exploring the city. Also after I move to another place I will receive the museum card from my host, saving me some money &amp; time.</p>

<p>After a while I went inside one shop which looked like they were selling SIM cards. If you want to imagine the conversation better the merchant was Indian (like Russell Peters said &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t make stereotypes, I see them&rdquo;).</p>

<p>&ldquo;Hi, I would like a local SIM card with a data plan, do you have any?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Hi, yes, it will be 20 € please. What model is your phone?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;The Nexus 5 <em>*confused with a raised eyebrow*</em>, does it make any difference?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;I never had Nexus, I can do Apple, Samsung, Nokia. Here are the instructions how to install it. I don&rsquo;t know if it will work on your phone.&rdquo;</p>

<p>After some haggling we decided to try and if it will work, I will pay. If it will not work he will take the card back and I will not need to pay. Good deal, <em>I have nothing to lose after all, or so I thought</em>. After changing the card and rebooting the phone the language automatically changed to Dutch (without asking me about it), started installing some apps and if you enter the settings (to change the language or enable WiFi) the application would just close down. WTF?!? <em>I wasn&rsquo;t expecting my phone catching an STD</em>. I had doubts about myself, who knows were I might end sticking my USB stick in, but I didn&rsquo;t expect this happening to my phone. Thanked the shop keeper for trying and left without local SIM card.</p>

<p>Continued to keep going down the street as somewhere around here was a park (I love green &amp; blue colors on maps). At the same time trying to figure out how to at least change the language to English. What I found is what if you restart the phone you have about few seconds of browsing the settings app before it&rsquo;s closed. Not an easy task to change something in few seconds when you don&rsquo;t even know where it is. After a while I just gave up as this was unsustainable. Restarting the phone took about a minute and it provides only a few seconds which probably won&rsquo;t be enough. Another problem was what I was kind of lost, the GPS/maps application was in Dutch and without any cache. <em>The easy way would be just to go back, which is boring</em>. After calculating the direction I should move to I continued my travels.</p>

<p>After reaching a place which was close to the boat house stopped for some traditional Dutch pancakes. At first trying to think how to fix the phone. Soon changed that with just drinking my mint tea with honey and enjoying the fresh air. Decided my best choice would be to go back home, try to figure out how to fix my phone or at least to cache the map.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17333602178" title="Traditional Dutch Pancakes by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8879/17333602178_1f965387dc_z.jpg" width="474" height="640" alt="Traditional Dutch Pancakes"></a></p>

<p>The Google wasn&rsquo;t helpful with answers about what I should do. Except for step-by-step instructions where to find the languages. Which wasn&rsquo;t helpful as settings application wasn&rsquo;t working. In the end I was able to fix my phone. Not really sure why or how, but I was glad for settings application to start working allowing me to go back to English language. The fix was kind of simple. Inserted my original SIM card which doesn&rsquo;t work outside my country, but I&rsquo;m guessing the &ldquo;virus&rdquo; figured it was not able to do his thing and just left. Or something along those lines. It&rsquo;s a mystery to me. I was just glad for it to start working the way it&rsquo;s supposed to work. Except for antivirus being in English which I was able to change only after about a month.</p>

<p>Back in full gear went to look for that park again. Small, but nice park. As long as you don&rsquo;t step into any dog shit that is. Decided it&rsquo;s time to visit the Vondelpark park. It was the weekend and streets can get noisy from all the tourists who come to be loud, be stupid, be drunk, be unhappy and be back in 9-to-5 job on Monday. Don&rsquo;t get offended if any of those describe you. <em>I don&rsquo;t have anything against having some fun (choose your own definition)</em> or anything like that, I just don&rsquo;t think that because it&rsquo;s the weekend and you went to another country it allows you to be an idiot. <strong>I know common sense is dead, but try to find it</strong>.</p>

<p>The Vondelpark is wonderful. It&rsquo;s a large area with green zones, water and all kinds of people in it. If the day is sunny &amp; warm it&rsquo;s perfect to just lie down and relax, maybe with a book, maybe without one. It takes a while to walk through whole park, especially if you get lost as roads can sometime get confusing (they are wiggly). It has public toilets, refreshments (you can always bring your own), benches. It should take care of most of your needs. You will also meet some &ldquo;strange people&rdquo;, I call them &ldquo;crackers.&rdquo; Don&rsquo;t know why but this is what comes to my head then I think about them (in the voice of Eddie Griffin). I met three different categories during my two weeks. The first one being friendly ones which talk with you about something and  after a bit asks if maybe you could share some coins. The second one was similar to friendlies except I call them idiots. I try to be positive, but when you tell me about how hard their life is and they have no money for food because he wasted couple hundred euros yesterday in casino. Sorry, this is were I draw the line and walk away. I&rsquo;m not good enough yet to deal with this kind of situations. The third one are the aggressive kind and best to avoid as it wouldn&rsquo;t be surprising if one of them stabbed you (I have good imagination).</p>

<p>Before leaving the park stopped to listen to one guy playing incredible jazz music. Liked it so much that stopped to listen to it while talking with his friends. They were from Chile and damn, their language is beautiful. A bit later two other people stopped to listen to music and join the conversation. After a while a new guy mentioned that if someone wants Marilyn Monroe LSD he has some to sell. I would guess it would be an easy way to spice up my birthday and after listening to Tim Ferriss podcast I sometimes wonder that it would be a positive experience to experiment a little with psychedelic drugs. The thing is that some risks I like to take in the controlled environment. <em>Taking who knows what, with who knows who, who knows were for me personally isn&rsquo;t that comforting or something I couldn&rsquo;t live without</em>.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Amsterdam - Exploring the City](/amsterdam-exploring-city)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - First Experiences (part 1) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-first-experiences"/>
    <updated>2015-05-12T11:35:44+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-first-experiences-part-1-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>&ldquo;Why are you going to Amsterdam if you don&rsquo;t smoke?&rdquo;</em> A question from my friend before leaving, makes me smile every time I remember it. If you came here looking for some crazy juicy stories from Amsterdam, keep looking. I&rsquo;m sure a lot of (young) people go to Amsterdam exactly for sex, drugs &amp; alcohol. I chose to explore the other side of it: beautiful city, great culture &amp; museums.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t know what the series are about you can read the <a href="/testing-world-series-intro">intro</a>.</p>

<p>A few months before my birthday I was starting to think what I should get myself for it. It&rsquo;s not like I care a lot (any) about my birthday. It&rsquo;s just what most of the time I can remember what is the date so it&rsquo;s easy to assign some crazy gift/event with it (like testing operation table for the first time or quitting my job). The runner was to get a tattoo. I don&rsquo;t like or understand tattoos, but it would be another thing I done in life. Wondering that kind of tattoo? A black dot (probably below my belly button) and if someone would ask what it means (tattoo must have a meaning) the reply would be &ldquo;I dot F&hellip;ing give a S..t&rdquo; (aggressive, but effective). Then I remembered my promise to return to Amsterdam for at least a week. The first time I visited I was acting like some stupid tourist (going through shops, etc.) and it was only for half a day. From the map it looked like a great city with a lot to see. We have a winner!</p>

<p>I spent a lot of time trying to decide what kind of a trip it should be. First was thinking about traveling around whole Netherlands (it happened in a way, but you will read about it at the end). After some calculations decided to just take two weeks off, working as little as possible and just stay all that time in Amsterdam. Tickets purchased, places booked, map marked with places to visit (didn&rsquo;t think about keeping it so can&rsquo;t share it). Only need to wait until the end of June.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17521426095" title="Packed &amp; ready to go by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7683/17521426095_e7069aa254_z.jpg" width="637" height="640" alt="Packed &amp; ready to go"></a></p>

<p>Few hours later after a strangely pleasant flight (don&rsquo;t like them) was back in Eindhoven. A few years ago I lived in this city for a few weeks through ERASMUS. You can take the bus or the train to the Amsterdam. It costs about the same and it takes about the same amount of time. The bus is near the airport exit, but it looked like you should have a printed ticket for that (maybe someone knows if you can buy the ticket from a driver?) so just decided to use the train. At the same time I would grab something to eat at city center. While reading a cafe menu almost got hit by a car. <em>A great way to start your holidays/trip is on the front hood of a car as an ornament</em>. Maybe I lost my appetite or maybe the menu didn&rsquo;t had anything tasty and decided to try to reach Amsterdam before some other car tried to take a bite out of me.</p>

<p>Before you arrive to Netherlands &ndash; get a lot of € coins, a lot, like at least 20€ worth of coins. Why? You need them to buy the bus/train tickets and no one has any coins. You could pay with a debit/credit card, but I was against that as you get a 2% charge for paying with a card. Also I try to avoid having my card while trying and keep it at the place I&rsquo;m staying. <em>If I loose my wallet with the money in it I just lost my money, I can always get more at the ATM. If I loose my wallet with the card in it I&rsquo;m just left with that I have in cash. Just a safer choice in my opinion</em>. You can buy a ticket from the office with an extra charge. Now that I think about it the price is probably the same in the end.. Still stupid.. Forgot to add that some places accept only cash, some places accept only cards and some places I&rsquo;m not even sure accepts anything. I work with technology, I know it fails. What do you do when you can&rsquo;t accept card payments? Tell everyone to F&hellip; off and close down the shop? Well in short just <strong>know what you will be charged for paying with a card and always check which payment methods are available</strong>.</p>

<p>The trains have a free WiFi allowing you to contact your host about your arrival, search for information or just read the articles. Which I did as the first half part of the trip is boring. The second half starts where the sea should start so it&rsquo;s more interesting to look at the canals and ships. I have planed my way from the train station, but the more I looked at the map the more doubts I had about reaching it. Must be my paranoia, I&rsquo;m sure it will turn around somewhere and I will go to the train station. At least I thought so until the voice over the speakers went &ldquo;This is the last stop, please get out&rdquo;, crap. So, I&rsquo;m in the Schiphol airport. WiFi is not working anymore. Everything is in Dutch and I have no idea which bus goes to the city center. I guess I could always walk to it, it&rsquo;s only one screen away, the same distance as if walking to America. All the thoughts were gone once I found the tour mini-bus which was giving information about how to get to the city and selling the tickets.</p>

<p>While studying the map provided with the ticket I was starting to get doubts again about reaching the train station (<em>it can be confusing until you get your bearings around any new city</em>). Decided to just risk it and get out at what looked the closest stop to the place of my stay. Made the right choice and got out on the street I needed. The sun was shining and atmosphere was refreshing. It&rsquo;s nice to be back in Amsterdam, this city does have something special.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16901067473" title="Under attack by ducks! by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5329/16901067473_b3f0ea1c0c_z.jpg" width="474" height="640" alt="Under attack by ducks!"></a></p>

<p>That I love about traveling and booking your places through airbnb is what you can try some interesting houses without having to make a long term commitment. My first house &ndash; a house boat. Even if it&rsquo;s only for one day (it had some maintenance issues) it&rsquo;s a new experience. Somehow I missed checking the rest of the photos of my host and was expecting some tall guy. The door opens and I see someone who looks like Mr. Chow from Hangover movie, even his voice was similar. &ldquo;You&rsquo;re Andrew? Hi, you look different than in your photo. Come in, sorry, I&rsquo;m still hangover from yesterday, come in come in.&rdquo; After all the formalities of explaining rules and suggestions, I looked around and took a big breath of air overflowed with excitement. It&rsquo;s strange when you look out the window and water is like only a hands length away and when a big fleet of ducks start swimming your way for their payment of food. Can&rsquo;t even remember it without smiling. Another strange thing is tourists swimming in boats past your window, especially when you&rsquo;re peeing.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Amsterdam - Exploring the City](/amsterdam-exploring-city)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
