<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | ifdattic]]></title>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-06T17:40:09+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://ifdattic.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Marcinkevičius]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spain - Barcelona First Impressions (part 2) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/spain-barcelona-first-impressions"/>
    <updated>2016-02-10T11:23:43+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/spain-barcelona-first-impressions-part-2-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Even after 6 weeks in Spain I haven&rsquo;t got used to Spanish time. I have no idea when they work, when they sleep or do anything else; I just know it&rsquo;s not compatible with my personal clock. It&rsquo;s refreshing to walk around the city early in the morning without meeting anyone. Maybe I like the idea of the apocalypse where everyone dies or maybe I just like some personal space, but what I do know is that it&rsquo;s fun.</p>

<p>First things first, as I&rsquo;m the person who likes to be prepared the focus is to find the place where I should live. With the GPS cached on my phone and Barcelona being split into little squares it&rsquo;s not hard to follow the streets to find the one I&rsquo;ll be living at. The address had a strange &ldquo;º&rdquo; in it, but I didn&rsquo;t pay any attention to it. Well who cares, I&rsquo;m somewhere in the vicinity and I will figure out the rest when needed. As I will probably won&rsquo;t have cell phone coverage or internet, I asked my host to meet me at noon. A few hours till noon so it&rsquo;s a great time to explore the city (it&rsquo;s easy to do when you travel light).</p>

<p>The La Rambla main street is the main tourists street. I liked it for being great for people watching. Of course, because it&rsquo;s the main street people are not the only thing you see. You can also see some interesting activities going on, like cops running after a thief. And from what I read on the internet it gets even more interesting once the sun goes down. Following my tactics for walking (walk where your eyes look) I soon reach the sea. As someone who is always attracted by the water or by the sky, this is the great place to sit for a few minutes and relax.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/24100057912/in/album-72157663094134401/" title="12"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1441/24100057912_606493f9f5_c.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="12"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>As I was starting to get a feeling of the city, I made getting a local SIM card a priority. Having one could expand my opportunities. I had more success with this task than I had in the Netherlands, but not without glitches. First make sure you&rsquo;re getting the prepaid card, consultants are eager to sign you for a monthly contract. It&rsquo;s not so easy to understand that without asking, because even to get a prepaid SIM card you need to give your passport. Why do you need to make simple things so hard&hellip; After a while my card was set up and I could use it to call and connect to internet. Being used to my own country phone providers I missed that part that SMS is not included (only calls and data). I sent (or tried to as the host has not received them) a few messages to let my host know I will be at the place after I eat something.</p>

<p>The funny thing is that after eating I could not use my phone for calls (you just hear some words in Spanish before the call ends) or access the internet. I fixed that after a few days by putting some money in my account. This happened because I &ldquo;used&rdquo; my account before the plan was activated, so I was charged for those services, which made my balance negative which in turn freezes my account. <em>(facepalm) *deep breath out while holding fingers on the base of nose with eyes closed*</em>, &ldquo;fine, just fix it&rdquo; was my response to this BS.</p>

<p>Another funny thing is that in Barcelona you can find free WiFi everywhere. Unfortunately at all the places I could find you either have to download some app or you have to register with your personal details&hellip; And you will receive your login details to your email <em>(facepalm)</em>. Why do your have to make everything so complicated&hellip;</p>

<p>So, it&rsquo;s almost half an hour after the noon, I have no way of communicating. The great thing is that you start adapting fast when your ass is on fire (the good kind of stress). It didn&rsquo;t took me too long to figure out where the place I will be staying in is and meeting with my host.</p>

<p>The place I booked, well.. I start rising one eyebrow when I have to move through a narrow street which keeps you alert just in case someone decides to spill a piss pot out the window. The stairs to the room are great for snapping your neck off, good thing I&rsquo;m not drinking anymore, otherwise it could be dangerous. Also great that I travel light as someone traveling with a big suitcase would be spending at least half a day taking it up the stairs. The good thing about the room was that it had a private bathroom. Well actually it&rsquo;s the only good thing about the room. The vomit colored walls, Spanish melodramas from the rest of the house, knowing when someone used a bathroom, mosquitoes and a &ldquo;balcony&rdquo; which makes you think you&rsquo;re inside some third world country prison I didn&rsquo;t find that welcoming.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/24100060382/in/album-72157663094134401/" title="6"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1470/24100060382_bda8c4b1d8_c.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="6"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Well, it could be much worse and I guess it&rsquo;s an opportunity to apply some stoic philosophy, so after some regrouping went out to explore the city. The sun is shining, weather is great (and I just arrived from negative temperatures) and it&rsquo;s a wonderful day. While walking around the city it&rsquo;s still enjoyable to see some palms and parrots in them. It doesn&rsquo;t take long for that to become unnoticeable, but for a while it&rsquo;s something special. I wasn&rsquo;t able to find that street again, but it was fun finding a big sculpture of the cat. All the walking from time to time makes you want to sit down for a few minutes to relax. Which is not very enjoyable as you&rsquo;re attacked by a bunch of flies right away.</p>

<p>The beach is lively at the day like this and it&rsquo;s wonderful to relax in the sun. Of course expect your relax time to be constantly interrupted by suggestions for massage or drinks. After a while you also start to ignore the beach vendors and just automatically reply with NO. You can find some sand artists along the beach or to be flashed by some naked human genitalia, nothing out of ordinary.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/24181993166/in/album-72157663094134401/" title="45"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1548/24181993166_71454df5ff_c.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="45"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>In the evening expect to be harassed by food vendors. In Spain the tip isn&rsquo;t expected, but keep in mind that you will have to pay an extra fee if you eat in terrace/outside. I didn&rsquo;t find Spanish food to be that much to my liking. I enjoyed calamares and gambas (the small ones), but other than that I don&rsquo;t find the rest of the food that great. Also too much screwing around to get the food in your stomach. That I liked about eating in Spain is that most of the time you get some olives while waiting for your food. Could definitely do without the bread (and often it doesn&rsquo;t look that trustworthy). For drinks you can get a bucket of beer (cerveza) or sangria. Or for someone like me who stopped drinking your choice is a small bottle of water or cola.</p>

<p>After getting back to my room it felt more like being in a bar than in a private room. Loud music, applause, screams included free of charge. It didn&rsquo;t take too long to decide that I won&rsquo;t be able to work in this place for a week. I had to move. An hour later I had a new place booked, informed my host that I will be staying only till tomorrow and ready for more adventures.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Spain - Intro](/spain-intro)
* [Spain - Barcelona First Impressions](/spain-barcelona-first-impressions)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1O4N2tD)
* to be continued...
* [Intro to testing the world series](testing-world-series-intro)
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spain - Intro (part 1) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/spain-intro"/>
    <updated>2016-01-06T12:23:47+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/spain-intro-part-1-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After purchasing the tickets to a SymfonyCon in Madrid I decided it would be great way to explore Spain. In Lithuania during that time weather gets colder so this will let me enjoy summer for a bit longer. My trip was supposed to be from October 23rd to December 9th. Maybe not the warmest months in Spain, but for someone who doesn&rsquo;t enjoy when it&rsquo;s very hot it looked like it will be a pleasantly warm trip.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/24182297796/in/album-72157663094134401/" title="2014-spain-cover"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1675/24182297796_34b637327f_c.jpg" width="800" height="400" alt="2014-spain-cover"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Some might wonder why it was &ldquo;supposed&rdquo; to be during that time range. The reason is simple with two great lessons for traveling: <strong>don&rsquo;t oversleep your flight</strong> and <strong>adapt</strong>.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/24100061032/in/album-72157663094134401/" title="3"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1581/24100061032_55b0332923_c.jpg" width="450" height="800" alt="3"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Actually, I wasn&rsquo;t surprised when this happened as the beginning of the trip wasn&rsquo;t going so well. Almost forgot my passport and almost got into head-on car crash. And I knew I will have to learn this lesson sooner or latter. For people who might be thinking &ldquo;<em>what an idiot, oversleeping a flight after setting up 10 different alarms</em>,&rdquo; I completely agree with you. Just not much to do when you set it for PM, not AM. But you can be damn sure I won&rsquo;t allow this to happen again anytime soon. Now I&rsquo;m too paranoid and have multiple systems in place.</p>

<p>You would also want to adapt quickly to situations and react with a cool head. I won&rsquo;t lie, I had thought about just dropping the whole thing and going back home where it&rsquo;s safe and relaxing. <em>You can&rsquo;t succeed without failing</em>. Half an hour later I had bought new tickets, canceled the reservations I won&rsquo;t be able to take, booked new places to stay at and ready to go for a chilly morning walk to freshen my head. It might have added an extra expense of $1000, but I always laugh remembering it, while the people who hear it are recovering from the shock.</p>

<p>After a long 3 hours flight and enjoying a wonderful sunrise I&rsquo;m in Barcelona ready to be overwhelmed by new experiences. It&rsquo;s an early morning. Streets are almost empty and it&rsquo;s something indescribable to see palms and enormous buildings for the first time. Unfortunately it doesn&rsquo;t last for long as palms get filtered out just like ordinary street posts. Streets are dirty like everywhere else (cans, cigarette buts, etc.) and the buildings just give a feeling like they are trying to measure who has a bigger one (you know what).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/24208105595/in/album-72157663094134401/" title="5"><img src="https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1479/24208105595_6d13a8cc23_c.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="5"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Still, it&rsquo;s not everyday you travel hundreds of miles to a completely different country, and I&rsquo;m grateful for that.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Spain - Intro](/spain-intro)
* [Spain - Barcelona First Impressions](/spain-barcelona-first-impressions)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1O4N2tD)
* to be continued...
* [Intro to testing the world series](testing-world-series-intro)
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaving by Getting Lost (part 8) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/leaving-by-getting-lost"/>
    <updated>2015-12-15T09:11:02+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/leaving-by-getting-lost-part-8-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last day the weather was getting better and I thought about visiting a few other places I had on the list. Until I understood that I reached that point where I don&rsquo;t care anymore about the journey and just want to reach the destination. No point in getting over the head just to put another check mark on the list. Spent the rest of the day in the park, sitting &amp; relaxing until it was time to leave Amsterdam.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/23142641809" title="10495853_10202339209902188_6895619919232677953_o"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5756/23142641809_0d6602204c_c.jpg" width="800" height="400" alt="10495853_10202339209902188_6895619919232677953_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Unfortunately my journey got a little longer than I wanted. I think right after I bought the train ticket (I would have been told before buying if there were issues), something happened to the power lines (from what I was able to find out later) and the line between Amsterdam-Eindhoven was closed. At that time I didn&rsquo;t had a lot of experience riding trains and every information was in Dutch. Was walking around trying to figure out which train I should take and starting to get a feeling something is wrong. Got into one train, but my gut started to tell I should get out. After some time asked an employee which train is to Eindhoven and she told I have to get on that train (by pointing), go to Rotterdam and then go to Eindhoven.</p>

<p>Something was definitely wrong. I got in a full train and started browsing internet to see how my plans are changing. It looked like my 1.5 hours Amsterdam-Eindhoven trip in best case will be 1.5 hours Amsterdam-Rotterdam, wait for 30-60 minutes, 1.5 hours Rotterdam-Eindhoven. Crap. Oh well, not like I can change anything. Sit down and try to relax, you still have a long trip left.</p>

<p>A much longer trip than I expected. Towards the end I started to notice that the train might not go to main train station. Maybe I was wrong, but it looked like at one point it will start going in opposite direction and the last time I waited I ended up in an airport not a city center. It was time to make a decision and I chose to get out and walk the rest of the way (if I was right it would be a shorter walk than going all the way).</p>

<p>I was in a middle of nowhere and had about 30 minutes to walk 10 kilometers. If I was late I will need to wait about an hour for the next train which would also take longer than 1.5 hours to reach the Eindhoven. This trip got long enough so no thank you. At this point I was very happy about traveling alone and only with a backpack. Started looking at the map and taking long fast strides to get a chance to reach a train station on time. Looking for fastest way led me through roads, fields, shady neighborhoods, etc. Didn&rsquo;t care. Just kept on walking from time to time letting out a curse word and motivating myself with &ldquo;if you gonna be late I will punch you in the face, hard.&rdquo;</p>

<p>After I got the train station in my view it felt great and I was still on time. Of course waiting in the line to buy the ticket, seeing how slowly it was moving and how fast the watch arrow turned was nerving. Was able to buy the tickets, go to the WC and wait on platform one minute before the train arrived. Sat down, relaxed. All that was left was a 1.5 hours train ride and my journey is done.</p>

<p>Or so I thought. Contacted my airbnb host that I will arrive in a few hours and come to him after I got a glass of cold beer somewhere to relax my nerves. My host suggested that I won&rsquo;t take too long as a big storm (supposedly) will start at around 11PM. I thanked him for the warning, the day was already long without any extra surprises.</p>

<p>After leaving the train I bought a can of beer at the train station shop. The day was long enough without having to go to some noisy bar. 8 minutes of walk to the place of my stay for the night and this long day would be done. I left the train station, walking towards the traffic lights and after a few meters the rain starts drizzling. Nothing what would be bad for 8 minutes, but just in case I put on my jacket. After few more meters the rain starts pouring in buckets. Fuck! Spent the next 8 minutes sprinting and looking for non existent places to hide from the rain.</p>

<p>The host opens the doors and I&rsquo;m standing dripping water only with my underwear dry (so not the worst walk in the rain I had). He shows me around the place and at first I go to the shower. After which I&rsquo;m starting to feel like a human again. Open a can of beer and work for half an hour; just needed something to do where I would be in control.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16898784814/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10483184_10202339208222146_4097043738260715951_o"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8694/16898784814_3cddbf26de_c.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="10483184_10202339208222146_4097043738260715951_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>My room was in a 11th floor and in something that I would call a glass balcony. With a thunderstorm going outside at least I slept very well (rain, thunder, turbulence relaxes me &amp; helps me sleep). The next morning I took the bus to airport. Of course the ticket machine takes no paper money &amp; who the hell has coins (they are heavy). After going through all the bus and exchanging 5 euros in paper to about 3 euros in coins (didn&rsquo;t care anymore, just needed the ticket) I reached an airport.</p>

<p>While boarding the plane the hostess suggested that maybe I would like to take the exit row seat. My first thought &ndash; oh great, gonna get lost one more time, well at least I will have enough room for my legs until we crash. I sit down, turn on vocals chill-out music &amp; try to relax. Towards the landing the turbulence starts to pick up helping me to relax and add panic for others. When the following lyrics come up &ldquo;<em>I&rsquo;m falling down, I&rsquo;m falling fast.</em>&rdquo; I&rsquo;m not making this up, this would be too stupid to make up. I take report of my surroundings &ndash; had a fresh drink of water, nice music is playing in my head, sitting comfortably &ndash; screw it, we can crash, I&rsquo;m feeling happy now. Still couldn&rsquo;t stop myself from starting to chuckle from this situation. Which I find from side view might have looked a little disturbing. Well, we landed safely and this was the end of the trip.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think I would like to live in Amsterdam/Netherlands. If I started to drink &amp; smoke it might have extra points about living there, but still wouldn&rsquo;t sell me so easy on long term living. But after some time I noticed that I do like Amsterdam. It&rsquo;s a wonderful place &amp; walking around it for a week or few makes me happy.</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Amsterdam - Exploring the City](/amsterdam-exploring-city)
* [Amsterdam - Museums & Attractions](/amsterdam-museums-attractions)
* [Amsterdam Dungeon](/amsterdam-dungeon)
* [Amsterdam - More museums & RLD](/asmterdam-museums-rld)
* [Amsterdam - Natura Artis Magistra Zoo](/natura-artis-magistra-zoo)
* [Amsterdam - Getting Lost](/leaving-by-getting-lost)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* [Photo album from 2015](http://bit.ly/1m0XfxT)
* [Intro to testing the world series](testing-world-series-intro)
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Natura Artis Magistra Zoo (part 7) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/natura-artis-magistra-zoo"/>
    <updated>2015-11-18T18:29:16+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/natura-artis-magistra-zoo-part-7-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to visit the Hortus Botanicus and Natura Artis Magistra before leaving. Unfortunately the last few days of my stay was rainy and walking around in the rain didn&rsquo;t feel like an exciting way to spend time. The rain let down a little bit giving me chance to visit the zoo. At first I was thinking about skipping it. I seen animals in the cage before so it won&rsquo;t be anything interesting. This is what I thought, but I&rsquo;m glad I just did it anyway. The ticket isn&rsquo;t cheap, but for the value you get it&rsquo;s worth it. After buying the ticket was asked if I would like to buy the map and the money spent for it will be used to improve the elephant section. I try to avoid extras like guided tours, audio tours, etc., but elephants never did anything bad to me so why not, let&rsquo;s help the little guys/gals. The map doesn&rsquo;t hurt as the place is enormous.</p>

<p>The first thing I noticed is that animals are actually not in the cages. So you better behave as there is not a lot of protection between getting your ass kicked. Seeing camels walking around with a bunch of other animals and being separated only by a narrow line of water looks awesome, disturbing, relaxing. All at the same time. Walking by them is like walking through a bad neighborhood, you try to look like you belong there and are ready to run just in case. Walking past the birds gives a different reaction. It&rsquo;s all in my head, but I just wanted to run to them, start making motions from ground to air with my hands and shouting &ldquo;<em>Fly you fools!! Freedom, fly to freedom!!</em>&rdquo; I&rsquo;m sure if they could talk, their reaction to this would be &ldquo;<em>Go eF yourself!</em>&rdquo;</p>

<p>After calming myself down started to wander around the zoo, looking at animals, reading about them and just having good time. Too bad the tigers (I think) habitat was closed for renovations. Walked past the cages with parrots. I do dislike them. They are just too noisy for my taste. Around that time the rain started to pick up again. Fortunately I just reached the aquarium part of the zoo giving me shelter from it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17519025602/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10550111_10202330518924919_6303576271895424654_o"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8754/17519025602_ac7e0f45d7_c.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="10550111_10202330518924919_6303576271895424654_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The aquarium is nice with lots of colors. Got into an eye staring contest with a blue frog (wanted to find out if she&rsquo;s real or not). Until noticed that I got surrounded by a bunch of her friends and it was time for me to leave. You can see a bunch of strange fishes, some of which makes you think about against getting a diver&rsquo;s license. Just too many things which got away from the horror movie and would eat you.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17495048186/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10428183_10202330521404981_5355992987067705238_o"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7775/17495048186_36c9b0ab05_c.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="10428183_10202330521404981_5355992987067705238_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After wandering around the zoo for a little longer found the terrarium with spiders &amp; snakes &amp; other cute lovely pets. It would be great to visit them during the feeding time. Or if they would let you pet them (I&rsquo;m against that as it would be too much stress for the poor animal, but I just always like touching &amp; biting new/interesting things).</p>

<p>You start understanding they don&rsquo;t care too much about cages when you reach one of the &ldquo;inclusive areas&rdquo; you can travel through. The first one for me was the butterflies habitat. It&rsquo;s something like a small patch of a tropical forest you can walk around with butterflies flying all around you. In some places where there food for them and you could take a closer look. So far I can&rsquo;t compare it, but it was the first time experience on how the tropical forest might feel &amp; I liked to get that under my belt. Thanks to my imagination I was also expecting a velociraptor to run past me, but I guess you can&rsquo;t get everything you want. *Side note: After a year I visited Hortus Botanicus which allows you to experience different climate zones, still no velociraptors :(*</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17519020132/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10551528_10202330524125049_746054191702381928_o"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5460/17519020132_a1ea28907a_c.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="10551528_10202330524125049_746054191702381928_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Another open area where you can get closer to animals was the lemur patch. You can walk right past them and maybe get a massage if you sit down (maybe if you forgot to see the bite signs). They look cute enough, but I didn&rsquo;t trust them enough for that. Was nice to learn that they have hands similar to human hands, with fingers and everything. You live and learn. They can scream loud too.</p>

<p>Walking around found the wolf&rsquo;s habitat. Don&rsquo;t know why, but I adore them. Maybe because I met a wolf while walking alone in the forest when I was about 5-7 years old. Maybe for some other reason. I do find them beautiful &amp; royal animals. Too bad due to rain or other reasons it was hard to have a closer look at them.</p>

<p>After a while I reached a tropical house (I think it&rsquo;s how it&rsquo;s called). The signs about not letting out the animals and getting bitten didn&rsquo;t made me comfortable. If it wasn&rsquo;t safe they won&rsquo;t be allowing you to enter and with this thought I entered the house. I slowly started going in deeper, looking around to make sure no one attacks me by surprise and still not sure if I&rsquo;m allowed in here.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17521337305/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10497313_10202330523645037_7410082079628888463_o"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8835/17521337305_6df8a106c6_c.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="10497313_10202330523645037_7410082079628888463_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>There is two categories of animals I &ldquo;fear&rdquo; &ndash; rodents (rats, mice, etc.) &amp; amphibians (frogs, etc.). I&rsquo;m not sure why. I just don&rsquo;t like them. Even in the toy shop I will walk around them. I include (included actually from then) bats to the same category thinking of them as flying rats. When I was about in the middle of the house from the other part of it the bat started flying into me, flew past me, turned around and flew past me again. At that moment I was crouching on the floor with my hands on my head, not sure what I should do.</p>

<p>The zoo employees who were sitting and talking told me it&rsquo;s safe and I don&rsquo;t need to be afraid of them. Easy for you to say, I don&rsquo;t see monsters flying past your head (all in my head, enchanted by wicked imagination). We started talking and she took me to the tree where the bat was eating. Once you get close enough to punch them in the face they are actually cute monsters.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17333556728/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10494995_10202330525205076_2228704594717199738_o"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5442/17333556728_e295b0927f_c.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="10494995_10202330525205076_2228704594717199738_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>She helped me to find all the animals what are in the house and their stories. The big lizards and the small lizards. The monkeys, how one of them has a broken tail and another one just had a baby. That squirrel animal from Ice Age movie. We also talked about the zoo itself. Was nice to chat with her and at the end I was comfortable staying in that house. Still being alert to do a karate chop in case someone attacked. I know, I&rsquo;m paranoid.</p>

<p>I put my nose inside the birds house (which was adjacent). I&rsquo;m not a big fan of birds (they are too noisy for me) &amp; I didn&rsquo;t want to get bombarded by crap so turned around and left.</p>

<p>The zoo was close to closing time so I chose to go past the water birds habitat which ends near exit. For someone who can&rsquo;t (probably) swim and being surrounded by birds which looks like drug dealers it wasn&rsquo;t very comfortable walking through a narrow metal bridge (without anything to hang on). But it&rsquo;s a new experience.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17519040952/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10541062_10202330522805016_403624763809583833_o"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5468/17519040952_daa1a41dea_c.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="10541062_10202330522805016_403624763809583833_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m glad I didn&rsquo;t listen to the voice in my head (something I should do more often) and went to the zoo. It was a surprise and a new experience to walk so close to animals not in cages. If you get a chance I would suggest to check it out.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Amsterdam - Exploring the City](/amsterdam-exploring-city)
* [Amsterdam - Museums & Attractions](/amsterdam-museums-attractions)
* [Amsterdam Dungeon](/amsterdam-dungeon)
* [Amsterdam - More museums & RLD](/asmterdam-museums-rld)
* [Amsterdam - Natura Artis Magistra Zoo](/natura-artis-magistra-zoo)
* [Amsterdam - Getting Lost](/leaving-by-getting-lost)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* [Photo album from 2015](http://bit.ly/1m0XfxT)
* [Intro to testing the world series](testing-world-series-intro)
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - More museums &amp; RLD (part 6) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/asmterdam-museums-rld"/>
    <updated>2015-08-19T16:02:43+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-more-museums-and-rld-part-6-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Amsterdam also has an Ice Bar. The ticket includes a drink in the normal bar. When time for another group comes you see an instructional video, put on some special clothes and enter I would say a medium sized freezer. It contains a bar made from ice and a few ice sculptures, nothing fancy. You can get two drinks which is either beer or vodka with juice (or without). As you can get only one glass the host suggests to choose your first drink wisely as you might end drinking beer from a shot glass. Glasses are also made from ice. You have big gloves, but make sure you&rsquo;re holding it tightly as a lot of them end up on the ground. Even thought the jacket keeps you warm enough I wouldn&rsquo;t suggest shoes with thin soles, your feet will get freezing fast. Or at least don&rsquo;t stop moving. I found this a pleasant experience and if you drink it&rsquo;s worth a visit. Barcelona also has the Ice bar by the beach and would have visited it again except I wasn&rsquo;t drinking anymore at that time.</p>

<p>As for the Heineken factory museum I would suggest to skip it. Unless you&rsquo;re some college student which finds things like this interesting. I had my doubts about visiting it, but while walking past it decided what why not, maybe it will have something fun. What a waste of money &amp; time. The big part of it is commercials related material or some crappy touristy things. It has some learning elements about how the beer is made, but they are not that interesting to catch your attention. At one point there is some kind of a ride which might be fun except what you would need to wait at least 20 minutes for it so you just skip it. At the end you can choose if you want to get two glasses of beer or one which you can pour yourself (which also has an enormous line). I disliked this one and recommending to skip it. Rather go spend that money to visit <a href="/amsterdam-dungeon">Amsterdam Dungeon</a> for the second time.</p>

<p>You can also find Torture Museum in Amsterdam. It isn&rsquo;t expensive so if you have nothing better to do you might want to visit it. Most of the time you&rsquo;re just walking through badly lid corridors checking out some torturing instruments and reading info about them. Other than a few strange/painful torture devices there isn&rsquo;t much to do in this one.</p>

<p>I also visited a Jews Museum, more or less because I was walking past it. It&rsquo;s a nice museum. I&rsquo;m just not emotionally invested in what it has to offer for it to be of much interest. If you&rsquo;re a Jew or connected to this topic I&rsquo;m sure you would find it interesting. Choose yourself.</p>

<p>Farther away from the city center you can find the Tropenmuseum. Take the lift to the top floor and start exploring it. I would say it&rsquo;s an interesting museum and allows you to get some basic knowledge about cultures from around the world. From amazon tribes to American sixties. It allows you to get a feeling how it might felt to be in some pop cafe or inside a hut. It was a relaxing place to visit and my suggestion would be to check it out.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/18898883370/in/album-72157654947589872/" title="IMG_20150623_124804"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/491/18898883370_935ed9bae5_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="IMG_20150623_124804"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Near the NEMO science center is the maritime museum which isn&rsquo;t that easy to miss due to a big ship outside it. As in most places you will be asked to put your bag in the locker which in here is a bit trickier than in most places were you give it to someone or get a key for locker. This one is higher tech, but as long as you follow the instructions you should be fine. The building has many wings which has different expositions. Can&rsquo;t remember them all, but some of things which you will see is history of slavery and lot of ship models. I found that just wondering around felt relaxing as this place had a nice &ldquo;aura.&rdquo; The ship is a little modified replica of some real ship. Below deck you will find storage space and living quarters. Don&rsquo;t forget to jump into one of hammocks and let your legs rest for a minute. I could also say that the ship wasn&rsquo;t made for tall people so watch your head! Above deck you find living quarters of a captain, the kitchen, steering wheel (you can tell I&rsquo;m not an expert on ships). All in all I wouldn&rsquo;t say that museum has something out of ordinary to show, but I found it relaxing and suggest to visit it. Also if you would look at the ceiling you might see the cousin of WALL-E cleaning the windows.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17494913486/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10504882_10202278717229909_6840611522421956903_o"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5322/17494913486_f1f7bc9000_z.jpg" width="640" height="474" alt="10504882_10202278717229909_6840611522421956903_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Of course you can&rsquo;t talk about Amsterdam without mentioning Red Light District. Skip the rest of the article if this topic is not acceptable to you.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s so integrated into the city center that you will probably pass it even by accident. You should watch out were you&rsquo;re walking as sometimes you might get blinded by a nice pair and have an accident. If you came to Amsterdam for bodily pleasure there are enough choices to find something you like. I personally look at all this RLD like an equivalent of fast food restaurant: get in, get out, vomit around the corner. No, I&rsquo;m not against prostitution and just like prostitutes my stance is what it should be legal everywhere. I just look at sex in a different perspective and RLD approach is not for me. If you didn&rsquo;t come to visit red or blue lights, you will soon start filtering out all the knocks and invitations.</p>

<p>If you walk around the church you might notice a pair of breasts on the ground. On internet it&rsquo;s made much more exciting, in reality it&rsquo;s &ndash; meh. From the smell you might also notice that RLD has a lot of coffee shops. I always liked the look and smell of cannabis plant, but now the smell makes me nauseous and had to do some navigation to avoid it. RLD is beautiful and has a different feel after sun down. Of course you hear a lot more of &ldquo;pssst, cocaine?&rdquo; Just keep on walking.</p>

<p>I would suggest to visit the prostitution museum. Especially if you think it&rsquo;s a joke and if you&rsquo;re paying for these services you can be an ass and do whatever you want. If you&rsquo;re on the next side of scales where you think prostitution is an abomination, should be banned and punished you should also visit and maybe learn a thing or two. Wondering what is my view on this topic? In my opinion every one of us is a prostitute, the only difference is only which part of yourself you&rsquo;re selling. Just try to be a decent human being and that&rsquo;s it.</p>

<p>You will find Hash &amp; Hemp museum in RLD. It doesn&rsquo;t have anything very exciting, but it&rsquo;s a nice museum to visit. For a few euros you get a chance to see some artifacts from the old days. If you have time to spend I think it&rsquo;s worth it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16898968414/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="616541_10202287386206628_588367605791041677_o"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7776/16898968414_c727a355a4_z.jpg" width="607" height="640" alt="616541_10202287386206628_588367605791041677_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>RLD has a few establishments providing live shows. The best choice would be Casa Rosso Theater or it&rsquo;s the one I visited. It&rsquo;s not cheap at about €50 with two drinks, but in my opinion worth the experience. You enter something that looks like a small cinema/theater with seats split into two sections. Right section is for groups (from that I understood) containing noisy teenagers who already had a little too much to drink. The left side contains walk-ins ranging from normal looking people to some shady looking people in raincoats. Once in a while the waiters walk in bringing the drinks and taking the orders for drinks. I guess the place has to look the part and if I had to describe how the waiters looked like I would say take someone from 60&rsquo;s or 80&rsquo;s porn movies (I still have no idea how it should look, but it&rsquo;s the thought which comes to mind). The shows have a mix of a girl playing with herself, a pair having fun, strip with someone from the audience, games with audience participation. If you want to take part in the show avoid being a walk-in. Learned that I was right about Rammstein music being good for &ldquo;making love.&rdquo; Also that I should start exercising. A nice experience to put under your belt if you have €50 to spend and want a few giggles.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Amsterdam - Exploring the City](/amsterdam-exploring-city)
* [Amsterdam - Museums & Attractions](/amsterdam-museums-attractions)
* [Amsterdam Dungeon](/amsterdam-dungeon)
* [Amsterdam - More museums & RLD](/asmterdam-museums-rld)
* [Amsterdam - Natura Artis Magistra Zoo](/natura-artis-magistra-zoo)
* [Amsterdam - Getting Lost](/leaving-by-getting-lost)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* [Photo album from 2015](http://bit.ly/1m0XfxT)
* [Intro to testing the world series](testing-world-series-intro)
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
