<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Travel | ifdattic]]></title>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/categories/travel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-12-02T15:26:14+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://ifdattic.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Marcinkevičius]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Natura Artis Magistra Zoo (part 7) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/natura-artis-magistra-zoo"/>
    <updated>2015-11-18T18:29:16+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/natura-artis-magistra-zoo-part-7-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wanted to visit the Hortus Botanicus and Natura Artis Magistra before leaving. Unfortunately the last few days of my stay was rainy and walking around in the rain didn&rsquo;t feel like an exciting way to spend time. The rain let down a little bit giving me chance to visit the zoo. At first I was thinking about skipping it. I seen animals in the cage before so it won&rsquo;t be anything interesting. This is what I thought, but I&rsquo;m glad I just did it anyway. The ticket isn&rsquo;t cheap, but for the value you get it&rsquo;s worth it. After buying the ticket was asked if I would like to buy the map and the money spent for it will be used to improve the elephant section. I try to avoid extras like guided tours, audio tours, etc., but elephants never did anything bad to me so why not, let&rsquo;s help the little guys/gals. The map doesn&rsquo;t hurt as the place is enormous.</p>

<p>The first thing I noticed is that animals are actually not in the cages. So you better behave as there is not a lot of protection between getting your ass kicked. Seeing camels walking around with a bunch of other animals and being separated only by a narrow line of water looks awesome, disturbing, relaxing. All at the same time. Walking by them is like walking through a bad neighborhood, you try to look like you belong there and are ready to run just in case. Walking past the birds gives a different reaction. It&rsquo;s all in my head, but I just wanted to run to them, start making motions from ground to air with my hands and shouting &ldquo;<em>Fly you fools!! Freedom, fly to freedom!!</em>&rdquo; I&rsquo;m sure if they could talk, their reaction to this would be &ldquo;<em>Go eF yourself!</em>&rdquo;</p>

<p>After calming myself down started to wander around the zoo, looking at animals, reading about them and just having good time. Too bad the tigers (I think) habitat was closed for renovations. Walked past the cages with parrots. I do dislike them. They are just too noisy for my taste. Around that time the rain started to pick up again. Fortunately I just reached the aquarium part of the zoo giving me shelter from it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17519025602/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10550111_10202330518924919_6303576271895424654_o"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8754/17519025602_ac7e0f45d7_c.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="10550111_10202330518924919_6303576271895424654_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>The aquarium is nice with lots of colors. Got into an eye staring contest with a blue frog (wanted to find out if she&rsquo;s real or not). Until noticed that I got surrounded by a bunch of her friends and it was time for me to leave. You can see a bunch of strange fishes, some of which makes you think about against getting a diver&rsquo;s license. Just too many things which got away from the horror movie and would eat you.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17495048186/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10428183_10202330521404981_5355992987067705238_o"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7775/17495048186_36c9b0ab05_c.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="10428183_10202330521404981_5355992987067705238_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>After wandering around the zoo for a little longer found the terrarium with spiders &amp; snakes &amp; other cute lovely pets. It would be great to visit them during the feeding time. Or if they would let you pet them (I&rsquo;m against that as it would be too much stress for the poor animal, but I just always like touching &amp; biting new/interesting things).</p>

<p>You start understanding they don&rsquo;t care too much about cages when you reach one of the &ldquo;inclusive areas&rdquo; you can travel through. The first one for me was the butterflies habitat. It&rsquo;s something like a small patch of a tropical forest you can walk around with butterflies flying all around you. In some places where there food for them and you could take a closer look. So far I can&rsquo;t compare it, but it was the first time experience on how the tropical forest might feel &amp; I liked to get that under my belt. Thanks to my imagination I was also expecting a velociraptor to run past me, but I guess you can&rsquo;t get everything you want. *Side note: After a year I visited Hortus Botanicus which allows you to experience different climate zones, still no velociraptors :(*</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17519020132/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10551528_10202330524125049_746054191702381928_o"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5460/17519020132_a1ea28907a_c.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="10551528_10202330524125049_746054191702381928_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Another open area where you can get closer to animals was the lemur patch. You can walk right past them and maybe get a massage if you sit down (maybe if you forgot to see the bite signs). They look cute enough, but I didn&rsquo;t trust them enough for that. Was nice to learn that they have hands similar to human hands, with fingers and everything. You live and learn. They can scream loud too.</p>

<p>Walking around found the wolf&rsquo;s habitat. Don&rsquo;t know why, but I adore them. Maybe because I met a wolf while walking alone in the forest when I was about 5-7 years old. Maybe for some other reason. I do find them beautiful &amp; royal animals. Too bad due to rain or other reasons it was hard to have a closer look at them.</p>

<p>After a while I reached a tropical house (I think it&rsquo;s how it&rsquo;s called). The signs about not letting out the animals and getting bitten didn&rsquo;t made me comfortable. If it wasn&rsquo;t safe they won&rsquo;t be allowing you to enter and with this thought I entered the house. I slowly started going in deeper, looking around to make sure no one attacks me by surprise and still not sure if I&rsquo;m allowed in here.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17521337305/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10497313_10202330523645037_7410082079628888463_o"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8835/17521337305_6df8a106c6_c.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="10497313_10202330523645037_7410082079628888463_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>There is two categories of animals I &ldquo;fear&rdquo; &ndash; rodents (rats, mice, etc.) &amp; amphibians (frogs, etc.). I&rsquo;m not sure why. I just don&rsquo;t like them. Even in the toy shop I will walk around them. I include (included actually from then) bats to the same category thinking of them as flying rats. When I was about in the middle of the house from the other part of it the bat started flying into me, flew past me, turned around and flew past me again. At that moment I was crouching on the floor with my hands on my head, not sure what I should do.</p>

<p>The zoo employees who were sitting and talking told me it&rsquo;s safe and I don&rsquo;t need to be afraid of them. Easy for you to say, I don&rsquo;t see monsters flying past your head (all in my head, enchanted by wicked imagination). We started talking and she took me to the tree where the bat was eating. Once you get close enough to punch them in the face they are actually cute monsters.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17333556728/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10494995_10202330525205076_2228704594717199738_o"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5442/17333556728_e295b0927f_c.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="10494995_10202330525205076_2228704594717199738_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>She helped me to find all the animals what are in the house and their stories. The big lizards and the small lizards. The monkeys, how one of them has a broken tail and another one just had a baby. That squirrel animal from Ice Age movie. We also talked about the zoo itself. Was nice to chat with her and at the end I was comfortable staying in that house. Still being alert to do a karate chop in case someone attacked. I know, I&rsquo;m paranoid.</p>

<p>I put my nose inside the birds house (which was adjacent). I&rsquo;m not a big fan of birds (they are too noisy for me) &amp; I didn&rsquo;t want to get bombarded by crap so turned around and left.</p>

<p>The zoo was close to closing time so I chose to go past the water birds habitat which ends near exit. For someone who can&rsquo;t (probably) swim and being surrounded by birds which looks like drug dealers it wasn&rsquo;t very comfortable walking through a narrow metal bridge (without anything to hang on). But it&rsquo;s a new experience.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17519040952/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10541062_10202330522805016_403624763809583833_o"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5468/17519040952_daa1a41dea_c.jpg" width="600" height="800" alt="10541062_10202330522805016_403624763809583833_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m glad I didn&rsquo;t listen to the voice in my head (something I should do more often) and went to the zoo. It was a surprise and a new experience to walk so close to animals not in cages. If you get a chance I would suggest to check it out.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Amsterdam - Exploring the City](/amsterdam-exploring-city)
* [Amsterdam - Museums & Attractions](/amsterdam-museums-attractions)
* [Amsterdam Dungeon](/amsterdam-dungeon)
* [Amsterdam - More museums & RLD](/asmterdam-museums-rld)
* [Amsterdam - Natura Artis Magistra Zoo](/natura-artis-magistra-zoo)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - More museums &amp; RLD (part 6) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/asmterdam-museums-rld"/>
    <updated>2015-08-19T16:02:43+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-more-museums-and-rld-part-6-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Amsterdam also has an Ice Bar. The ticket includes a drink in the normal bar. When time for another group comes you see an instructional video, put on some special clothes and enter I would say a medium sized freezer. It contains a bar made from ice and a few ice sculptures, nothing fancy. You can get two drinks which is either beer or vodka with juice (or without). As you can get only one glass the host suggests to choose your first drink wisely as you might end drinking beer from a shot glass. Glasses are also made from ice. You have big gloves, but make sure you&rsquo;re holding it tightly as a lot of them end up on the ground. Even thought the jacket keeps you warm enough I wouldn&rsquo;t suggest shoes with thin soles, your feet will get freezing fast. Or at least don&rsquo;t stop moving. I found this a pleasant experience and if you drink it&rsquo;s worth a visit. Barcelona also has the Ice bar by the beach and would have visited it again except I wasn&rsquo;t drinking anymore at that time.</p>

<p>As for the Heineken factory museum I would suggest to skip it. Unless you&rsquo;re some college student which finds things like this interesting. I had my doubts about visiting it, but while walking past it decided what why not, maybe it will have something fun. What a waste of money &amp; time. The big part of it is commercials related material or some crappy touristy things. It has some learning elements about how the beer is made, but they are not that interesting to catch your attention. At one point there is some kind of a ride which might be fun except what you would need to wait at least 20 minutes for it so you just skip it. At the end you can choose if you want to get two glasses of beer or one which you can pour yourself (which also has an enormous line). I disliked this one and recommending to skip it. Rather go spend that money to visit <a href="/amsterdam-dungeon">Amsterdam Dungeon</a> for the second time.</p>

<p>You can also find Torture Museum in Amsterdam. It isn&rsquo;t expensive so if you have nothing better to do you might want to visit it. Most of the time you&rsquo;re just walking through badly lid corridors checking out some torturing instruments and reading info about them. Other than a few strange/painful torture devices there isn&rsquo;t much to do in this one.</p>

<p>I also visited a Jews Museum, more or less because I was walking past it. It&rsquo;s a nice museum. I&rsquo;m just not emotionally invested in what it has to offer for it to be of much interest. If you&rsquo;re a Jew or connected to this topic I&rsquo;m sure you would find it interesting. Choose yourself.</p>

<p>Farther away from the city center you can find the Tropenmuseum. Take the lift to the top floor and start exploring it. I would say it&rsquo;s an interesting museum and allows you to get some basic knowledge about cultures from around the world. From amazon tribes to American sixties. It allows you to get a feeling how it might felt to be in some pop cafe or inside a hut. It was a relaxing place to visit and my suggestion would be to check it out.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/18898883370/in/album-72157654947589872/" title="IMG_20150623_124804"><img src="https://farm1.staticflickr.com/491/18898883370_935ed9bae5_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="IMG_20150623_124804"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Near the NEMO science center is the maritime museum which isn&rsquo;t that easy to miss due to a big ship outside it. As in most places you will be asked to put your bag in the locker which in here is a bit trickier than in most places were you give it to someone or get a key for locker. This one is higher tech, but as long as you follow the instructions you should be fine. The building has many wings which has different expositions. Can&rsquo;t remember them all, but some of things which you will see is history of slavery and lot of ship models. I found that just wondering around felt relaxing as this place had a nice &ldquo;aura.&rdquo; The ship is a little modified replica of some real ship. Below deck you will find storage space and living quarters. Don&rsquo;t forget to jump into one of hammocks and let your legs rest for a minute. I could also say that the ship wasn&rsquo;t made for tall people so watch your head! Above deck you find living quarters of a captain, the kitchen, steering wheel (you can tell I&rsquo;m not an expert on ships). All in all I wouldn&rsquo;t say that museum has something out of ordinary to show, but I found it relaxing and suggest to visit it. Also if you would look at the ceiling you might see the cousin of WALL-E cleaning the windows.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17494913486/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10504882_10202278717229909_6840611522421956903_o"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5322/17494913486_f1f7bc9000_z.jpg" width="640" height="474" alt="10504882_10202278717229909_6840611522421956903_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>Of course you can&rsquo;t talk about Amsterdam without mentioning Red Light District. Skip the rest of the article if this topic is not acceptable to you.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s so integrated into the city center that you will probably pass it even by accident. You should watch out were you&rsquo;re walking as sometimes you might get blinded by a nice pair and have an accident. If you came to Amsterdam for bodily pleasure there are enough choices to find something you like. I personally look at all this RLD like an equivalent of fast food restaurant: get in, get out, vomit around the corner. No, I&rsquo;m not against prostitution and just like prostitutes my stance is what it should be legal everywhere. I just look at sex in a different perspective and RLD approach is not for me. If you didn&rsquo;t come to visit red or blue lights, you will soon start filtering out all the knocks and invitations.</p>

<p>If you walk around the church you might notice a pair of breasts on the ground. On internet it&rsquo;s made much more exciting, in reality it&rsquo;s &ndash; meh. From the smell you might also notice that RLD has a lot of coffee shops. I always liked the look and smell of cannabis plant, but now the smell makes me nauseous and had to do some navigation to avoid it. RLD is beautiful and has a different feel after sun down. Of course you hear a lot more of &ldquo;pssst, cocaine?&rdquo; Just keep on walking.</p>

<p>I would suggest to visit the prostitution museum. Especially if you think it&rsquo;s a joke and if you&rsquo;re paying for these services you can be an ass and do whatever you want. If you&rsquo;re on the next side of scales where you think prostitution is an abomination, should be banned and punished you should also visit and maybe learn a thing or two. Wondering what is my view on this topic? In my opinion every one of us is a prostitute, the only difference is only which part of yourself you&rsquo;re selling. Just try to be a decent human being and that&rsquo;s it.</p>

<p>You will find Hash &amp; Hemp museum in RLD. It doesn&rsquo;t have anything very exciting, but it&rsquo;s a nice museum to visit. For a few euros you get a chance to see some artifacts from the old days. If you have time to spend I think it&rsquo;s worth it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" data-header="false" data-footer="false" data-context="false"  href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16898968414/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="616541_10202287386206628_588367605791041677_o"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7776/16898968414_c727a355a4_z.jpg" width="607" height="640" alt="616541_10202287386206628_588367605791041677_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>RLD has a few establishments providing live shows. The best choice would be Casa Rosso Theater or it&rsquo;s the one I visited. It&rsquo;s not cheap at about €50 with two drinks, but in my opinion worth the experience. You enter something that looks like a small cinema/theater with seats split into two sections. Right section is for groups (from that I understood) containing noisy teenagers who already had a little too much to drink. The left side contains walk-ins ranging from normal looking people to some shady looking people in raincoats. Once in a while the waiters walk in bringing the drinks and taking the orders for drinks. I guess the place has to look the part and if I had to describe how the waiters looked like I would say take someone from 60&rsquo;s or 80&rsquo;s porn movies (I still have no idea how it should look, but it&rsquo;s the thought which comes to mind). The shows have a mix of a girl playing with herself, a pair having fun, strip with someone from the audience, games with audience participation. If you want to take part in the show avoid being a walk-in. Learned that I was right about Rammstein music being good for &ldquo;making love.&rdquo; Also that I should start exercising. A nice experience to put under your belt if you have €50 to spend and want a few giggles.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Amsterdam - Exploring the City](/amsterdam-exploring-city)
* [Amsterdam - Museums & Attractions](/amsterdam-museums-attractions)
* [Amsterdam Dungeon](/amsterdam-dungeon)
* [Amsterdam - More museums & RLD](/asmterdam-museums-rld)
* [Amsterdam - Natura Artis Magistra Zoo](/natura-artis-magistra-zoo)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - Amsterdam Dungeon (part 5) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-dungeon"/>
    <updated>2015-08-12T19:09:26+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-amsterdam-dungeon-part-5-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The most enjoyable place I visited was the Amsterdam Dungeon, oh it was amazing. My suggestion would be just to find when the next play is and come a bit before that time. Even though it&rsquo;s funny to listen to the ghost in the cage, he starts repeating after a while and it&rsquo;s too loud to have a normal conversation with other prisoners. I would try to not disclose too much information about it (spoilers). I will have to write about some fun moments I had in there. This also contains some gruesome parts so you might want to skip it if it&rsquo;s not your thing. Warning provided, let the fun begin.</p>

<p></p>

<p>At first the group was split and I was expecting some cheap thrills, like a skeleton dropping out of the ceiling or something like that. After an elevator ride down you&rsquo;re some place looking like a torture dungeon. Some animatronics, spiked chair and stuff like that. Well if this is it then it will be boring, very boring. After a few minutes the sound of dragging chain begins and the door opens. I would say the actors are professional and react well to all the small problems. I feel a little bad about them because hearing them &ldquo;talk loudly / scream&rdquo; my own throat starts hurting; well they are probably used to it.</p>

<p>I take the front row seat. One from the group is chosen to be tortured and after some acting the lights go out. The voice starts praying in random places. Some screams from the group in random places and then something happened which made me thing &ldquo;OK, this might be fun after all.&rdquo; To better know why I liked this attraction is what I feel refreshed by &ldquo;seeing fear in other people eyes.&rdquo; Don&rsquo;t imagine me as some kind of monster who runs down the street with a chainsaw after the sun goes down; just for some reason it makes me smile and refreshed. OK, I&rsquo;m not explaining this well, fine, just imagine me running down the street with a chainsaw, brrrm brrrrm brrrrrrrrrrrrrrmmmmmm. It&rsquo;s all fun and games until someone loses the hand :D</p>

<p>After this one we went to a tavern, learning some history, getting few simple scares, etc. The tavern wench warned about not trusting anyone as sailors end up in ships because they wrote their name selling their soul. Then one from the group was asked to come and write his name. Which he did (oh come on, weren&rsquo;t you listening about not trusting anyone and not writing your name). Then she displays that he was tricked and now he will be going to work in the ship. But here&rsquo;s your chance to save your soul and if you open not a skull picture from three choices you will be free. Otherwise everyone will be going to the ship. Oh come on, this one is easy, you choose one, tell to open the other two and win, but no.. She mixes the choices, he chooses one of them, it&rsquo;s the skull and everyone is going to a ship.</p>

<p>The next room is below the ship deck and the pirate is explaining her life story, what a tasty soup rats make and choosing the jobs for everyone. Then she points at me and says &ldquo;You, come here. What is your name?&rdquo;. Me &ldquo;Andrew&rdquo;. She &ldquo;Who cares, from now on your name will be Bobby. You can&rsquo;t trust anyone on this ship, especially the traitors. Now, everyone point a finger at Bobby and shout TRAITOR!!!&rdquo;. A few people point their fingers and very silently and timidly start saying &ldquo;Traitor.&rdquo; At this point I was sure I will be having as much fun from this attraction as possible. I start lifting my hands in encouragement and shout &ldquo;Oh come on, you can do better!!&rdquo; Now everyone reacts a little better, still a little too much zombie like for my liking. The pirate gives me a rag and tells from now on my job is to clean the cannons and points to one of them. I start shining it off and soon enough it shoots. &ldquo;What have you done?! I told you to clean the cannon, not to shoot it!&rdquo; &ldquo;Premature detonation, it happens, it&rsquo;s not my fault!&rdquo; &ldquo;Give me back the rag!&rdquo; &ldquo;NO!!&rdquo; at this point we had a short discussion about who will keep the rag. She explains that as Bobby is the traitor he has to be tortured and puts me on the chair with a white sheet in front of me. When she asks something and strikes the hammer behind my head. I would guess that everyone else at that point was enjoying a nice splash of my brain on the front of the sheet. Then she does the same thing again. Then tells me to open my legs wide. Attractions like this are just like jumping with parachute. They are made to be safe as it&rsquo;s bad marketing when something happens to customers, but you never know that might happen *splash*. Lets just say I looked her in the eyes which said &ldquo;You better not F***ing miss,&rdquo; I might not care about my balls, but I don&rsquo;t feel like acting as a snake for the rest of the day. She hits between my legs, a cannon shoots and lets just say something happens, everyone has to abandon the ship. She takes everyone to the exit, explaining what to do. Due to my personally I choose not to stay at my current place, just get up and casually start leaving the ship. The pirate returns, notices I&rsquo;m gone, stays confused for a few seconds, then runs back to the exit and shouts &ldquo;If you will see Bobby on the shore.. Kill him!!&rdquo; Made me chuckle, my kind of girl.</p>

<p>I found a transition a little strange, but we ended in some kind of hospital or morgue or something like that. The cleaner explained that we shouldn&rsquo;t be here and it will be bad if the master found us. But as the master was away why don&rsquo;t everyone come closer so we could explore the corpse on the table. I went close enough to stick my nose in the stomach of the corpse, the rest of a group needed a few more invitations. He invited one from the group to hold the bucket and then started taking away the parts of a corpse. &ldquo;Here is the spleen.&rdquo; He pressed it and something wet hit me on the forehead. Someone from the group shouted &ldquo;Oh S<strong>t!!&rdquo; and the cleaner replied &ldquo;No S</strong>t, just piss.&rdquo; The master returned  and told us to hide in the next room which was full of corpses. After a few more scares we moved to the next room.</p>

<p>This time the theme was a trial and thought it had a few funny moments it didn&rsquo;t leave a lasting impression. The next room was some story about witches being burned and then going through a labyrinth. After the labyrinth we were at the city alley with a stake ready for burning a witch. After some talking one girl from the group was chosen and tied to a stake. Maybe not everyone understands what this is safe fun with possible consequences, but seeing the fear in the eyes of that girl about to be burned was something *take a deep breath* &hellip; Well I can&rsquo;t find the words to explain it. A big fire starts roaring, it stops after a bit and only a skeleton left on the stake. I guess you can&rsquo;t save all, time to move to the next live show.</p>

<p>We enter a room in the house and an actor tells us to sit before he could tell the story of this house. I scan the room and choose the seat by the chest as in my opinion it should provide the most fun. I wasn&rsquo;t wrong. I also do the same thing when I enter any room. Just look for a place which will be comfortable enough and would provide a best survivability chance in case some madmen came in through the door shooting/stabbing everyone in his sight. An actor tells a story about a sister killing a sister, hiding her in the basement and if you visit the house on the day she was killed you might see her ghost. As it happens today is the day of her death and then basement door starts banging. The lights go out. Now if you watch &ldquo;horror movies&rdquo; (in quotes because I have my opinion about that) just imagine the scene were it&rsquo;s pitch black, at some points in time a light(ing) flashes so you could see something scary. Fun.</p>

<p></p>

<p>This is the end of the attraction. Unless you&rsquo;re some sensitive person who starts running up the ceiling every time something makes a sound (scaring everyone else) I would highly suggest visiting Amsterdam Dungeon. So much fun!</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Amsterdam - Exploring the City](/amsterdam-exploring-city)
* [Amsterdam - Museums & Attractions](/amsterdam-museums-attractions)
* [Amsterdam Dungeon](/amsterdam-dungeon)
* [Amsterdam - More museums & RLD](/asmterdam-museums-rld)
* [Amsterdam - Natura Artis Magistra Zoo](/natura-artis-magistra-zoo)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - Museums &amp; Attractions (part 4) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-museums-attractions"/>
    <updated>2015-07-16T09:29:22+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-museums-and-attractions-part-4-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I won&rsquo;t remember that I did in chronological order. Will try to write about the places I visited and my thoughts about them in general.</p>

<p>As now I had museum card it was time to start visiting museums. My suggestion is to either ask your host if he has one or maybe buy it. Depending on how long you&rsquo;re staying and how much you want to visit (Amsterdam card might also work). It&rsquo;s great because if you&rsquo;re visiting a lot of places it can save you a lot. You also don&rsquo;t need to wait in general queue and most of the time can just go in (going through a special queue which rarely has any people).</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16901087803/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10448519_10202296476393877_511676680794428938_o"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8868/16901087803_ccdc32a729_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="10448519_10202296476393877_511676680794428938_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t visited it this time, but I would suggest to visit the sex museum which is near train station. The ticket is cheap and you will find a lot of funny items in there.</p>

<p>Van Gogh museum I found interesting. It can be hectic at times with people making long queues. If you just gonna enjoy the paintings themselves, read only about the ones which make you really interested and be unconventional (going opposite direction than everyone) it can be easy to navigate it. Some paintings I liked, others not so much. Even thought after seeing the paintings I think he was a good artist I don&rsquo;t really care about that. That fascinates (I knew this before visiting museum) me about Van Gogh is his choice to paint every day. This is the great reminder that if you do something every day the compounding interest will pay off in the long run. You could also see that he experimented a lot. This is a great idea to keep in the back of your mind, not just do the same thing you did hundreds of time, but to be brave and try something new. I also found his &ldquo;mental problems&rdquo; interesting and would have enjoyed to get more information about it. My recommendation for this museum &ndash; visit it.</p>

<p>Close by is the Rijksmuseum which is hard to miss. You might go by it even if you&rsquo;re not planing on visiting it. I think the toilets are in public space (as far as I remember) so it&rsquo;s an extra reason to visit it (especially for female visitors as they can&rsquo;t take a leek in the street). The museum is big. As I missed where you could get a map navigating it was a bit of a challenge trying to decide if you went down this corridor or not. It&rsquo;s split into many cultures / times / purpose blocks so you will see a lot of different things. Parts of it can be explored in a relaxing manner. Parts of it are so saturated with tourists that you just want to get away as far as possible (especially the paintings). I think the book lovers would especially like the library as at least my first thought after entering it was &ldquo;I want this room.&rdquo; At least before I remembered I&rsquo;m allergic to things. It will take a while and some legwork to visit all museum, but I enjoyed it and suggest to visit it.</p>

<p><a data-flickr-embed="true" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17333620578/in/album-72157652211723419/" title="10448686_10202296477433903_6185703472155902306_o"><img src="https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8727/17333620578_d4fbced7fa_z.jpg" width="640" height="480" alt="10448686_10202296477433903_6185703472155902306_o"></a><script async src="http://ifdattic.com//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js" charset="utf-8"></script></p>

<p>If your stay in Amsterdam is short and you need to optimize your visiting this general area is a great start. You have the Rijksmuseum with small a park (a nice place to sit down, relax and read a book). On the right side you have the Van Gogh museum. Between them is the small pool and a park and a big letter sign. On the right you also have some other museums.</p>

<p>For me I didn&rsquo;t find the diamonds museum that much interesting. That is because of my personality. I just can&rsquo;t understand the point of paying so much for some shiny, useless (then used as a jewelry) peace of stone. For me it&rsquo;s worth as much as some fake stone for a few bucks. They still look the same and as you won&rsquo;t be sawing any walls they both serve the same purpose of being useless. If you have some free time to kill you might go visit it, it wasn&rsquo;t the worst place I visited.</p>

<p>Close by you will find House of Bols, the Cocktail &amp; Genever Experience museum. Which I visited mostly because of &ldquo;learn something and get drunk, sure, why not&rdquo; (being sober wasn&rsquo;t on my plan at that point in life). I would just suggest to skip this one. It isn&rsquo;t cheap, you won&rsquo;t learn a lot and most of it feels like being in a big commercial and the drink at the end isn&rsquo;t that good (at least mine wasn&rsquo;t). Rather buy some snacks, a bottle of wine and go to Vondelpark which is close by. Have a picnic. If you would like to eat behind a table there is a street which whole focus is on food. Just can&rsquo;t remember where, but if you would walk past it you would notice as everyone is trying to get you inside. Walking away often is met with additions for free drink or some other way to sweeten the deal.</p>

<p>As my walk from the place I was staying to central streets always led through Amsterdam museum I decided to visit at some point. Not for long. I found it confusing (navigation) and requiring a lot of attention/effort. It soon looked like something I&rsquo;m not enjoying and just left. Your experience may vary.</p>

<p>In the center square is Madame Tussauds wax museum. I was trying to decide if I should visit, but in the end decided to skip it. Mostly because seeing &ldquo;From this point on you have only to wait 20 minutes.&rdquo; How about, No. Also, looking at wax sculptures of the people I don&rsquo;t care about isn&rsquo;t something I find exciting. Especially when you can see much more excitement by walking down the Red Light District which is only a couple minutes away. Close by is a church to which I went simple because I had a free pass with museum card. Also to test if I turn to ashes after going past the doors (I had my doubts). Meh, there are more interesting things to see. Quick circle around and I&rsquo;m out the doors (also don&rsquo;t want to take the chance on turning to ashes, just in case where was a lag in the system).</p>

<p>From tourist kiosks you can buy the tickets to museums/attractions. Depending on what you get it can save you at least a few euros. In my opinion it&rsquo;s worth to check out the options, especially if you know you will be visiting them. Just make sure you have all the information about the ticket. For example if you buy the ticket for Body Works you&rsquo;re allowed to use it only from 4 pm (there are other options). It only works until 6 pm so you would want to there as soon as you&rsquo;re allowed to use the ticket. I was thinking that about an hour should be enough for it so arrived a bit later. That I didn&rsquo;t take into consideration is how big it&rsquo;s and it would be so fun that I will want to read everything. Everyone would have his own definition of fun. As someone who gets hungry watching an autopsy I found this exhibition a lot of fun. You start at the sixth floor and go down until you reach the basement. Every floor has a theme, like bones, muscles, reproduction, sex, etc. The first few floors I was able to explore undisturbed. Then an employer started shadowing me blocking the doors back to the previous floor. Then she started asking if I knew they worked until 6 pm and in the end just plainly suggesting what you might want to pick up the pace. The basement contains the sex theme and if you ever wondered how the act of making love looked from inside this is your chance. I would highly suggest visiting this exhibit, but I think it would depend on how hard your stomach is.</p>

<p>You might be inclined to drive a bike around Amsterdam. I would just suggest simply walking around. In a nice weather it is relaxing. You&rsquo;re able to pay more attention to your surroundings and Amsterdam has a lot of nice places and hidden gems. Just make sure you pay attention and don&rsquo;t stand in goofing around in car/bike road.</p>

<p>During some random walks I found a few rich people houses made museums including free entry with museum card. Some have some pros to them like a nice garden. Others might have some strange things like a church in the attic. In summary it wasn&rsquo;t bad to learn how people lived before we had internet and computers and it was a way to kill some time. That I liked about visiting them is that it hardened my choice of being minimalist as all that to me looked so pointless. You might have already noticed this about me, but after returning back home I&rsquo;m almost put everything I own in the middle of the room and put it on fire. Made a compromise to send everything I don&rsquo;t need to my friends the next day.</p>

<p>The museum card also allowed me to visit a photo gallery and I was pleasantly surprised. Part of the gallery was closed and part of it just tried to sell you something. The thing I liked and was surprised by was that it was having an exhibition by Larry Clark (if you don&rsquo;t know who he is just know that it will be NSFW).</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Amsterdam - Exploring the City](/amsterdam-exploring-city)
* [Amsterdam - Museums & Attractions](/amsterdam-museums-attractions)
* [Amsterdam Dungeon](/amsterdam-dungeon)
* [Amsterdam - More museums & RLD](/asmterdam-museums-rld)
* [Amsterdam - Natura Artis Magistra Zoo](/natura-artis-magistra-zoo)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - Exploring the City (part 3) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-exploring-city"/>
    <updated>2015-07-08T09:07:57+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-exploring-the-city-part-3-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the morning it felt great to have my cup of tea in front of a fleet of ducks. I like water, it&rsquo;s relaxing. As the houseboat required maintenance we moved to hosts' house which was close to city center. It was a nice place. The only problem was that internet connection was down. For someone who requires it for working this wasn&rsquo;t good news. At least the host could hotspot his phone, but the speed of it was as exciting as counting dust falling. I could hardly check my email. After having a birthday breakfast prepared by the host I went out for a random walk around the city. My first destination was to check out NEMO science center. We saw it while taking a taxi ride and it looked interesting. It didn&rsquo;t look that interesting after I found out you have to take the stairs to the top. Was starting to think if I should even bother with it. Well, nothing is easy in life and you need to put some effort if you want something back. Climbing them wasn&rsquo;t as bad as I thought, just the first 10 steps looked terrible. You can see most of the Amsterdam from the roof and it&rsquo;s a nice place to relax (as long as you stay away from kids). I chose a quiet spot and sit down to read Psycho Cybernetics. You can&rsquo;t get the original on kindle and I chose to return without it after a trip.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17333628968" title="10438926_10202278717309911_6209002604154581610_n by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7690/17333628968_eb54ccf813_z.jpg" width="480" height="640" alt="10438926_10202278717309911_6209002604154581610_n"></a></p>

<p>Can&rsquo;t remember exactly which places I visited, but I took a large circle around town. I roughly guessing that during my trips I walk about 10-20 kilometers per day. Of course Amsterdam is a great city to rent a bike and explore it this way, but I don&rsquo;t see a point for that personally. For me I get tired about the same. It&rsquo;s just the question of time (bike takes a bit less) which I had enough, so I chose the transport type I like most &ndash; my legs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16901198423" title="10269094_10202278718189933_2393730023996421613_o by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7797/16901198423_de904fbbc3_z.jpg" width="640" height="452" alt="10269094_10202278718189933_2393730023996421613_o"></a></p>

<p>After returning the host invited to join them to watch a game in a city. Unlike most people think I&rsquo;m not against the sports and if I had enough health or skills I would do them. That I don&rsquo;t understand is the point of watching a bunch of people with the ball. I can find more interesting things to do. Recently someone asked &ldquo;what things?&rdquo; and my answer was &ldquo;You&rsquo;re old enough, use your imagination.&rdquo; But sure, why not, let&rsquo;s try it, who knows maybe I will enjoy it. The game was a nice one, but I could still just watch 2 minute reel the next day and save at least an hour.</p>

<p>The tip time: <em>avoid drinking beer (or a lot of any beverage) in Netherlands</em>. Why? Because you have to pay for the toilet in bars. And no, they don&rsquo;t care that you&rsquo;re a customer. You want to piss &ndash; you pay. As they don&rsquo;t even have normal beer (meaning you can drink as much as you want and you won&rsquo;t get drunk) if you went a little overboard you could end up spending more on WC than on the drinks. Drink responsibly.</p>

<p>After a while we went to a house boat. Amsterdam is beautiful during the night. I don&rsquo;t know about you, but I personally find it funny when people try to hide the usage of drugs. Like if you close yourself in the toilet and I hear *cocaine snorting sounds* like I will be thinking that you&rsquo;re cleaning the toilet. Then four of us went to a club. One high on cocaine, one on ecstasy, one on weed and one (me) had a few beers. And from that I saw, I still had the most fun (and it wasn&rsquo;t a fun night). Before entering we first had to wait until some overdosed girl was taken out. Kids, use drugs responsibly.</p>

<p>You might kind of guess it, but I&rsquo;m not a big fan of clubs. I&rsquo;m not against them or anything, it&rsquo;s just not for me. If it&rsquo;s impossible to have a normal conversation (the one were your only reply is nod then lips stop moving) then the place is too loud. Give me one person who loves to talk (I&rsquo;m better listener than talker), a cup of tea, cozy atmosphere and I will be having the best night of my life. The place was crowded, full of smoke and DJs were so terrible that I wanted to go to them and slap them in the face and just tell them to leave the Spotify playing without messing with controls. One thing I noticed is that I stopped caring about tobacco smokes. Don&rsquo;t like it, it makes me nauseating, but don&rsquo;t care and don&rsquo;t ever want to do that again. Then came 3 AM and I think I know how Cinderella must have felt when midnight came. All the better looking (from outside) ass grinders (girls that grind their asses into anything that moves or doesn&rsquo;t move) in a blink of an eye changed into some alligator monsters. Group or no group, I don&rsquo;t care, I chose not to stay a second longer in there. They looked hungry and I&rsquo;m too old to be grinded into a wall.</p>

<p>The next day I chose to go to Westerpark because it looked like a big splash of green and was close from my position. My suggestion is just to avoid it and better go to Vondelpark. Only the start of it is a real park and the rest is I think some kind off housings (haven&rsquo;t found the entry). You end up walking a side street all the way around without being able to enjoy any greenery. As my new host will be able to check-in me only in the evening we made a deal that I will leave some things at her place so I wouldn&rsquo;t have to walk with them everywhere tomorrow (knowing with how much I travel it&rsquo;s not that big of a deal). Can&rsquo;t remember the exact description but it make me happy thinking about &ldquo;go meet a girl in a red dress.&rdquo; Sometimes silly things make you smile. Went by the Anne Frank house and right away I knew that I won&rsquo;t be visiting it (especially after the host added some more info about it). No way I&rsquo;m standing in that long of a line for something I don&rsquo;t find interesting. I was invited for a cup of tea, we talked and learned about each other. One of many enjoyable conversations we had with the host. Can&rsquo;t remember that I did for the rest of the day.</p>

<p>The next day after waking up and noticing that WiFi is still not available I packed my stuff and left. The host was not home, but I was not going to waste precious hours I could spend working and earning money to pay off this trip. The weather was gray and wet, not enjoyable. I chose to stop at some organic burger place with a big table in the corner (window included). You wouldn&rsquo;t believe how productive you can be after changing the scenery and with a cold beer nearby. Did all my planned work in about an hour surprising myself and my client. Too bad I was charging by an hour. Time for another tip. In Amsterdam you don&rsquo;t need to worry much if you might need WiFi for something. Some places require using some app (skip those), some have it available (you stand in the street doing what you do) and some have the password on their menu. You might need to shop around to find the WiFi you like, but you will find it somewhere if needed.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17519150272" title="10480565_10202281410217232_2518834619728254079_o by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5455/17519150272_a8f301ceda_z.jpg" width="474" height="640" alt="10480565_10202281410217232_2518834619728254079_o"></a></p>

<p>The new place I was staying at was a bit strange, but nice. Third floor, from one window you can see the street and canals. My room was in the attic which has a window to the inner yard. It was quiet except for birds singing (strangely I liked that). Most of the mornings I woke up with sun tickling my naked leg. The architecture I found a bit strange and hard to figure out. Every day I had to watch out not to be killed by circular stairs or low ceilings (I&rsquo;m tall). Also I find it strange that everything is small when Dutch people are tall. I think some great-great-grandfather just went &ldquo;How about we mess up with future generations and build everything small?&rdquo; The host was a very lively French girl. I enjoyed our conversations and dinners together a lot. We became friends during this trip. She found my approach to minimalism interesting. She accepted my suggestion to try it out and simplify her own life by removing material chains. I also gave her many heart attacks (which I found satisfying) as most people are not used to someone who moves around like a ghost.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Amsterdam - Exploring the City](/amsterdam-exploring-city)
* [Amsterdam - Museums & Attractions](/amsterdam-museums-attractions)
* [Amsterdam Dungeon](/amsterdam-dungeon)
* [Amsterdam - More museums & RLD](/asmterdam-museums-rld)
* [Amsterdam - Natura Artis Magistra Zoo](/natura-artis-magistra-zoo)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
