<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Travel | ifdattic]]></title>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/categories/travel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ifdattic.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-02T16:49:18+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://ifdattic.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Marcinkevičius]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - Phone STD &amp; Parks (part 2) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks"/>
    <updated>2015-06-03T09:55:35+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks-part-2-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After taking an inventory of what happened so far decided now was the time to:</p>

<ul>
<li>check where to find the places suggested by the host (shops, restaurants, etc.);</li>
<li>buy the local SIM card for internet;</li>
<li>get something to eat.</li>
</ul>


<p>I was in no hurry to start going through museums and similar places. I was here for two weeks and decided to spend the weekend just exploring the city. Also after I move to another place I will receive the museum card from my host, saving me some money &amp; time.</p>

<p>After a while I went inside one shop which looked like they were selling SIM cards. If you want to imagine the conversation better the merchant was Indian (like Russell Peters said &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t make stereotypes, I see them&rdquo;).</p>

<p>&ldquo;Hi, I would like a local SIM card with a data plan, do you have any?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Hi, yes, it will be 20 € please. What model is your phone?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;The Nexus 5 <em>*confused with a raised eyebrow*</em>, does it make any difference?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;I never had Nexus, I can do Apple, Samsung, Nokia. Here are the instructions how to install it. I don&rsquo;t know if it will work on your phone.&rdquo;</p>

<p>After some haggling we decided to try and if it will work, I will pay. If it will not work he will take the card back and I will not need to pay. Good deal, <em>I have nothing to lose after all, or so I thought</em>. After changing the card and rebooting the phone the language automatically changed to Dutch (without asking me about it), started installing some apps and if you enter the settings (to change the language or enable WiFi) the application would just close down. WTF?!? <em>I wasn&rsquo;t expecting my phone catching an STD</em>. I had doubts about myself, who knows were I might end sticking my USB stick in, but I didn&rsquo;t expect this happening to my phone. Thanked the shop keeper for trying and left without local SIM card.</p>

<p>Continued to keep going down the street as somewhere around here was a park (I love green &amp; blue colors on maps). At the same time trying to figure out how to at least change the language to English. What I found is what if you restart the phone you have about few seconds of browsing the settings app before it&rsquo;s closed. Not an easy task to change something in few seconds when you don&rsquo;t even know where it is. After a while I just gave up as this was unsustainable. Restarting the phone took about a minute and it provides only a few seconds which probably won&rsquo;t be enough. Another problem was what I was kind of lost, the GPS/maps application was in Dutch and without any cache. <em>The easy way would be just to go back, which is boring</em>. After calculating the direction I should move to I continued my travels.</p>

<p>After reaching a place which was close to the boat house stopped for some traditional Dutch pancakes. At first trying to think how to fix the phone. Soon changed that with just drinking my mint tea with honey and enjoying the fresh air. Decided my best choice would be to go back home, try to figure out how to fix my phone or at least to cache the map.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17333602178" title="Traditional Dutch Pancakes by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8879/17333602178_1f965387dc_z.jpg" width="474" height="640" alt="Traditional Dutch Pancakes"></a></p>

<p>The Google wasn&rsquo;t helpful with answers about what I should do. Except for step-by-step instructions where to find the languages. Which wasn&rsquo;t helpful as settings application wasn&rsquo;t working. In the end I was able to fix my phone. Not really sure why or how, but I was glad for settings application to start working allowing me to go back to English language. The fix was kind of simple. Inserted my original SIM card which doesn&rsquo;t work outside my country, but I&rsquo;m guessing the &ldquo;virus&rdquo; figured it was not able to do his thing and just left. Or something along those lines. It&rsquo;s a mystery to me. I was just glad for it to start working the way it&rsquo;s supposed to work. Except for antivirus being in English which I was able to change only after about a month.</p>

<p>Back in full gear went to look for that park again. Small, but nice park. As long as you don&rsquo;t step into any dog shit that is. Decided it&rsquo;s time to visit the Vondelpark park. It was the weekend and streets can get noisy from all the tourists who come to be loud, be stupid, be drunk, be unhappy and be back in 9-to-5 job on Monday. Don&rsquo;t get offended if any of those describe you. <em>I don&rsquo;t have anything against having some fun (choose your own definition)</em> or anything like that, I just don&rsquo;t think that because it&rsquo;s the weekend and you went to another country it allows you to be an idiot. <strong>I know common sense is dead, but try to find it</strong>.</p>

<p>The Vondelpark is wonderful. It&rsquo;s a large area with green zones, water and all kinds of people in it. If the day is sunny &amp; warm it&rsquo;s perfect to just lie down and relax, maybe with a book, maybe without one. It takes a while to walk through whole park, especially if you get lost as roads can sometime get confusing (they are wiggly). It has public toilets, refreshments (you can always bring your own), benches. It should take care of most of your needs. You will also meet some &ldquo;strange people&rdquo;, I call them &ldquo;crackers.&rdquo; Don&rsquo;t know why but this is what comes to my head then I think about them (in the voice of Eddie Griffin). I met three different categories during my two weeks. The first one being friendly ones which talk with you about something and  after a bit asks if maybe you could share some coins. The second one was similar to friendlies except I call them idiots. I try to be positive, but when you tell me about how hard their life is and they have no money for food because he wasted couple hundred euros yesterday in casino. Sorry, this is were I draw the line and walk away. I&rsquo;m not good enough yet to deal with this kind of situations. The third one are the aggressive kind and best to avoid as it wouldn&rsquo;t be surprising if one of them stabbed you (I have good imagination).</p>

<p>Before leaving the park stopped to listen to one guy playing incredible jazz music. Liked it so much that stopped to listen to it while talking with his friends. They were from Chile and damn, their language is beautiful. A bit later two other people stopped to listen to music and join the conversation. After a while a new guy mentioned that if someone wants Marilyn Monroe LSD he has some to sell. I would guess it would be an easy way to spice up my birthday and after listening to Tim Ferriss podcast I sometimes wonder that it would be a positive experience to experiment a little with psychedelic drugs. The thing is that some risks I like to take in the controlled environment. <em>Taking who knows what, with who knows who, who knows were for me personally isn&rsquo;t that comforting or something I couldn&rsquo;t live without</em>.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amsterdam - First Experiences (part 1) - Testing the World and Looking for Home series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-first-experiences"/>
    <updated>2015-05-12T11:35:44+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/amsterdam-first-experiences-part-1-testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>&ldquo;Why are you going to Amsterdam if you don&rsquo;t smoke?&rdquo;</em> A question from my friend before leaving, makes me smile every time I remember it. If you came here looking for some crazy juicy stories from Amsterdam, keep looking. I&rsquo;m sure a lot of (young) people go to Amsterdam exactly for sex, drugs &amp; alcohol. I chose to explore the other side of it: beautiful city, great culture &amp; museums.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t know what the series are about you can read the <a href="/testing-world-series-intro">intro</a>.</p>

<p>A few months before my birthday I was starting to think what I should get myself for it. It&rsquo;s not like I care a lot (any) about my birthday. It&rsquo;s just what most of the time I can remember what is the date so it&rsquo;s easy to assign some crazy gift/event with it (like testing operation table for the first time or quitting my job). The runner was to get a tattoo. I don&rsquo;t like or understand tattoos, but it would be another thing I done in life. Wondering that kind of tattoo? A black dot (probably below my belly button) and if someone would ask what it means (tattoo must have a meaning) the reply would be &ldquo;I dot F&hellip;ing give a S..t&rdquo; (aggressive, but effective). Then I remembered my promise to return to Amsterdam for at least a week. The first time I visited I was acting like some stupid tourist (going through shops, etc.) and it was only for half a day. From the map it looked like a great city with a lot to see. We have a winner!</p>

<p>I spent a lot of time trying to decide what kind of a trip it should be. First was thinking about traveling around whole Netherlands (it happened in a way, but you will read about it at the end). After some calculations decided to just take two weeks off, working as little as possible and just stay all that time in Amsterdam. Tickets purchased, places booked, map marked with places to visit (didn&rsquo;t think about keeping it so can&rsquo;t share it). Only need to wait until the end of June.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/17521426095" title="Packed &amp; ready to go by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/8/7683/17521426095_e7069aa254_z.jpg" width="637" height="640" alt="Packed &amp; ready to go"></a></p>

<p>Few hours later after a strangely pleasant flight (don&rsquo;t like them) was back in Eindhoven. A few years ago I lived in this city for a few weeks through ERASMUS. You can take the bus or the train to the Amsterdam. It costs about the same and it takes about the same amount of time. The bus is near the airport exit, but it looked like you should have a printed ticket for that (maybe someone knows if you can buy the ticket from a driver?) so just decided to use the train. At the same time I would grab something to eat at city center. While reading a cafe menu almost got hit by a car. <em>A great way to start your holidays/trip is on the front hood of a car as an ornament</em>. Maybe I lost my appetite or maybe the menu didn&rsquo;t had anything tasty and decided to try to reach Amsterdam before some other car tried to take a bite out of me.</p>

<p>Before you arrive to Netherlands &ndash; get a lot of € coins, a lot, like at least 20€ worth of coins. Why? You need them to buy the bus/train tickets and no one has any coins. You could pay with a debit/credit card, but I was against that as you get a 2% charge for paying with a card. Also I try to avoid having my card while trying and keep it at the place I&rsquo;m staying. <em>If I loose my wallet with the money in it I just lost my money, I can always get more at the ATM. If I loose my wallet with the card in it I&rsquo;m just left with that I have in cash. Just a safer choice in my opinion</em>. You can buy a ticket from the office with an extra charge. Now that I think about it the price is probably the same in the end.. Still stupid.. Forgot to add that some places accept only cash, some places accept only cards and some places I&rsquo;m not even sure accepts anything. I work with technology, I know it fails. What do you do when you can&rsquo;t accept card payments? Tell everyone to F&hellip; off and close down the shop? Well in short just <strong>know what you will be charged for paying with a card and always check which payment methods are available</strong>.</p>

<p>The trains have a free WiFi allowing you to contact your host about your arrival, search for information or just read the articles. Which I did as the first half part of the trip is boring. The second half starts where the sea should start so it&rsquo;s more interesting to look at the canals and ships. I have planed my way from the train station, but the more I looked at the map the more doubts I had about reaching it. Must be my paranoia, I&rsquo;m sure it will turn around somewhere and I will go to the train station. At least I thought so until the voice over the speakers went &ldquo;This is the last stop, please get out&rdquo;, crap. So, I&rsquo;m in the Schiphol airport. WiFi is not working anymore. Everything is in Dutch and I have no idea which bus goes to the city center. I guess I could always walk to it, it&rsquo;s only one screen away, the same distance as if walking to America. All the thoughts were gone once I found the tour mini-bus which was giving information about how to get to the city and selling the tickets.</p>

<p>While studying the map provided with the ticket I was starting to get doubts again about reaching the train station (<em>it can be confusing until you get your bearings around any new city</em>). Decided to just risk it and get out at what looked the closest stop to the place of my stay. Made the right choice and got out on the street I needed. The sun was shining and atmosphere was refreshing. It&rsquo;s nice to be back in Amsterdam, this city does have something special.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16901067473" title="Under attack by ducks! by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://c2.staticflickr.com/6/5329/16901067473_b3f0ea1c0c_z.jpg" width="474" height="640" alt="Under attack by ducks!"></a></p>

<p>That I love about traveling and booking your places through airbnb is what you can try some interesting houses without having to make a long term commitment. My first house &ndash; a house boat. Even if it&rsquo;s only for one day (it had some maintenance issues) it&rsquo;s a new experience. Somehow I missed checking the rest of the photos of my host and was expecting some tall guy. The door opens and I see someone who looks like Mr. Chow from Hangover movie, even his voice was similar. &ldquo;You&rsquo;re Andrew? Hi, you look different than in your photo. Come in, sorry, I&rsquo;m still hangover from yesterday, come in come in.&rdquo; After all the formalities of explaining rules and suggestions, I looked around and took a big breath of air overflowed with excitement. It&rsquo;s strange when you look out the window and water is like only a hands length away and when a big fleet of ducks start swimming your way for their payment of food. Can&rsquo;t even remember it without smiling. Another strange thing is tourists swimming in boats past your window, especially when you&rsquo;re peeing.</p>

<p>To be continued&hellip;</p>

<p>Read the rest of the series:</p>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Testing the World and Looking for Home - Intro to series]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/testing-world-series-intro"/>
    <updated>2015-05-03T08:44:47+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/testing-the-world-and-looking-for-home-intro-to-series</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/ifdattic/16728375584" title="Testing the World and Looking for Home - Intro to series by Andrew Marcinkevičius, on Flickr"><img src="https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7745/16728375584_736018f7be_c.jpg" width="800" height="400" alt="Testing the World and Looking for Home - Intro to series"></a></p>

<p>I have a &ldquo;strange&rdquo; approach / thinking about everything. I <strong>never understood putting imaginary walls like countries / borders / nationality / etc.</strong> To me it always looked strange. <em>Why someone would be willing to cram in himself into some imaginary box</em>. Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, I understand what culture, country you grew up, nationality defines you and could have a high impact on how you might react to things. But my answer to &ldquo;Where are you from?&rdquo; is &ldquo;From Earth, last time I checked?&rdquo; (I have some doubts, but lets leave it at that). I&rsquo;m also not someone who will just pack his backpack and would go on the round the world trip (at least not yet). Damn, about a year ago, listening to someone&rsquo;s latest trip would suck out the energy from me.</p>

<p><strong>Staying in another country in my opinion is something you have to do as soon as possible</strong>. No matter how much you read, it won&rsquo;t <em>expand your thinking</em> as mush as surrounding yourself with a different culture &amp; environment. Today, when you have so much opportunities to travel, <em>it&rsquo;s something you can&rsquo;t miss out on</em>.</p>

<p>As a digital nomad I have a great opportunity to travel as long as I have my laptop and internet connection. Even internet is not a requirement. My current approach is to visit the country for a few weeks or months, learn about the culture and life in that country and return to my &ldquo;base of operations&rdquo; country. A lot of people would suggest that you should stay 3 months in one place or at least a month, and I agree with you, but I also found that for me 2 weeks is great. It allows enough time to get a feel for a place, but it&rsquo;s not that long in case you won&rsquo;t like it. My &ldquo;base of operations&rdquo; country is the one I grew up and quite used up to. But it&rsquo;s not the country I would like to live for the rest of my life. Before, I used to hate it. As I traveled more and my thinking expanded the thinking about it changed and just like any country it has pros and cons. One of the pros is that it&rsquo;s relatively cheap to live in, allowing to save that money for the next trip.</p>

<p><strong>So what is my main reason for traveling? It&rsquo;s to find a place which I could call my home</strong>. <em>You know what feeling where thinking about some place makes you warm inside and you can&rsquo;t wait to return to it</em>. Some might say the home is the place which you make, and you would probably be right, but as long as I&rsquo;m able I will first try to find that place. At least failing to find that place would help me into understanding what I&rsquo;m really looking for.</p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t done a lot of traveling yet. But thought that some might find it useful to learn what I learned through my travels. <strong>The purpose of the series is to share what I liked, disliked and general tips about places visited</strong>. <em>It&rsquo;s always good to be wise and learn from other people mistakes, but never forget to make your own</em>.</p>

<p><strong>Below you will find the links to all the articles in the series, happy reading:</strong></p>

<h2>Amsterdam, Netherlands [2014]</h2>

<p>* [Amsterdam - First Experiences](/amsterdam-first-experiences)
* [Amsterdam - Phone STD & Parks](/amsterdam-phone-std-and-parks)
* [Photo album](http://bit.ly/1IvAlYb)
* to be continued...
</p>

<h2>Barcelona / Seville / Madrid, Spain [2014]</h2>

<p>* Intro
* to be continued...
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Digital Nomad One Backpack Packing for 6 Weeks Trip (Video)]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/one-backpack-packing"/>
    <updated>2015-03-16T19:02:17+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/digital-nomad-one-backpack-packing-for-6-weeks-trip-video</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In 2014 I took the 6 weeks trip to Spain. Forgot to record a video of packing my backpack at that moment. After talking with other digital nomads about packing thought that it might be really fun to try recording a video of it. This is the first time I did something like it, so feedback would be appreciated. Here&rsquo;s the video:</p>

<iframe width="732" height="412" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xH3QEfMXjh0?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>For the list of gear mentioned in the video check the <a href="https://bitly.com/bundles/ifdattic/1#">bitly collection</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ready to travel? Use the following tips]]></title>
    <link href="http://ifdattic.com/ready-to-travel-use-the-following-tips"/>
    <updated>2014-08-06T10:15:37+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://ifdattic.com/ready-to-travel-use-the-following-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m not someone who backpacked around the world for years (maybe some day). Actually not that long ago I didn&rsquo;t even like traveling, just listening to someone who returned from somewhere made me tired. But some time in spring of 2014, I just got the itch of needing to travel. As a lazy person who is always looking for ways to optimize and simplify his life, I decided to share some tips which I wish I knew before I started traveling or just giving them to someone who is about to pop his cherry. Tips are in no particular order.</p>

<p>You can jump to any particular tip:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="#travel-lightly">Travel lightly</a></li>
<li><a href="#duffel">Get a convertible duffel bag</a></li>
<li><a href="#board-last">Be among the last people in the plane</a></li>
<li><a href="#use-headphones">Use in-ear headphones</a></li>
<li><a href="#prepare-smartphone">Prepare your smart phone</a></li>
<li><a href="#dont-plan-adapt">Don&rsquo;t plan, adapt</a></li>
<li><a href="#use-common-sense">Use common sense</a></li>
<li><a href="#use-zip-trash-bags">Use zip lock and trash bags</a></li>
<li><a href="#eat-nuts">Eat macadamia nuts</a></li>
<li><a href="#check-alarm">Check your alarm five times</a></li>
<li><a href="#optimize-medkit">Optimize your med-kit</a></li>
<li><a href="#lodgings">Learn about your lodgings</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Travel lightly <a name="travel-lightly"></a></h2>

<p>Lightly is the relative term so it might be a backpack or a suitcase, but if you can just travel with medium backpack (42x32x25 cm). Don&rsquo;t be one of those travelers who drags a bunch of suitcases just for a weekend get away. You have no idea how refreshing it is when you can just move through the airport without waiting in some pointless lines. Or moving through the busy street without disturbing anyone or being disturbed. Most of the time you can get by without a lot of things and if you really need something you can always buy it.</p>

<h2>Get a convertible duffel bag <a name="duffel"></a></h2>

<p>I personally use <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/Kiva-Convertible-Duffel-Bag-Ruby/dp/B002AA7LCI">Kiva Convertible Duffel Bag</a>, but you can get something similar. At first I had my doubts about it, in theory it sounded like a great product, but I wasn&rsquo;t sure I will be using it in practice. Now I love it, and will probably be buying a couple more. Even if you travel with one backpack, which doesn&rsquo;t weight much it is probably quite full and just makes you feel rigid. Just fill your duffel bag with stuff from it and your comfort level will improve a lot.</p>

<h2>Be among the last people in the plane <a name="board-last"></a></h2>

<p>Don&rsquo;t be one of those who tries to cut the line to get into the plane. You won&rsquo;t fly out sooner than me, so just relax. Most will say it&rsquo;s just to get a better seat, well I&rsquo;m sorry, but it&rsquo;s a lie. You won&rsquo;t get a better seat by boarding earlier. If it&rsquo;s your first time flying, well OK, you might want to get a window seat, but believe me it&rsquo;s not so interesting either way. Also from my experience I found that being among the last people in, gives you much better choices for where to sit (also the <a href="http://blog.bufferapp.com/6-powerful-psychological-effects-that-explain-how-humans-tick">research</a> shows what it&rsquo;s better to have less choices). The important part is to enter through the front of the plane. After that you can just walk down the aisle and process your choices (e.g., a crying kid too close, teenagers, etc.) and take one which you think will be enjoyable or least bothersome. If you look like someone who might start carrying people under his arms in emergency (never was in a crashing plane so not sure about it) you might get upgraded to the emergency exit seat. Also for someone who &ldquo;has no ass&rdquo; and sitting for long periods of time becomes painful, I want to be on my legs for as long as I can.</p>

<h2>Use in-ear headphones <a name="use-headphones"></a></h2>

<p>First, because you can remove the noise everyone is making and exchange it with some music you like or a good audio book. I don&rsquo;t know about you, but listening for hours of kids crying to me doesn&rsquo;t sound like a good time. Second, I hate flying mostly because it messes with my ears. I noticed that in-ear headphones helps with it. Earbuds isn&rsquo;t bad either, in-ear headphones is just more comfortable for me. Over the ear headphones are useless and cumbersome. Another tip for helping with pressure messing with your ears is to squeeze your nose shut with your fingers and swallow. I was suggested this when I was jumping with a parachute (too late), but I did it on the couple of flights and it helped a lot. Just don&rsquo;t overdo it, use your gut and do it when you feel it&rsquo;s needed.</p>

<h2>Prepare your smart phone <a name="prepare-smartphone"></a></h2>

<p>Best choice would be to get a local sim card with a data plan. Doesn&rsquo;t always work. At least after I tried to put a local sim card in Netherlands it felt like my phone got an STD: it changed language everywhere to Dutch and everything stopped working. Didn&rsquo;t feel like giving it a second try. The most important thing to do is while you&rsquo;re connected to Internet just cache the area you will be visiting in Google Maps. Your GPS will work fine without the Internet and you won&rsquo;t need to fight with a paper map trying to figure out where you are. Just walk in the direction you want and from time to time check you position to correct your direction. Getting lost is just seeing more things than you planned and this way you will always have pointers how to get back to a familiar ground. You can also download a note with an information of where you&rsquo;re staying, a screen shot of a map (helped after trying to put local sim card) or anything else you might need.</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t plan, adapt <a name="dont-plan-adapt"></a></h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m not saying you shouldn&rsquo;t plan your trip, but don&rsquo;t overdo it and better be ready to adapt. Like googling <em>&ldquo;how to get from point A to point B&rdquo;</em> or <em>&ldquo;what to do in point C&rdquo;</em> is fine and useful. <em>&ldquo;On 2 pm I will be in point A, in 10 minutes the train will arrive, travel to point B for an hour, &hellip;&rdquo;</em> not so much.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s an example from my trip to Amsterdam. The end of the trip was supposed to be simple: travel with a train from Amsterdam to Eindhoven for 1.5 hours, sleep, fly back home. The real trip had much more steps. After buying the train ticket some kind of power failure happened which closed the whole Amsterdam-Eindhoven line. Had to travel to Rotterdam. After about 1.5 hours from all the information I had noticed it won&rsquo;t be taking me to the city center and will be going to the wrong direction. Had to make a call to get out (don&rsquo;t know if it was the correct call or not, just had to adapt to a situation to the best of my knowledge). Got out in suburbs at least 10 kilometers away from train station. As a bonus had to reach the train station in about 30 minutes (as the next train will be in another 30 minutes and the trip is longer). This is the great example why you should travel lightly. With a few more hick ups along the way, finally got in the train which was traveling for 1.5 hours to Eindhoven. From train station to the place I booked for the night was about 8 minutes of walking. After 7 meters of walking it started to drip. Put the jacket on just in case. After 3 meters the storm started with rain pouring like the sky was drowning. Arrived to my host drenched in water. Only after a shower I felt like human again and after working for a bit I felt like I&rsquo;m back in control. So it wasn&rsquo;t surprising when my first thought after I was suggested emergency exit seat my first thought was &ldquo;Great, another detour. At least I will have some legroom until we crash&rdquo;. Unfortunately, had a very nice flight with lots of turbulence and song lyrics <em>&ldquo;I&rsquo;m falling, I&rsquo;m falling fast&rdquo;</em> while landing. However, I wouldn&rsquo;t change this for anything as it showed me how I can react to un-expected situations (What doesn&rsquo;t kill you makes you stronger). Just sometimes you have enough to stop caring about adventure and all you can think of is a destination.</p>

<h2>Use common sense <a name="use-common-sense"></a></h2>

<p>If you walk around with your phone or wallet half falling of your ass pocket, don&rsquo;t be surprised when it will get stolen or lost. You might look like a tourist (especially if you&rsquo;re dragging a bunch of luggage around) making you an easier target, but all the problems might as well happen in the country you live. Just use some common sense and you should minimize your chances of being robbed or something like it happening to you. Keep your valuables in front pockets or somewhere where it is not so easy to reach. Get a padlock for your backpack, it won&rsquo;t do any good, but will make you mind feel safer thinking it will be harder for someone to get into your backpack (placebo effect). Don&rsquo;t flash around all the expensive toys you have. And if someone comes to you and asks if they could use your phone just say &ldquo;No&rdquo; and get ready to fight.</p>

<h2>Use zip lock and trash bags <a name="use-zip-trash-bags"></a></h2>

<p>Put your chargers into one of them, small medkit/toiletries in a different one and have a few spare bags (they take almost no space/weight). Not only it helps with organization, but it might also save your things from getting destroyed, if for example you get in a rain storm.</p>

<h2>Eat macadamia nuts <a name="eat-nuts"></a></h2>

<p>They are not cheap, they take space, they are heavy (all points relative), but they will keep you going until you could put a steak or some other nice meal in your stomach. A couple of them will keep you going for a few hours and won&rsquo;t make you crash like some crappy carbs filled snacks you would put in yourself otherwise.</p>

<h2>Check your alarm five times <a name="check-alarm"></a></h2>

<p>Learn from my mistakes and make sure your alarm is set correctly as you really DON&rsquo;T want to miss your flight.</p>

<p><img class="<a" src="href="https://googledrive.com/host/0B3f3EKRXYPx4dUxwcTdSUk0tU0U/content/images/check-your-alarm-five-times.jpg">https://googledrive.com/host/0B3f3EKRXYPx4dUxwcTdSUk0tU0U/content/images/check-your-alarm-five-times.jpg</a>" title="&lsquo;&rsquo; &lsquo;Screenshot of failed alarm&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>If you learn it the hard way just like I did (I had to learn this lesson sooner or later), please see <a href="#dont-plan-adapt">Don&rsquo;t plan, adapt</a>.</p>

<p>And if you&rsquo;re trying to stay away from bad habits, like smoking or drinking, the urges for them will be much higher at this point. It&rsquo;s the perfect situation to have a smoke or a beer. Just acknowledge the urges and stay strong, they won&rsquo;t help at this point (at least I can&rsquo;t imagine how they might help at this point).</p>

<p>Smile and enjoy an expensive story :)</p>

<h2>Optimize your med-kit <a name="optimize-medkit"></a></h2>

<p>This will be different for everyone. Don&rsquo;t pack half of your backpack with drugs because you might need it if something almost impossible will happen. You probably don&rsquo;t want to leave some medication that is important for you either.</p>

<p>A good test that I will be using from now: if pharmacies are closed and will only open in the morning, could I survive over the night?</p>

<p>A few personal examples. Lets say, I get a terrible head ache and have no painkillers. Even if I had to spend time until morning rolled in the ball, it&rsquo;s still more of an inconvenience than a problem. There are also natural ways to help with it and after a couple hours of sleep it might even pass away. So pain killers would be useful to have, but not very important.</p>

<p>On the other side I have problems with my nose being blocked which, when trying to sleep leads to grasping for every molecule of air you can get in your lungs. There are some long term fixes which can lessen this issue. A short term fix also exists, but I try to avoid it as even the doctors suggest to avoid it. So for the trip to Spain I packed only the long term fix and it would have been enough, unfortunately, I got a cold and situation worsened leaving long term fix useless. Also, there is nothing I could do naturally to improve the situation (have enough problems with sleeping without having to do it while standing). After spending hours trying to fall asleep, decided to stop this torture and rather go for days without sleep, at least this way I won&rsquo;t <a href="#check-alarm">oversleep my flight</a>. Next time I will make damn sure I packed the short term fix as even an hour without it is one hour too much.</p>

<p>Pack everything you wouldn&rsquo;t want to be an hour(s) without. If you have free space, pack that might be helpful to shorten the wait time and for everything else just wait it over.</p>

<h2>Learn about your lodgings <a name="lodgings"></a></h2>

<p>If you know where you will be staying (for example by booking through <a href="https://www.airbnb.com">airbnb</a>) always ask about what is important for you. Don&rsquo;t assume things just from photos or description, always ask before booking.</p>

<p>As a digital nomad I need good (even poor works) internet connection to be able to work and earn money for financing my trips. What I don&rsquo;t want to hear during it is: <em>&ldquo;My internet connection isn&rsquo;t working, it will be fixed on Monday (which is after I check out).&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Also from now on I ask if any smoking is being done inside (including shared space). As for someone who stopped smoking, I find it nauseating when I have to walk through smoked area (or even worse, it starts getting inside my room).</p>

<p>Even if something important for you is written in big letters, ask, don&rsquo;t assume.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t the end of the list as I&rsquo;m sure it will be updated once I get more travel experience. But these are the tips I wish I knew about before having my first trip.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
